hey team Sid here with devops directive
and welcome to this complete kubernetes
course I've been wanting to build out
this course for a few years now and
finally found the time to dedicate to
doing so properly this course is for
software Engineers who want to level up
their expertise and add kubernetes to
their tool B of devops and
infrastructure skills over the next few
hours we're going to go from beginner to
Pro learning the fundamentals of
kubernetes before building out a robust
application platform deploying a
representative demo application to
multiple environments also while you're
probably watching this video on YouTube
the video is just one component of the
course there's also a companion GitHub
repo containing all of the code samples
so you can follow along each lesson has
a written module that you can view over
at courses. devops directive. comom and
there's a Discord Community where you
can join to interact with other
community members and ask questions if
anything isn't clear or if you get stuck
along the way I've invested around 150
hours into designing and building out
this course and I'm providing it to you
free of charge because I want to ensure
that this information is accessible to
everyone who wants it if you find Value
in the course and want to support me in
building out this kind of content
there's a few ways you can help first
like the video on YouTube and star the
repo on GitHub these are both completely
free and will help more people discover
and benefit from the content that being
said I can't pay for my groceries with
YouTube likes and GitHub Stars so if you
do want to support financially you can
do so via GitHub sponsors or buy me a
coffee both of which will be linked in
the description
okay that's enough Preamble let's get
into it throughout the course uh we'll
be switching back and forth between
covering Theory uh using diagrams and
visuals and then jumping into our code
editor and interacting with kubernetes
clusters directly deploying resources
inspecting them learning how to deploy
and manage applications on top of
kubernetes there are a handful of
prerequisites that will help you
immensely as you follow along in this
course the first of which is some
familiarity with web applications the
example applications that we use in this
course are built in JavaScript go and
python so if you have familiarity with
at least one of those that will be super
helpful the second one is knowing some
basic shell commands and being
comfortable to navigate around within a
Linux shell as we build and debug our
applications this will come in super
handy the third one is some basic Cloud
infrastructure knowledge so we're going
to mostly be working with managed
kubernetes clusters and I'll talk about
what that means in a later lesson but
being able to go to a cloud provider
create account and provision some
resources will help you to understand
what we do when we set up those clusters
and how to do so effectively finally I'm
assuming that you have intermediate
level containerization knowledge now if
you're lacking this I do have a whole
course covering Docker and containers
that will get you far beyond the
expected Baseline here so I would
suggest you go check that out but if you
have these four things will make
learning kubernetes much much easier now
I've broken the course down into two
major sections in the first section
we'll be doing a little bit more of the
theory component we'll be learning the
motivation and history behind kubernetes
how kubernetes itself works and what the
system components do we'll set up our
development system with all of the
necessary tooling and dependencies that
we're going to use and then we'll
provision both a local cluster as well
as two Cloud clusters and any of those
three options are perfectly fine for
following along with the demos but I
wanted to give people options for the
cloud providers of their choice or they
don't want to have to create and manage
a remote cluster there is an option to
run entirely on your own
system we'll then dive into the built-in
resource types that come out of the box
with kubernetes these are the building
blocks upon which you're going to build
your applications and finally in part
one we'll wrap up by covering a tool
called Helm which is a way to package
and bundle your applications that is
very popular in the cloud native
ecosystem and is often how you will
consume thirdparty applications that you
install into your clusters in part two
we're going to go really Hands-On and
learn how to take those building blocks
that we covered in part one and using a
representative demo application we're
going to first showcase what that
application is we're going to deploy it
onto kubernetes using the built-in
kubernetes resource types we're going to
talk about how people are extending
those buil-in Resources with custom
resources of their own we're going to
deploy a lot of third party tools to
help enhance our experience working with
the Clusters we're going to examine a
couple of challenges with the developer
experience in kubernetes and how to
improve upon those we're going to learn
how to debug broken applications within
kubernetes and then we're going to take
those skills and learn how to deploy
them to multiple environments so in the
real world you're not just going to have
one cluster you're probably going to
have a staging cluster and a production
cluster maybe many more clusters and so
being able to take a configuration and
build it out in such a way that you can
reuse it across those environments is
super
critical we're going to talk about
cluster and node upgrade so kubernetes
itself is evolving and releasing new
versions every quarter we need to be
able to upgrade onto those both for
taking advantage of new features but
also with staying up to date with the
latest security patches we'll talk about
how to automate our continuous
integration and continuous delivery how
we can take changes to our codebase and
get them deployed into kubernetes
automatically and quickly and then we're
going to talk about Concepts that were
out of scope for this course but you
might want to investigate moving forward
I mentioned the demo application a few
times I just want to highlight here what
it is so that you have an expectation of
the type of thing that we're going to be
building out it uses a react front end
so that's the client application that
you're going to run in your browser it
then has two different API
implementations and these apis are super
minimal they have a health check
endpoint and they have a root endpoint
that returns two things it Returns the
current time uh as well as the number of
times that that endpoint has been called
we store the information about those
connections so that we can know how many
times it's been called in a postgres
database and then we also have a python
application that just runs in a loop and
calls those apis over and over to
generate some sort of
load this is quite familiar to the demo
application that we used in the docker
course the new components here are the
python load generator as well as in the
docker course
we didn't store anything in the postgis
database we were just getting that time
stamp this time every time we make a
call to either of these apis we store a
row in a table in that database before
we start working with kubernetes it's
useful to take a look back and try to
understand some of the history and
motivation behind why a system like
kubernetes even exists if we roll the
clock back to the 2000s there was no
kubernetes there was no Cloud if you
were deploying your applications to the
internet uh you needed to do so
on premises meaning you're going to have
servers that you own and operate within
a data center or perhaps you are hosting
your servers within a shared facility
where someone else is taking care of the
power and HVAC and facility
infrastructure and you're operating your
servers within that location companies
would generally have teams of system
administrators to handle provisioning
and managing all of these fleets of
servers there was a lot of Toil and
effort that would go into doing so you
were operating primarily in a bare metal
context and so by that I mean you're
running your applications directly on
the hardware without a layer of
virtualization between the hardware and
your application
stack because of the complexities of
provisioning and managing these servers
it was not practical to operate in a
with a microservice architecture
monoliths were pretty much the only
practical way to go because it greatly
simplified the operational overhead of
dealing with this Hardware the tooling
was relatively immature would often have
tons of homegrown tooling for monitoring
your application lots of sort of bash
script and and glue code and Powershell
tyeing everything together and so this
is what the world looked like in the
2000s for deploying your applications
now in the 2010s uh the cloud has
emerged and has sort of shifted the
Paradigm in terms of now virtual
machines can be created and destroyed in
a matter of minutes uh and so this
allows you to approach your operation
slightly differently you can deploy a
new VM uh very quickly rather than
needing to physically purchase a server
and install it in a data center along
with this a lot of the tooling around
configuration management for these
systems things like puppet and Chef have
started to come into popularity and
allow you to much more much more easily
and programmatically configure a fleet
of servers you're still doing some
things manually for example if you have
a number of different applications that
need to go onto a set of VMS you're
still doing a manual bin packing meaning
kind of plank Tetris with the resources
required to fit your applications into
the virtual machines in an intelligent
way the tooling is continuing to improve
uh and it makes managing a larger set of
applications practical so you're able to
look at different architectures uh such
as microservices and manage them in a in
a more practical manner however managing
large numbers of cloud resources is
still a challenge if we move forward
into the last few years containers have
really become the deao standard for
deploying applications and workload
orchestrators such as kubernetes are
enabling operators to treat clusters of
machines as a single
resource these types of systems provide
a number of utilities and interfaces to
address common challenges with operating
applications things like automatic and
efficient scheduling across different
instances so rather than picking and
choosing oh this application and these
two applications need to fit on this ver
machine instead you can provide a
specification to the system about how
much CPU and memory each application
requires and allow it to figure out the
proper scheduling onto each different uh
machine things like automated health
checks to ensure that if an application
gets into an unhealthy state it will be
removed and replaced automatically
service Discovery so how your
applications can find and talk to each
other over the network many of these
workload orchestrators will contain
mechanisms for doing this right out of
the box including kubernetes
configuration management now rather than
needing to configure the host itself
much of that configuration is moved into
the orchestrator layers so you're
defining all of the ways that your
application needs to be configured and
deploying that alongside your
application as part of its config the
ability to automatically scale Up and
Down based on demand mechanisms to
easily provision and manage persistent
storage to go alongside your application
and finally how you can configure
networking across your different
applications running within one of these
systems kubernetes itself evolved from
earlier work within Google uh and their
workload orchestrator named Borg as you
can see here this is an architecture
diagram showing how things worked
internally at Google and they decided to
take many of the ideas that they had
built and matured for their internal
systems and make a huge bet in terms of
building out this open source system uh
as a differentiator for them in the
cloud world as they wanted to grow
Google Cloud platform they started the
kubernetes project and brought in many
other companies from across the industry
and have continued to evolve and build
kubernetes such that it has become such
a Powerhouse in the cloud deployment
space if you want to learn more about
the history there and there's a number
of really interesting aspects of why
Google decided to open source kubernetes
what the BET was that they were making
Honeypot has made this two-part
documentary where they interview experts
and key people from throughout
kubernetes history and so I would
definitely recommend watching these two
videos it will give you a great
historical context for where kubernetes
came from and how it got to where it is
today now that we have a grounding in
the historical context of kubernetes and
the types of challenges that it's
helping to solve let's take a look at
the system components and the
architecture of kubernetes itself to
understand how those components play
together and form the system there's a
few terms that are very important to
understand as a foundation uh those four
terms are cluster node control plane and
data plane so in this diagram I've laid
out what those actually are the cluster
is the set of resources that make up the
kubernetes system uh those will be
comprised of individual nodes so each
node is a server that it could be a
virtual machine or a bare metal system
uh that is interconnected to form this
kubernetes cluster those nodes are going
to be broken across two groups primarily
uh the first one is called the control
plane and this is where all of the
system components run so the components
that comprise the kubernetes system
itself will run on the control
plane and then the data plane is where
our enduser applications so if I'm
building a system that's deployed to
kubernetes those applications are going
to run on these worker nodes you can
host a sing a cluster in a single node
where the control plane and the data
plane are just one however in most
production systems you'll have a
separate control plane likely with three
or more nodes and then you'll have a
data plane with as many nodes as you
need to host your applications I've
taken that same diagram and you can see
we've split between control plane and
data plane and added the system
components that make up kubernetes the
blue icons are the kubernetes system
components and then you can see I've
added uh a workload and another workload
uh those are the end user applications
finally I've added a cloud provider API
because often times you're deploying
your cluster onto a cloud and there's
interactions there between the system
and the cloud provider let's walk
through each of these components in turn
and describe briefly what they do the
first one at the top here is the cloud
controller manager this is the interface
between kubernetes and the cloud
provider this is where Logic for
resources that live at that boundary are
going to happen for example if you need
to provision a load balancer on the
cloud provider there's going to be API
calls that the cluster makes to the
cloud API or any other resources uh that
need to be provisioned outside of the
cluster within the cloud provider are
going to live there the next component
labeled cm is the controller manager
this runs all of the various controllers
that regulate the state of the cluster
kubernetes is based on this idea of a
control Loop where you have a set of
applications that are running and
looking at some State and making sure
that that desired State matches the
actual state of the world and the
controller manager is what manages all
of those controllers such that they can
do their job and make sure that the
actual State matches the desired State
the next one down is is the API so this
is the kubernetes API itself this is how
you actually interact with the
kubernetes cluster you make API calls to
this API and then it will in turn make
calls to the other various components as
needed to carry out the actions that
you're requesting next up is etcd uh
this is the data store that kubernetes
uses to manage all of the resources that
you deploy to it it is a highly
available key value store that contains
information about all of the resources
deployed into the cluster and ensures
data consistency across all the
different nodes the last component here
shown on the control plane is the
scheduler so the schedule's job is to
assign pods to new nodes based on their
current usage so when you define a
workload for kubernetes you can tell it
how much CPU and memory that workload
requires the scheduler can then look at
the set of nodes available and which one
would make the best fit based on the
available resources now there's two
kubernetes system components that live
on the worker nodes as well uh and these
are the cuet and the cube proxy the cuet
is the component which is responsible to
actually uh spawn and manage the
workloads themselves it also performs
the health checking of the application
and relays that information back to the
API server on the control plane cube
proxy is responsible for setting up and
maintaining the networking between the
different workloads uh so so it sets up
the uh rules within IP tables for
example to sure that the workloads can
communicate based on how youve set up
the configuration now not every cluster
is going to leverage Q proxy there are
some newer uh networking plugins that
don't use Q proxy and instead use
different mechanisms for this but most
clusters that you use will have q proxy
there to handle the networking while
it's useful to understand what all these
system components do uh in the context
of this course we're focused more so on
the workloads that we're deploying onto
kubernetes and how to use an existing
kubernetes cluster rather than
administering the cluster itself many
Cloud providers have hosted or managed
clusters that hide most of this
complexity from us and provide us with
access to that kubernetes API server and
we're able to consume that kubernetes
API to deploy our applications without
having to get into the nitty-gritty of
all of these system components that
frequently I provide it so that you
understand what the components are doing
behind the scenes but mostly in the
context of this course we're going to be
focused on the applications that we
deploy onto the data plane onto those
worker nodes now there's also three
standard interfaces that kubernetes uses
to handle the container runtime uh
container networking and container
storage these allow for a much more
modular system where you can have a base
kubernetes cluster and then use
different implementations of these
standard interfaces to allow an
individual company or organization to to
iterate more quickly on one specific
component of the stack and so there's
many different implementations of the
cni of the CRI or of the CSI and so we
can pick and choose which
implementations fit our needs uh and
swap them out to achieve new
functionality or better performance and
so this is a really key aspect of the
kubernetes ecosystem where much of this
used to be included in the full
kubernetes deployment itself these
pieces have been moved out of the core
of kubernetes such that we can have a
pluggable implementation and innovate on
one domain independent of the rest of
the project the CRI or the container
runtime interface is the standard
interface that kubernetes uses to
execute and run container processes
within the system the two most popular
container run times these days for
kubernets clusters are container D and
cryo container D is certainly the most
popular historic Al Docker was used as
the container runtime but it had a
slightly its interface was slightly
different than the official CRI
interface and so there was this
component called Docker shim that used
to exist and in kubernetes 1.20 uh
kubernetes removed Docker shim and so
Docker can no longer be used as the
container runtime because it's not
compatible with that CRI interface and
so from then on container D and cryo are
now the the more popular choices there
the cni or the container Network networ
interface defines how networking should
be set up for the containers that are
running within kubernetes there are many
different implementations of the cni uh
including a number that are listed here
some are cloud provider specific so if
you're working on Amazon you may want to
use the Amazon VPC cni because it
integrates well with their virtual
private Cloud uh offering if you're on
Azure and Google similarly they have
their own cni implementations there are
also a number of popular projects such
as Calico flannel or psyllium that
implement this as well I mentioned Cube
proxy earlier not all of these cni
implementations use Cube proxy something
like psyllium uses a technology called
ebpf uh to eliminate the need for cube
proxy and instead manage the networking
at the kernel layer the CSI uh is a
standard interface by which we can
provide storage two containers this
interface is used for a variety of
purposes the most obvious one is to
provide durable persistent storage to a
workload running in kubernetes these
drivers often times interact with a
cloud provider to use their underlying
block storage implementations such as
EBS for Amazon or compute engine
persistent discs for Google cloud and by
using this specific CSI driver
kubernetes is able to interact with that
cloud provider and provision and manage
those persistant discs there are also
other use cases for the CSI driver where
you can use
this driver to provide information or
configuration to a container at runtime
for example CT manager which is a tool
for provisioning uh TLS certificates can
use the Cs the container storage
interface to load a certificate at
runtime into the file system of the
container
automatically or The Secret store CSI
driver enables you to load sensitive
information into the file system at
runtime as well while we're focusing on
kubernetes and looking at a handful of
projects associated with kubernetes the
cloud native ecosystem is massive and in
particular the cloud native compute
Foundation has a program by which they
assess and manage the maturity of
different projects here I have the what
is known as the cncf landscape and as
you can see there are just a swath of
different projects at various levels
some are at the graduated level so those
are quite mature and are often being
used in production across industry there
are others that at the incubating stage
which maybe are a bit less mature but
are upand cominging projects in the
space and so as you start to work with
kubernetes and need functionality to
provide specific capabilities definitely
check out the cncf landscape and see if
there is tooling that might provide the
capabilities that you need okay the time
has come for us to set up our local
development systems and provision the
kubernetes Clusters that we're going to
be using throughout the course for the
demo and lab sections there are a number
of different tools that we're going to
use and within the GitHub repo for the
course I've provided a configuration
that will allow us to install most of
these automatically we're going to
install a couple manually and then use a
tool called devbox to install the rest
of the dependencies that will ensure
that you have all of the dependencies
available and are using a version that
is compatible with the one that I'm
using in this
filming the first dependency that we're
going to install is Docker desktop this
one I suggest that you go to the docs at
docs. do.com Docker and follow the
instructions for your specific operating
system it will guide you through the
installation process and should be
relatively
straightforward the second tool that
we're going to install manually is
something called devbox now devbox is
essentially a wrapper around a
technology called NYX NYX is essentially
a package manager that provides access
to a number of different tools and
allows you to configure a reproducible
installation however the learning curve
for NYX is notoriously difficult uh and
devbox provides a really nice wrapper
around it that makes it much easier to
get started
with if you go to the jifi website and
look at the docs for devbox there's a
quick start there that will provide you
the commands you need to run for your
specific system if you're on Mac or
Linux it should work directly if you're
using Windows I would suggest that you
use WSL so that you have a Linux
environment to work
with jumping over to the companion repo
for the course and as you can see at the
top level we have this devbox do Json
and devbox do loock file the devbox Json
file contains a listing of all the
different CLI tools that we're going to
install via
devbox and then the devbox do loock file
contains the specific versions so that
you will be guaranteed to get the exact
version that I'm using and you won't
have any incompatibilities because of
different versions the way that devbox
installed these is into an isolated
environment on your system and sets up
your environment path variables such
that you can activate a specific shell
associated with this project and then
deactivate it when you're done and it
won't have any impact on other projects
throughout your system so for installing
devbox as you can see I'm here on their
doc site uh the Linux instructions are
here the Mac instructions which I'm on
are here I'm going to curl this endpoint
it's going to get me a bash script which
is then piped into bash to install it if
I paste that into my
terminal it's going to ask me if this
default location is where I want to
install it I'll say yes I need to enter
my password because it requires pseudo
permissions and there we go now we've
successfully installed devbox in order
to you use devbox anywhere within the
context of this git repository uh
because I have the devbox configuration
files that I just mentioned I can do
devbox
shell and it's going to create create a
shell containing all of those
dependencies ready for use on the very
first time you run it it's going to take
quite a bit longer because it's going to
have to pull all of those dependencies
from the package manager but on future
times it's going to cash all of those
dependencies such that the shell will
start right up I can then do devbox list
and we can
see here are all the dependencies that
devbox installed within my current shell
session you'll notice one dependency in
particular go task and this is a
taskrunner program that I using
throughout this course to help store all
of the commands that you're going to
need uh and make it very easy to follow
along with all of the various demos so
for example if I now navigate to the
third module of the course and I run
task list all you can see I've defined a
number
of tasks within this task
file each of which executes some set of
commands as we run through this portion
of the
course for example we have a number of
tasks in this task file associated with
deploying and managing a kind kubernetes
and Docker
cluster which brings me to the next step
in this module we're going to deploy a
kind cluster onto our local machine one
really nice thing about kind is that
even though it's running locally and
each node is technically a container it
still supports running a configuration
with multiple nodes so we're actually
going to set up a cluster which has a
single control plane node as well as two
worker nodes so that while we're running
on a single host we still get a feel for
for how things would work and scheduling
workloads across different nodes even if
they're just
simulated this will work for most
examples throughout the course there are
a few places later in the course where
we're setting up public DNS to Route
traffic to our applications that won't
work here but for pretty much everything
else the kind cluster will work uh as
expected so let's jump over to
our code
editor so if I just run TL that is Alias
to run task-list all and it's going to
show me all the tasks within the task
file here defined within the third
module of the course as you can see
there are these four associated with our
kind cluster the first one is to
generate a configuration file uh that
we're going to use to deploy our cluster
or the reason that we have to generate
this rather than use one that already
exists is that I want to have these two
extra mounts specified and these are
where within my host system the kind
cluster is going to mount in uh each
node for persisting data so in this case
this is a path on my system it's an
absolute path and obviously your
username is going to be different than
mine and so rather than use that
directly I've created this template
containing these two environment
variables such that when we run task
kind1 generate
config it's going to execute this
command where we substitute in the
present working directory into that
template file and outputs a version that
is not checked into git uh containing
the absolute path to these two extra
mounts now you'll notice there that I
was able to tab complete
the various tasks that are available uh
the way that I was able to set that up
was following the setup completion step
within the installation instructions and
so you can see all completions are
available on the task repository within
this completion subdirectory it provides
the necessary completion files for your
various shells download the relevant
file and then you'll want to make it
executable and finally add a source call
to your profile for your shell such that
you'll get that autocompletion set up
with each time you open a new Shale
session with this config now generated
we can now run the second command within
our task file and so that second command
is going to be to actually create the
cluster we're going to run the kind
create cluster command and pass it that
config with the name of the config file
so I'll just run task kind O2 create
cluster behind the scenes it is going to
create the corresponding Docker
containers that we specif so we're going
to have one container for the control
plane and two containers for the worker
nodes this is going to take a little
while maybe 30
seconds great it looks like it's done
setting up so I can do Cube C get nodes
and by default it's going to add the
configuration file to connect to that
kubernetes API directly to our config
such that we can now authenticate to the
API server by doing CTL get nodes it
shows us we have that control plane node
and we have the two worker nodes within
the cluster awesome now there's one
additional task associated with the kind
cluster here in this task file and that
is the cloud provider kind uh this is a
tool that will enable us to run load
balancers within the kind cluster such
that we'll be able to access it from the
host and so when we get to the point
where we're deploying a service of type
load balancer we're going to come back
here and run this command and this will
set up a program running on the host
that will enable us to make that
connectivity happen for now we don't
need to deal with it but I'm just
calling it out because we're going to
use it later once we're done with the
course or want to clean things up we
have this command the kind delete
cluster command and that's going to take
the cluster and remove it from our
system cleaning up those containers on
our
host now I showed you the Cub C get
nodes command we can also look at the
Cub C get pods across all namespaces and
we see there's a number of system pods
including the types of things that I
talked about earlier Cube proxy is
handling that networking piece we got
the API server we've got the controller
manager
Etc and so with that we have a fully
functioning local cluster uh where each
node is running as a container that we
can use for the various demo portions of
the
course however I think it's also
educational to deploy remote clusters on
various CL providers CU that's probably
how you're going to configure things uh
in a workplace environment uh the first
cloud provider that I'm going to use is
one called SEO it's going to allow us to
provision a simple cloud-based cluster
uh they have very fast cluster creation
and destruction so it's very useful for
cases like this where we're going to
provision clusters and maybe tear them
down uh throughout our learning process
they provide during your first month a
$250 free credit for new user so that
should be more than plenty to handle the
use case within this course uh and then
beyond that you'll have to start paying
for the compute resources in this case
relative to kubernetes and Docker it's
going to allow us to demonstrate some
more realistic networking configurations
we'll be able to have public load
balancers that we can route uh DNS
records to uh as well as having
persistent storage that lives outside of
the cluster so that we can maintain
State across application deployments and
reloads outside of our containers last
time I checked there was an account
verification process that was required
for new accounts so after you sign up
there could be some delay before you're
actually able to provision a cluster and
so make your account reach out to the
team there and make sure that your
account gets verified such that you'll
be able to provision clusters and and
work along with the course now let's
jump back over to our code editor and
provision a cluster with COC Cloud if I
run the TL or task list command I'll see
the tasks associated with SEO uh we're
going to first authenticate to the SEO
command line with an API key we're then
going to create a network so you could
provision a cluster within the default
Network it's much better practice to
create an isolated network uh rather
than the default so you are in control
of all the settings we're going to
create a firewall to specify exactly
which ports we should allow Ingress and
egress traffic within that network uh
then we'll create the cluster itself if
you wanted to Short Circuit all of that
and run all of those in sequence you
could run first you need to authenticate
the CLI but then could run the create
all command and it would create the
network the firewall and the cluster
Allin one go let's go ahead and run that
first authenticate CLI
command these notes are provided within
the task itself uh we're going to log in
and create an account if you don't have
a team already you'll want to go to the
teams page and create a team and add
yourself to that team then you can go to
the security page to get the API key
itself so if we navigate here I'm
already logged in I'll regenerate a new
key it it's generated here I'll copy it
now I need to give it a name we'll call
it beginner to Pro I'll paste in the
value of that key and you can see I had
one key named primary which is set as
the default and I have this new key
which I just added to the CLI here in
order to use that new key I need to run
Zeo API Key current and then give it
that beginner to Pro
name if I list the keys again
I can see now the new beginner to Pro
key that I just saved is set as the
default
great let's examine what these next
commands are actually going to execute
the first one is going to run coo
Network create it's passing in this
cluster name environment variable as
well as the COO region environment
variable those are set up here at the
top the cluster name is going to be Dev
obective kubernetes course I'm using the
New York City 1 region you could change
the region if you have a different if
you have a different region that you
prefer or if you're located at a
different
place so if I execute
that we can see a new network was just
created with this
ID next up we're going to create
firewalls associate associated with that
Network it's going to run a few commands
in sequence the first one is going to be
to create the firewall itself Now by
default the firewall rule tools that SEO
creates with a firewall are very
permissive they allow access on all
ports and so we want to actually remove
the firewall rules that they provide and
so this is just a little Loop that looks
up the firewall rule IDs and removes
them all and then we're going to go
ahead and add back three specific rules
one for Port 80 one for Port 443 and one
for 6443 80 and 443 are for normal web
traffic that we're going to bring into
the cluster and then 6443 is for
accessing the kubernetes API itself The
Cider block that we're allowing is all
IP addresses because we want traffic to
arrive from the public internet if you
wanted to be a bit more restrictive for
the API server in this third rule you
could limit that to let's say your
specific IP of the machine you're
connecting from or you could have a
another machine that you're connecting
through as a proxy and specify only the
IP address of that machine let's go
ahead and run that command
it created the firewall it's now looping
through and deleting the default
rules we then added back the three rules
I described and I just have this note
here around if we wanted to lock down
that kubernetes API server further we
could restrict that third firewall rule
to a specific set of IP
addresses let's go look in the COO
interface and see the network and
firewall that we just created we can go
here to networking
networks you'll see the default Network
that we could have used we see the new
network that I just created and then I
also host host a plausible web analytics
server here and that's on its own
network as well we can look at the
firewalls here's the firewall that I
created associated with that same
network we just created we can look at
the rules
and we can see that for inbound traffic
we have the three rules that I described
and we're allowing egress on all ports
across all IP
ranges at this point the next step is
going to be to create the cluster itself
we're going to run the SEO kubernetes
create cluster command uh we pass it the
cluster name we specify the network and
the firewall that we have just created
in this case we're going to create a
cluster with two nodes using this uh
machine type if you want additional CPU
or memory you can either change the
number of nodes or you can change the
size that we're using to create those
nodes by default coo installs a traffic
Ingress controller using a node Port
configuration we don't want that for our
cluster we're going to start with a base
cluster that has no Ingress
controller and then this wait option
tells the command line to wait until the
cluster is done provisioning before it
returns so I'll run
T3 cluster
create it executes that command subbing
in the environment variables as
specified in my task
file and this will take between 90
seconds and 2 minutes if we navigate
back over to the COO dashboard we can
see the cluster here listed on the
kubernetes page it looks like one of my
two nodes is active the other one is
still coming
online this is that node type I
specified it has two CPUs 4 GB of memory
uh and a 50 GB disc
let's click into
it okay uh and now it is completed the
first time I tried it it failed for some
reason so I deleted it and recreated it
it looks like it completed this time in
about a minute and a half so that's
great uh and if we do Cube
CTX we see that currently we only have
that kind cluster in our Cube
configuration
file however we have a command
coo uh get Cube config
which is going to execute the COO
kubernetes config passing in the cluster
name --save and D- switch so it's going
to merge it into our existing Cube
config file and then switch such that
the default is the new SEO cluster so
now if I do Cube
CTX we see both the kind cluster and the
devops directive kubernetes course
cluster and if I do a cube CTL get nodes
we see the two nodes within that cluster
also you'll notice throughout the course
that I often times skip typing out cube
C and just do Cube just do K get
nodes that's because I have an alias set
with k equals Cube
CTL so now we have our kind cluster
setup we have a COO cluster
setup and the third type of cluster that
I'm going to demo here is Google
kubernetes engine on
gcp so GK is the oldest
and in my opinion the best manage
cluster experience if you want to manage
cluster and you aren't already using a
different cloud provider GK is probably
the way to go there's two different
modes that they offer there's a standard
mode which will be very similar to what
we just saw with SEO where you deploy
the cluster they manage the control
plane uh and you sort of manage the
worker nodes within your Google Cloud
account there's also an autopilot mode
which abstracts even more a way such
that you don't even really have to think
about the control plane at all you set
it up you interact with the kubernetes
API they abstract away all of the worker
nodes as well so you're you just Define
a workload and they handle all of the
underlying node provisioning and
management and so if you want to really
minimize the operations having a deal
with kubernetes autopilot can be a great
way to go we're going to go with the
standard mode just so we get a little
bit more hands-on experience working
with clusters Google Cloud also has a
free trial for new users within the
first 90 days you can get a $300 credit
also within their free tier you can have
one zonal cluster meaning the control
plan is deployed within a single zone
rather than across multiple
zones uh included within their free tier
so that includes the control plane only
any worker nodes that you deploy you're
going to have to pay for outside of that
free trial but it is nice that they have
one zonal cluster control plane included
within Google Cloud again we're going to
be able to demonstrate more realistic
networking to what you're going to be
using in the in a production setting
load balancers that we can route public
DNS to just like on coo within Google
Cloud there are multiple different
persistent storage classes coo just has
one you can deploy different types of
storage with different speeds and IO
capabilities Etc and then Google Cloud
also provid some some basic but useful
workload monitoring capabilities out of
the box you'll be able to see things
like how much CPU and memory your
workloads are using as well as viewing
aggregated logs from across all of your
workloads if we jump back to our code
editor and once again list out our tasks
similarly we're going to start by
initializing the CLI Google
interestingly doesn't enable a lot of
their Cloud apis out of the box you have
to tell it specifically in each project
which apis you want to be able to use so
we'll enable all those apis we're going
to set a default region and Zone this is
just so we don't have to specify it
every single time and then the following
steps are pretty similar to what we did
with CA we're going to create a VPC or a
virtual private Cloud that's essentially
the network we're going to create a
subnet within that Network and then once
we've done that we can create uh the
cluster itself this create all command
just combines all these steps together
if you wanted to run a single command
and bring up the cluster like that you
can do so with that single uh create all
command just like witho you could do all
this through the web interface you could
click here create a GK cluster and go
through the web UI however we want to
have everything codified in our repo and
so we're going to do so via the command
line an even better approach would be to
use an infrastructure as code tool like
terraform to handle this I'm just using
the CLI because it's a quick way to get
up and running but still allows us to
codify our configuration in the
repo the very first thing we're going to
do is to initialize the CLI so we'll do
T
gcp1 init
CLI it's going to walk us through the
setup of the command line uh in this
case I'm going to reinitialize the
configuration with new
settings so I'll pick number one if you
haven't already initialized maybe you'll
be picking number two create new
configuration it does a little bit of
Diagnostics you pick which account you
want to
use which project in this case I want to
use the kubernetes course
project we'll config configure a default
compute region in
zone I'm going to
use us Central
1 a as my default that's number
eight and we should be good to
go next up I'll run the enable apis
command and so the seven the eight apis
that we're going to use here are are the
compute API the container API the cloud
resource manager API uh the identity and
access management API secret manager
service management and service usage so
these are all the apis that we're going
to end up using behind the scenes and so
we need to enable those before we're
able to do
so because this was already set during
that initialization process you can skip
it if it was unset you could run this
command and it would set the default
region and zone for us
now we want to create a VPC if we look
here within the web
UI we click on VPC
Network we can see there's this default
network with 41 subnets lots of settings
that we may or may not want so instead
of using that we're going to deploy our
own new
VPC using the gcloud compute networks
create uh we're passing it a name for
the VPC
and then we're giving it this subnet
mode
custom this is going to tell this is
going to allow us to deploy our own
subnets versus automatically deploying
one subnet per
Zone once the VPC is created we're going
to create the
subnet we're naming our subnet subnet
one we're passing it the name of our VPC
we're passing it the region that we want
to deploy it into and then we're giving
it an IP range this is the set of
private IP addresses that should be
included on this
subnet with the VPC and Subnet in place
we can now run the create cluster
command this is the command is running
behind the scenes gcloud container
clusters create passing at a cluster
name giving it a Zone giving it a
network name from the network we created
before the sub network name that we
created in the previous
step the machine type that we're using
is this E2 standard 2 machine with two
nodes and we're turning on the standard
Gateway API option this is so that it
will automatically deploy the custom
resource definitions for the uh Gateway
API that we'll talk about a little bit
in the next section and then this final
option the workload pool this is going
to allow us to authenticate to other
Google cloud services without needing to
have static credentials so we're able to
use something called workload identity
to to handle authentication to other
Google cloud services in a much more
streamlined fashion than if we needed to
create static credentials and pass those
in this is going to take a few
minutes and in the meantime we can go
over to the Google Cloud console and
take a look at the resources we've
created thus
far if we refresh here on
the UPC page we can see we have not only
the default network but also the new
network that we created with our single
Subnet in the US Central One region
using the IP range that we
specified if we go to the kubernetes
engine
page we can
see the cluster that I'm creating via
the command line is spinning up
here it's configured it's deploying and
then it will do some health checks just
to make sure that the cluster's healthy
before it deems it
complete all right it looks like the
cluster is up and now it's doing its
health
checks we used a few options with that
command line provisioning but as you can
see here there's tons of different
toggles and configurations that we could
have chosen as we provisioned the
cluster uh so if there are non default
settings that you want you should go
through the documentation and see if any
of these should be turned on I've
enabled the options that we care about
for exploring the different kubernetes
capabilities but there are things here
that you may want to check a look
at okay it looks like our cluster
creation is complete uh so let's go
ahead and do Cube CX you'll you'll
notice that this gke cluster creation
process added the credentials to our
Cube config file automatically uh and
set it as the default so now we have the
kind cluster the gka cluster and the COO
cluster all listed here
we'll use the GK cluster K get
nodes and we've got our two nodes online
and ready do K get pods in all the
namespaces we see just like with our
kind cluster we've got the system pods
in that Cube system
namespace even though we haven't
deployed any workloads ourselves these
are things that GK is managing behind
the scenes uh for our cluster so that it
works
properly each of these Cloud providers
has a cleanup
task as well so if we wanted to delete
the cluster the network Etc we could run
the gcp cleanup task uh however there
are edge cases where maybe you've
deployed something that is associated
with the cluster that I haven't
accounted for and so if you run that
cleanup task and it runs into an issue
you may need to go into the console
figure out what resources are blocking
and manually clean those up I just want
to make sure to call that out because if
you have these resources up and running
uh and leave them there you will be
paying for them over time once those
free trials run out and so I don't want
you to accidentally leave a cluster
running I did that when I was first
starting out and incurred a multiple
hundred bill from AWS luckily they
forgave it when I explained what had
happened but just want to make sure
you're being careful about looking at
the resources that you're deploying
understanding them and cleaning them up
if they're no longer
necessary you can use whichever of these
cluster types that you'd like throughout
the course I wanted to Showcase how to
deploy all three of them so that you can
pick uh but realistically any of them
are going to work and hopefully give you
experience working with the different
types of
clusters so that when you encounter a
new one in the future you'll be
comfortable and able to do so
effectively now that we have an
understanding of some of the kubernetes
history and how the system components
function as well as having deployed one
or more clusters that we can operate
with it's time to take a look at the
built-in resources that kubernetes
provides out of the box what we would
use them for and how they behave this
section is meant to give you a high
level understanding of the different
pieces and build blocks but outside the
context of a demo application it's very
hard to fully understand the nuances and
so my hope is that you will leave this
section with awareness of the breadth of
different resources that are available
and then as we revisit these resources
in more detail as we build out our demo
application later in the course that
understanding will solidify and you'll
start to understand the patterns with
which you would use these in future
application designs the first resource
type that we want to look at is a
namespace and this this provides a
mechanism to group resources within the
cluster it kind of helps to provide
organization or tidiness to your cluster
where you can take app a single
application and put it in its own
namespace or you could take a group of
similar or or applications that interact
with each other and put them in a
namespace while it is possible to put
everything in the default namespace you
would end up with tons and tons of
resources and it would be very hard to
understand what was going on and so it's
best practice to use namespaces to group
things logically so that it's easier
to reason about and understand the
applications running within a cluster it
is important to call out that by default
namespaces do not act as a network or
security boundary uh you can still make
Network calls across namespaces and so
while it seems like you're isolating
your applications with a namespace they
don't provide additional security sort
of out of the box when you first create
a kubernetes cluster there's going to be
four initial namespaces created by the
system the default namespace which is
there just to allow you to get started
without needing to create your own
namespaces if you don't want however as
I said it's best practice to do so and
then there's some system name spaces
like Cube system Cube node lease and
Cube public uh that the kubernetes
system uses you probably won't need to
worry about those too much except for
knowing that within that Cube system
namespace you'll recognize some of the
system components that we've talked
about like Cube proxy within the module
4 directory in the companion repo you'll
see that there is a subdirectory for
each of the resource types that we're
going to explore and so in this case
we'll be taking a look at the namespace
folder within each folder there will be
a task file as well as some other yaml
files those other emo files are where we
have the actual definition for the
resources
themselves while the task file contains
all the different commands that we're
going to use to interact with a resource
they're all going to start by creating a
namespace and so that's why we're
looking at namespaces first by creating
a namespace for each resource type in
this case we're able to isolate things
and pro avoid name conflicts even if we
don't clean up from one resource to the
next while this may be a little over the
top in terms of creating tons of name
spaces I thought it would be useful in
order to isolate each resource type and
avoid potential issues with conflicts
there so hopefully that gives you some
idea of the structure here I'm going to
jump over to my code editor and pull up
these same files and then we can execute
them against one of our
clusters I could use any one of the
three clusters that I set up in this
case I'm going to use the kind cluster
for now just because it's simple and
it's local the results would be
identical across all these different
clusters though I want to at this point
call out another useful command that the
cube C interface has and that is Cube
CTL explain so you can do Cube CTL
explain and then put in any resource
type in this case we'll do
namespace and it will tell us all the
different fields that we need to specify
a description of what that field
represents within this top level set of
fields you can also dive in to see any
of the sub Fields so you could for
example do K explain
namespace do
metadata within the metadata we can see
all the different fields in this case
the only field that we're setting is the
name field for each of these resources
we'll also be using the cube TL command
line to investigate and inspect the
resources so before we've done anything
else we can do K get namespaces so there
are the four Nam spaces that I called
out that would be in any uh kubernetes
cluster upon startup and then there's
this additional local path storage
namespace that is specific to kubernetes
and Docker and it is provisioning an
application in that namespace to enable
us to use local paths on our host system
uh to set up persistent storage at the
top here we can see the definition of a
namespace we specified that is it is of
kind namespace and that namespace
belongs to the API version V1 and so
that's just that's the root kubernetes
API version number one and the only
information we really need to provide it
is the metadata name field and this is
the name that will show up after we
create it now if I navigate into the
namespace
subdirectory where this task file lives
and I do TL for task list we can see
there's three different commands here
the first one is to create a namespace
via the command line so we we can just
say Cube C create namespace and then
pass it a name so I'll go ahead and do
that it executed this command and we see
that the namespace 04 namespace CLI was
created I can do K get namespaces now
and we see that it now exists it was
just
created however this is creating it in
more of an imperative fashion if we want
to store the definition of our resources
in git then we do so by putting the
definition within a yaml file and then
we can instead of running the create
command we can run the apply
command so Cube CTL apply DF for file
and then pass it the name of that
resource configuration so in this case
we can do
T2 it's going to create the namespace
based on this file and now again we can
do K get namespaces and we see the new
names space- file namespace was created
in general it is preferred to store the
definition of your resources within your
code basee rather than creating them on
the command line imperatively and so in
this case I would generally recommend
that you create these files and use the
apply command rather than creating them
directly with a cube CTL create
namespace namespaces are simple enough
that it doesn't matter too much but as
we move to more complex resources this
will matter more and more now just to
clean up we can run this delete
namespaces command which will run in
sequence these two commands first we'll
delete this one by passing its name via
the command line and then alternatively
we can pass again the file containing
the definition and it will find the
resources that are contained within that
file and delete
those now if I do a k get namespaces
again we can see that the two Nam spaces
we had previously created are
gone now I wanted to cover Nam spaces
first because we're going to use them in
each of these lessons but the next
resource that we're looking at the Pod
is really the foundational building
block upon which the rest of our
workloads in kubernetes are going to be
built it is often cited as the smallest
Deployable unit within kubernetes uh and
it is where our containers are going to
be
run however I will caveat with the fact
that you were almost never going to
create a pod directly we're going to do
so here for educational purposes uh such
that we can look at it and interact with
it in isolation however there are higher
level controllers and resources that
we're going to get to down the road that
we'll use in almost every scenario I've
included here a minimal definition for a
pod resource we need to give the Pod a
name within the metadata field and then
we need to specify one or more
containers within the spec field giving
each of those containers a name and a
container image to reference while a pod
can have a single container it can also
have multiple containers within it uh if
you have multiple containers within a
pod generally you're going to have one
primary application container
and then you might have what are known
as init containers or sidecar containers
an init container is going to be a
container which runs before the startup
of the other containers uh and that can
be used to do things like preparing
various files in the file system
injecting dependencies for something
like a a metrics aggregator into the
primary container uh there's a number of
use cases there and then side card
containers are containers that uh don't
run before the primary container but run
alongside it in perpetuity these are of
used for things like serving as a
network proxy uh for example uh on gcp
there's a proxy that is provided by
Google to help you connect to their
managed database instances called
cloudsql proxy and that is often run as
a sidecar
container now within a pod the
containers are going to share networking
resources and storage resources they can
have shared access to volumes and so
they can pass files and signals between
each other using those volumes and also
while my previous configuration
literally only contained a name and a
image there's tons of different
configuration options that are available
such as which ports the application
should be listening on uh things like
liveness and Readiness probes that tell
the cuet how to check if the application
is healthy or not and how often to check
you can set the uh CPU memory and
storage requests and limits so the
requests are the amount that you require
and and the limits are the maximum
amount that the system should allow uh
the application to utilize there is a
security context which allows you to
specify whether or not the application
is allowed to run as root whether it
should have readon access to the file
system
Etc we can specify environment variables
and that can be a way to manage
configuration across different
environments or pass in sensitive
information in the form of credentials
you can specify volume that could be
used for persistent storage or
configuration and you can specify how
DNS should resolve for that particular
pod as we deploy both in this lesson and
future lessons we'll explore how a
number of these different configuration
options manifest now I wanted to just
throw this slide in here to give a
number of useful patterns kind of a
cheat sheet for using Cube CTL you'll
see me follow and execute many of these
commands throughout I'm not going to go
through each one right now but I put it
here for reference so that you can come
back and take a look at it the general
structure of these commands is going to
be Cube CTL and then a verb like uh get
create apply edit Etc and then a noun
where that noun is a is the resource
type so that could be namespace or pod
or any of these other resources that
we're learning about in this section if
you're targeting a particular namespace
you would do the- n flag with the
namespace name and then you can get the
output in a variety of formats uh by
default def fault it's going to be a
format that looks nice in the command
line via standard out however if you
want it in Json or yaml such that you
can do parsing of the results via uh
some other program you can specify that
with the- flag jumping back to our code
editor and navigating to the uh pod
subdirectory of lesson 4 we can see that
we have a namespace
file that namespace file is going to
follow the convention o--
pod4 meaning it's module 4 and then Das
Das and the resource name is POD and
then we have two pod definitions here
that we're going to take a look at but
first let's peek into the task file and
see the commands that we're going to be
running as you'll notice it's very
familiar to before the first thing that
we're going to do is create a namespace
so we'll apply that namespace
yaml by running task 01 create namespace
you can see it does two things first it
do the cube C apply command on our
namespace resource creating that 04--
pod namespace and then secondly we're
calling this Cube namespace command
we're setting that to be our default
namespace so that in future commands we
don't have to pass it that dashn flag
now if I try to do K get pods we can see
we haven't deployed anything yet next up
let's use the cube CTL run command to
create a pod directly from the command
line you'll notice that I've provided a
big warning saying please please do not
do this this works just fine however you
now have no record within your code base
that this was created it's likely going
to live on in perpetuity as just sort of
this orphaned resource until it causes
some issue down the
road but if we look at the command that
it ran it executed Cube C run we passed
it the image via this image option uh in
this case we're running an engine X web
server version
1.26 we are deploying it into the
namespace that we created and then I
named it created the wrong way so if we
do K get pods we can see we have created
the wrong way is the name of our pod and
it's been running for 41 seconds for now
we're just going to leave it there it's
not harming anything and we can take a
look at the two configurations uh of
PODS that we have here in our yaml files
the first one is a super minimal
configuration with the minimum set of
values specified in this case we're
providing it with a name uh we're
providing it with one container that
container has a name and that container
has an image this container similar to
the one we created with the qctl Run
command is going to take the default
values for all of the other
configuration specs however at least
this time we have the resource yaml in
our code base and so it's possible for
us to understand and reason about the
fact that why it would exist the way it
does I can apply it by doing T3 minimal
apply
it starts in this container creating
State and then a few seconds later it's
running these two have a pretty much
identical
specification however the minimal is
preferred because again we have this
declarative state that we can store in
our code repository that being said
there's a number of default values that
this minimal configuration is going to
take on and we can do better that's what
this pod engine X better specification
is is doing um many of these ideas and
specifications are pulled from a friend
of mine Brett fiser who has this GitHub
repo podspec you should definitely check
it out it provides uh some ideas on the
a set of good defaults you can use
within your pod and understanding which
of these values matter and which of
these values it's fine to take the the
regular default for in this case we're
specifying both the name and the name
space so in the minimal configuration we
didn't specify namespace and so it was
deployed into whatever namespace our
Cube configuration happened to set as
the default because in my previous task
I had set my default namespace to be
this 04-- pods it was deployed here but
otherwise it would have been deployed
into the default namespace for our
better spec we're actually specifying
the namespace in our configuration so
it's super clear uh and explicit there's
no way you confuse which name space it
ends up in also instead of only
specifying a name in an image uh you can
see I've specified a whole bunch more
information here about the container I'm
also using this uh image from chainu
guard and chainu guard is an interesting
company that helps build uh more secure
container images if you are concerned
about uh vulnerabilities and keeping
your images secure definitely check out
chuard for the types of images that they
provide and you'll see that I've
provided uh a listing of ports that this
appc is listening on and so for
something like enginex generally you
want to have it serving up content on
some port in this case 880 is the
default so we'll be able to uh actually
test this in a second here I've also
specified that the Readiness probe that
ku990 should use is just to make a
request on Port 80 using that root
path I've given it a resource limit and
request in this case I'm specifying um a
memory and CPU requests so this pod will
be guaranteed at least 50 mtes of memory
and 250 millor of CPU and I'm only
specifying a limit for memory uh so this
is important because if you don't
specify a limit for memory and the Pod
has a and the container has a memory
leak it can consume more and more memory
and eventually it will be competing with
other containers and pods scheduled on
the same node which can cause issues and
kubernetes will start to evict some of
your pods which can cause instability in
your
application we've also set the security
context to disallow privilege escalation
uh and set the privileged value to false
as well as enabled the set comp runtime
uh and some specific users and groups
that are nonroot as long as our
application and container image are
designed to run in such a fashion these
can just provide an additional layer of
security such that there's no potential
for a privilege escalation should an
attacker gain access to this runtime
environment we apply this in the same
way we'll do
T5 and now all three of our pods are
running to show you uh that these are
actually engine X and actually serving
something we can do a command called
cctl port forward uh so in this case
let's start by port forwarding to the
minimal pod which executes the cctl port
forward in the Nam space that we're
operating in the name of the Pod and
then we're going to go from port 8080 on
my host system so 8080 in my browser or
uh command line to Port 80 within that
container so I do Local Host 8080 we can
see we get the default engine X page
served up that just shows that it is
running and it's doing what we expect
however if you remember we didn't
actually specify any ports here we can
still port forward to that pod directly
uh but we but it's much better if we
specify the ports that it's expecting to
listen on such that others looking at
that configuration can easily read that
and see oh it's listening on Port 80
similarly we can port forward to the
other
pod however in this case we're
forwarding from 880 on the local system
to 880 in the container that's because
this image is running as a non-root user
and that non root user cannot bind to
Port 80 inside the container
uh so slight Nuance there but just
important to understand which ports the
applications are listening on so that
you can connect to them on the right
Port having that defined within the spec
here makes it very clear for other
teammates to know this pod is going to
be listening on port
8080 if I reload this we get the exact
same thing those two container images
are quite similar except that the chain
guard one is a bit more minimal and
likely has less vulnerability ities now
finally before we move on I'm just going
to delete the name
space and
conveniently deleting a namespace
recursively deletes the resources inside
of it so all of those pods that I
created are now going to be deleted uh
and so if I do K get namespace you can
see that namespace no longer exists and
K get pods that namespace doesn't exist
so the pods definitely don't exist
within it building up from the base
level of the pod we can now move on to
the replica set the replica set takes a
pod definition and wraps it in another
layer adding the concept of replicas
it's going to take that definition of
the Pod that you provide and then you
can specify from one to n replicas and
there's a controller within that Cube
controller manager that's going to
ensure that we have however many
replicas specified instances of that pod
running at all time you'll notice
highlighted into green that the
specification of the pod on the left
Maps one one to one with the
specification under the template section
of the replica set so any of those
options that we talked about before we
can configure for the replica set and
the way that you connect a replica set
to its underlying pods is through labels
we see that selector using match labels
where you're having some key value pairs
when managing these the replica set
controller is going to look with pods
containing those same labels so we need
to make sure that whatever we specify in
that selector we also add as labels on
the Pod template these will get applied
to the individual pod pods and that's
how the controller can maintain the link
between the replica set and the pods
again like pods you almost never are
going to manage a replica set or even
interact with a replica set directly
instead we're going to use a higher
level construct deployment which we'll
learn next let's jump over to our code
editor create some replica sets and see
how they behave I'll navigate to the
replica set
folder we've got a task file the first
thing I'm going to do as always here is
create the namespace so we created this
namespace 04- replica set and then we
use the cube NS command to set it as a
default now let's take a look at the
minimal replica set definition that
aligns with what I showed on the slide
here at the bottom within the template
section we have a specification that
contains the definition for our pod
we've got a label that's going to be
applied to each of those pods and then
we have our match labels selector that's
going to allow the replica set
controller to find and create those pods
so if I apply this definition we're
going to expect one replica set to be
created and then we're going to expect
three pods because I have replica set to
three to also be
created by applying this file using the
cube CTL apply DF command uh we see this
replica set was created again I can do K
get replica
sets or just K get RS it shows our
replica set it shows us the desired
number of replicas as well as the
current number of replicas and how many
of those are determined to be ready
based on the let's health check if I do
a k get pods
now we see each of these three pods have
have come up based on that single
replica set now an interesting thing
here is I can delete one of these pods
and you'll notice it gets this random
hash at the end uh this is so that we
don't have naming conflict it's going to
take our name of our replica set and
then append this as a postfix to each of
the pods that it creates however watch
this I'll delete this
pod now I'll run kg get pods again and
we have have two of the original Three
running but the third was deleted the
replica set controller noticed that the
number of replicas was lower than the
desired State and added a new pod to
compensate like I said you're very
rarely going to interact with replica
sets directly you'll see them in your
cluster because we're going to use
deployments and deployments create
replica sets uh but it's useful to
understand what they are and the fact
that what we're adding here are the
number of replicas and how we use labels
to connect the replica set to its
underlying pods replica sets are great
for for maintaining a static definition
of that pod and keeping the number of
instances that we want alive however in
order to be able to change your pod spec
by doing things like updating the
container image within it maybe
modifying the amount of resources that
the Pod needs basically any change to
the specification of that pod the
replica set can't handle in it of itself
for that we move one step further up
this chain and create a deployment if
you look at the definitions here again
we can go from pod to replica set we see
that spec within the template matches
that of the Pod and then as you can see
in this minimal example the spec of the
deployment matches the spec of the
replica set there are some additional
fields that I'm not showing here uh in
the deployment spec that you can use
such as the strategy with which you want
to handle rollouts and the revision
history limit so how many ver how many
older versions of a deployment you want
to keep around but for the most part the
specs between these two resources are
quite similar the main difference being
that the deployment controller adds this
concept of rollouts and roll backs uh
and so you can specify how you want the
pods to change as you go from one
version of the deployment to the next uh
so for example if we if we update the
image tag to a new version of our
application we can specify do we want
that to happen one POD at a time how
many pods are we okay with being
unhealthy at a time uh Etc and so this
gives us all of the tooling that we need
create our cap applications take
advantage of that replica set controller
to ensure that the number of replicas
that we want are running and then take
advantage of the deployment capabilities
to smoothly roll from one version to the
next or one configuration to the next
you're going to use deployments very
frequently for pretty much any stateless
application that you're running on top
of kubernetes you're going to reach for
the deployment as your resource of
choice it allows you to Define that
podspec specify how many replicas you
want and smoothly move from one version
or configuration to the next let's jump
over to the code editor and create a few
deployments and see how they behave I'll
navigate to the deployment
subdirectory once again we'll create the
namespace now we've got this 04
deployment namespace and we've set it as
the default now let's apply this minimal
deployment
configuration and we'll apply the better
configuration as well these are pretty
much the same Concepts that we saw in
the Pod lesson where the minimal
specification only contains the absolute
minimum set of values required whereas
the better specification includes all of
the additional pod configuration options
we can do K get deployments to see all
the deployments in this Nam space in
this case we have our two deployments
this one was just created and so only
one of three pods were available at the
time if I run it again now we see that
both of the deployments are healthy we
can do K get replica
sets and we see one replica set for each
so we created the deployment kubernetes
in turn created an underlying replica
set and then each of those created and
manages those underlying pods so if I
now do kg pods I expect to see six three
associated with the minimal deployment
and three associated with the better
deployment great I mentioned this
concept of deployments adding rolls roll
outs and roll backs uh we can showcase
this by doing one of a few things one we
could modify the container image
specified in the deployment
specification and reapply it that would
trigger an update to the deployment
which would create a new replica set
which would create new pods or we can
issue the roll out restart command so we
can say
T4 this issued the cctl the cctl rollout
restart on the deployment engine X
better and I'm watching the cube CTL get
pods command and we saw it cycled
through those pods one at a time
bringing up a new one deleting an old
one bringing up a new one deleting an
old one we can also look at the replica
sets
now and we see there's one replica set
for the minimal deployment but because
we've gone through this upgrade or this
roll out it actually created a new
replica set the old one Still Remains
but now the number of replicas is set to
zero such that it's not creating any
pods these are kept around so that we
could roll back if we wanted for example
we could do the cctl roll out undo
command
and it's going to roll back to that
previous state we'll see the number of
pods in this replica set jump back up
and the number of pods in the the
current replica set go
down there we go now as I mentioned the
third the other thing that might trigger
a roll out like this is modifying the
Pod specification so for example if we
went within
here to the engine X minimal
configuration and we updated this to
version
1.27 and then we reapplied it with
K apply DF uh on engine X
minimal we can see that it is tearing
down some of the old pods and creating
new pods in their
place this is a new pod that has been
created with that new image these are
still the old pods that haven't been
torn down yet once that roll out
completes we now have three new pods all
running that new
image this shows the power of this
declarative approach because we can have
this single definition of our
application deployment we can modify
Fields within that specification as we
upgrade things as we need to change our
configuration we then reapply that same
definition kubernetes takes the new
state and figures out based on its
controllers how to reconcile that state
with the state of the cluster such that
we get the end state that we desire and
by default it does so in that rolling
fashion where we're replacing one po at
a time so we never had to have any
downtime because we had multiple pods
running and it would only remove the old
pod after the new pod was healthy we'll
be using deployments quite a bit for the
stateless components of the demo
application in a future lesson now that
we have a mechanism to host our
applications using the deployment uh the
next logical question is how to get
network traffic to those applications
and the answer in kubernetes is a
service there's a few different types of
services that we're going to talk about
here but effectively a service will
serve as a load balance spor across
replicas of our application that could
be only accessible internally or it can
be accessible outside the cluster as
well like the connection between the
replica set or the deployment and the
underlying pods the services are going
to use labels to determine which pods to
serve traffic to and there's three
primary types of services that we're
going to care about uh the first one is
known as a cluster IP service this is
the default type of service uh and will
be accessible only within the cluster
it's going to provide a stable IP
address that will then Route traffic to
any number of replicas containing the
appropriate labels in most cases when we
create a deployment we're going to
create a service alongside of it to
Route traffic to the pods within that
deployment now a node Port is similar to
a cluster IP except for the fact that
instead of only being accessible
internal to the cluster it's actually
going to listen on every node within the
cluster such that you could Route
traffic from outside the cluster into
the cluster and to your application and
finally the service type load balancer
will use that cloud controller manager
component of kubernetes to talk to the
cloud API for whichever Cloud you're
running on and provision a load balancer
within their system and that load
balancer will be used to bring to bring
traffic into the cluster it is important
to note that these load balancers within
each cloud provider generally have a
charge associated with them so adding a
load balancer service for every single
application that needs external traffic
would add up quickly there are other
mechanisms that we'll talk about down
the road where you can use a single uh
point of entry either a node either a
load balancer or nodeport and then Route
traffic using either what's called an
Ingress or the Gateway API and we'll
talk about those in a little bit you can
see in the service specs down at the
bottom the main things that you're going
to need to Define are the ports and
protocols that the service is listening
on the port is the inbound port for
addressing the service and the Target
Port is going to be the port in the Pod
that it is connecting to you also need
to have a selector and this needs to
align this needs to map the label
specified in your pod definition in the
node Port specification you can see at
the bottom I have commented out a node
Port value you can specify an exact node
Port it needs to be between 30,000 and
32,000 something uh if you don't specify
a port number here kubernetes will pick
a port within that range uh and
automatically deconflict with any other
services if we look at the diagram in
the upper right you can see traffic can
reach our cluster from the outside world
uh that could either come into the
cluster via a node Port Service uh or
via a load balancer service and then the
cluster IP service is only accessible
from within the cluster so here we have
application B talking to application a
via that cluster IP service behind the
scenes kubernetes is going to set up all
the necessary networking to be able to
route that traffic across nodes as long
as they're connected to the cluster
let's go ahead and jump to the code
editor provision a few services and see
how they behave uh we'll need to
navigate to the service subdirectory
and as you can see task was not found
that's because I had restarted my
computer between filming uh so I can
just do
devbox shell it's going to find that
devbox configuration and start a new
shell with all those dependencies
available as always we're going to start
by creating that
namespace so now we have the 04 service
namespace and it's set as our default
next up we're going to apply this
deployment configuration it matches the
minimal configuration from the previous
lesson with the main difference being
that I've changed the labels a little
bit just to Showcase which of these
labels matters for which purpose uh in
this case uh the key here for the label
on the deployment is Fu the key for an
annotation on the deployment is bar the
selector is using the key
baz and the podspec template is using
the label baz so the important thing
here is that these two match and then
we're going to also have to use that
same
baz pod label key value pair in our
service to Route traffic to this so we
can do a cube CTL apply on that
deployment file and it is creating an
enginex minimal deployment within this
name
space those pods are all up and running
now we're going to create three services
one for each of our different types that
I described
I've added this warning here when we
create the noport type Service uh unless
we have our firewall rules or Security
Group set up to enable traffic on that
node Port Port uh we're not going to be
able to reach the cluster accordingly so
if you do want to use a node port to
bring traffic into your cluster you'll
need to update those rules to allow that
traffic we can do K get
service or just K get
SVC and for this example I was using the
cluster deployed onto sio
cloud and so when we did K get service
you'll notice the cluster IP has an
internal IP address here that's a
private IP the node Port does as well
and then the load balancer has both an
internal address as well as a public
external facing address that we can use
to access that service you'll see for
the node Port it's listening both on
Port 80 as well as on Port 31500 if I
access that external IP for my
browser you can see that traffic is
routed into my cluster if we go into the
web interface for coo under the
networking and load balancers page we
can see this load balancer was just
provisioned uh we've got our public IP
here that we were just using and now we
could set up DNS and Route traffic to
our service from the public internet and
so this is highlighting the usage of
that cloud controller manager where
we're interfacing with a cloud provider
to provision a res Source outside of the
cluster but that integrates nicely with
the cluster also while it's nice that it
creates a IP address for us that
wouldn't be all that useful from a
service Discovery standpoint and so
there's actually another service running
within our cluster called core DNS and
we can look at it in the cube system
namespace so we can see there's this
deployment containing two pods for core
DNS and what that does is looks at all
these services and sets up DNS that
resolve internal to the cluster so that
based on the service name and the name
space we can create a DNS name that will
route us to that service to demonstrate
this I'll create a temporary pod in
first I'll create it in the namespace
that we're working
in in the o4 service name space and then
I'll curl the service at enginex cluster
IP on port 8080 on Port 80 as you can
see we get the welcome to enginex
default index. ml return to
us so if we're in the same name space we
can just use the name of the service
directly however if we exit this and we
create the same pod but in the default
namespace or any other namespace for
that
matter and we tried to run the same
command now that's no longer going to
resolve if we want to make a call across
name spaces we have to use the service
name followed by by the name space where
the service lives followed by service
cluster local now if we run this command
even though we're making that call from
the default namespace by using that
fully qualified domain name cord DNS is
going to resolve it to the service in
our o for service Nam space this will be
very important as you work with services
and want your applications to address
each other within the cluster I'm also
going to run this demo on the kind
cluster just to Showcase how to get the
load balancer service working properly
so I'm going to apply the deployment and
load balancer service types
so I'll do
T1 create namespace
t02 uh apply deployment and then
t05 apply load balancer
service if we did nothing else this load
balancer service would be stuck in
pending forever uh because kind out of
the box doesn't have support for these
load balancer type
Services however if you recall back in
lesson 3 when we were setting things
up we had this additional task where we
could run the cloud provider kind uh to
enable those load balancer services so
I'm going to open a new terminal
here I'm going to navigate
to lesson three and we're going to run
that uh cloud provider kind command in
this terminal we have to run it as
pseudo
and now if we do Kate service we can see
that our load balancer running on the
kind cluster now has this external IP
address this isn't truly an external IP
that's publicly accessible however it
will be accessible from our host system
so I can now access this from my laptop
and ACC and access that deployment
running in the kind cluster directly
this is very useful if you want to have
your uh local development cluster match
the behavior of your remotely deployed
Cloud clusters so the deployment was the
right resource type for our long running
stateless applications but that's not
the only type of application that we
might want to deploy onto kubernetes
there are also applications that we want
to run to completion uh and so that is
where the resource type of job comes
into play it's still built off a
foundation of a pod but we're adding to
the concept of a pod this idea of one or
more completions for a particular
container as you can see here in the
example specification at the bottom
rather than running something like
enginex which is meant to run as a long
running process I've instead modified it
to use this busy box image busy box is a
suite of Unix tools uh bundled up in
this container image uh one of those
Unix tools that I'm using here is the
date command all this container is going
to do is start up issue the date command
which is going to print the current date
time to the command line to standard out
uh and then exit and then I've specified
a restart policy as never such that
kubernetes doesn't try to restart this
container within the context of that job
on the left hand side is a standalone
pod and we can see that specification
for the Pod translates directly into the
spec template portion of the job
specification I've also added a backoff
limit to the job specification that
tells kubernetes how many times if it
were to fail on the first try how many
times it should retry before it gives up
on completing the job let's jump over
into the code editor and create some
jobs to see how the behave I'll navigate
to the job
subdirectory we're going to start by by
creating the
namespace and now first let's create
this pod directly without a
job you can see it starts in container
creating
State and then it's in status completed
we can look at the logs for this pod by
doing K logs and passing it the name and
we see it printed the current date time
to the standard out just like we
expected however ever if something had
gone wrong during the execution of this
pod let's say rather than just printing
something immediately and exiting it was
a long running job that might take an
hour or two hours or a day and during
that time there was some sort of
interruption if we had divined it as
just a pod kubernetes would not retry it
for us by using a job specification we
can track completions and if one fails
it will automatically retry so instead
we can jump over and use this job
specification
so here we're doing Cube CTL apply on
the minimal job
yl we can list the jobs and we see
here's our job it's in a complete status
with one of one desired completions the
default number of completions is one you
can modify that if you want to have it
run if you want to have it execute
multiple times and we can see it took 3
seconds before it completed let's look
at the
pods this is the Pod we created
Standalone manual and then this is the
Pod that the job controller created
based on on our job specification it
shows zero of one ready because the Pod
is already run and completed and is no
longer executing now let's take a look
at this additional job specification
using some of the additional options
that are available for configuration
here I've set parallelism to two so it's
going to run up to two copies of this
pod in parallel we want two completions
so it's going to run them until we have
two successful completions I've
specified an active deadline so this is
how long a pod should be allowed to run
before kubernetes decides that it is too
long and kills
it and then again we've specified a
backoff limit saying retry up to one
time and now I forget if this is
inclusive or exclusive so let's actually
do a k explain on jobs to check out the
back off limit
field specifies the number of retries
before marking it failed so by
specifying one it will retry one time
and if that second if that retry failed
it would Mark the job as failed as we
can see the default value would have
been six I've also modified the
container spec here slightly uh we're
we're using a chain guard image rather
than the Upstream busy box image we're
specifying limits for memory and
requests for memory and CPU we're
modifying the security contexts many of
the best practices that I highlighted in
the section where we covered pods now if
I apply that better
job we're going to
expect two pods to create at the same
time because of that parallelism and
complete completion
setting we can see that we have two of
two completions and that pod is now done
we're going to reach for a job whenever
we have a specific task that needs to be
completed one or more times rather than
a long running process that kubernetes
should keep up forever continuing down
this path of running uh workloads that
are expected to complete we just learned
about the job and how we can use that to
run a one-off task to one or more
completions there are many cases however
where you want to run a job like that
but you want it to run periodically on a
schedule that's where the Cron job comes
in so if we see here we can create a
Cron job and specify a schedule in the
form of a cron string uh you'll notice
that five character uh string Under the
schedule key five asteris means run on
every minute each character in that
string specifies a different portion of
the time that it should be run and so
we're once again building up from the
Pod we have our pod that's going to run
to completion we wrap that in a job and
then we further Define a Cron job which
is going to execute our job on a
schedule for learning more about how to
specify the cron string or for figuring
out the cron string that you care about
I would suggest go into this website
cab. Guru and as you can see in my
example I had specified five stars this
just means at every minute let's say we
wanted to run uh once a day at midnight
we could say run at 0
0 and this would run at midnight UTC
time every single day as you can see you
specify a different value for different
fields within the string and that will
give you a different schedule upon which
the Cron job will run there's not much
different about cron jobs and jobs
except that cron jobs are going to
automatically execute on the schedule
whereas jobs execute only at creation
time let's jump to the code editor
create some cron jobs and see how they
behave we'll navigate to the Cron job
subdirectory we'll create the
namespace so let's go ahead and apply
the better Crown job
definition we can see the crown job was
created but if I do K get jobs there's
no jobs yet we have to wait until the
next minute occurs at which point a job
will be spawned based on our
schedule now that the next minute has
ticked over we can see that the Cron job
has spawned a job it's running it's now
completed if we let this be
every minute we would get a new job
which would be created from that
template which would run based on our
specification however when debugging
your schedule is usually not going to be
as frequent as every minute you're
probably going to run something daily or
a few times a day and so it's not very
convenient to have to wait until that
schedule occurs in order to test that
your configuration is correct there is a
convenient option to create a job from a
Chron job specification so we can do
this and it's going to be the cube CTF
create job-- from we pass it the name of
our Cron job and then we give it a name
of the job that should be created so in
this case I named the job manually
triggered if I go to k get jobs we can
see here's the one that was
automatically created from the schedule
and here's the one that I just manually
created now that another minute has
passed if I do K get jobs again we can
see two jobs have been created
automatically and we have the manually
triggered one that I created via the
command line this can be a useful
technique if you're actively iterating
on a job and want to make sure that your
updated configuration is working uh
without having to wait till the next
instance of that Chron schedule occurs
another type of application that you
might want to run on a kubernetes
cluster is one that requires having an
instance on each of our different nodes
and so for that we use what is called a
demon set the types of applications that
would use this are things like uh log or
metrics aggregation you often want to
have one copy of your application
running on each node where it can scrape
those logs or metric and propagate them
to some other system uh you might want
to do some sort of monitoring of the
node itself or if you're needing to do
something like setup storage on those
nodes having that application running
locally is necessary or improves
performance in these examples here I'm
using a different container because
using the enginex image wouldn't make
much sense here instead I'm using a a
container image fluent d uh fluent D is
a log shipping agent in this case it's
not configured to send those logs
anywhere but I figured I should at least
use an application that would make sense
in this context on the left hand side
we've got a standalone pod definition
and then on the right hand side we see
that pod definition Maps into the spec
portion of our Damon set template just
like with our deployment we're going to
use the match label selector to align
our demon set resource with the pods
that it creates and manages and by
default a demon set is going to run one
copy on every node except for the
control plane nodes you can modify this
and for example have it run on a subset
of those nodes based on particular
conditions or you could modify it so
that it does run on the control plane
nodes if that were necessary let's jump
to our code editor and deploy a Damon
set to see how it behaves we'll navigate
to the Damon set
directory we'll create our
namespace and now let's create our Damon
set
as you can see it created two pods I'm
going to do KGET pods - wide and by
doing so we get some additional
information that's not included by
default and the part that we care about
here is the node that the Pod is running
on as we can see this was in my kind
cluster we've got our control plane node
and our two worker nodes the demon set
automatically spawned one copy on each
of the two worker nodes but not on the
control plane node as I mentioned before
you're often going to encounter demon
sets uh when working with things like
log and metrics aggregation so for
example if you were installing data dog
into the cluster you're going to run uh
their data dog agent as a demon set so
it can collect the the necessary
information from each of those nodes and
that brings us to the fourth and final
built-in workload type within kubernetes
uh that is the stateful set so a
stateful set is going to be quite
similar to a deployment uh except that
it is designed for stateful workloads
and because of this each pod within the
stateful set each replica is going to
have a stable or sticky identity so
rather than having a random hash at the
end of the Pod names we're going to have
A- 0-1 an ordinal within a deployment if
we were to have used persistent volumes
each replica would have shared a single
volume however in a stateful set each
pod is going to have its own separate
volumes and then finally the roll out
behavior is ordered so it's going to go
in sequence from 012 Etc versus with a
deployment there's no specified order in
which kubernetes replaces each pod goal
of the stateful set is to enable
configuring workloads that require some
sort of State management such that each
pod in the stateful Set uh May behave
slightly differently for example if you
have a database configuration where one
of the pods is the primary and the other
pods are read replicas you could use a
stateful set to handle that type of
thing because each pod has that sticky
identity and is maintaining its
connection to its own separate storage
volume you'll notice that the minimal
example here on the right is a bit more
involved than many of our other resource
types uh that is because in order to
Showcase some of the features of the
stateful set I needed to add an init
container and as you can see the inet
container here is running a little bash
script that bash script is storing a
HTML snippet into a path on the file
system and that file system path happens
to be in a volume that is shared between
the primary container and the init
container and so by doing this the init
container will come up it will store
that HTML snippet containing the ordinal
number of the Pod into the volume and
then when the primary container comes up
it will load that this type of approach
of using an init container to store a
specialized configuration for each
replica based on which number in the
stateful set it is is a technique that
you can use such that you can have
different configurations loaded into
each of our replicas so that they can
know whether or not they need to act as
the primary read replica Etc or whatever
configuration you're using for your
application one thing to note here is in
that volume claim template section we
haven't covered persistent volumes or
persistent volume claims yet those are
coming soon but in order for this
stateful set to run successfully that
storage class name standard needs to
exist in your cluster I believe for the
kind cluster and the gke cluster that
I've spun up for this course those have
out of the box a storage class named
Standard so it will work I think the COO
cluster by default it has a storage
class but it is not named Standard so
you would need to update this to use the
storage class that exists or create a
new storage class named Standard to be
compatible stateful sets could be a
course in and of themselves uh there are
as many types of configuration for a
stateful application as there are
stateful applications that exist and
there are a number of shortcomings
associated with the stateful set in
kubernetes specifically a big one is
that you can't modify many of these
fields after it's been created for
example you can't modify the resource
request or storage size of that
persistent volume after the stateful set
has been created even though in newer
versions of kubernetes you can resize a
volume but the stateful set in order to
main backwards compatibility only allows
modifying very few Fields within its
spec there are some approaches that
projects have used to try and get around
this they're outside the scope of this
course and I think a deep dive on
stateful sets is important if you plan
to run significant stateful applications
on top of kubernetes let's jump over to
the code editor deploy a stateful set
and see how it behaves we'll navigate to
the stateful set
directory we'll create our namespace
and then let's apply that definition
containing the init container so I'll
load it here just to remind
ourselves we're going to have three
replicas I'm also explaining here that
engine X is a bit silly to use as a
example for a stateful application
because generally it is run as a
stateless web server or proxy but I'm
demonstrating a common pattern where you
would use an init container to
pre-populate a customized config for
each replica and then load that within
the primary container to act accordingly
there's an example within the kubernetes
docs showing a similar pattern used for
a MySQL stateful set to set up one
replica as the primary and other
replicas as read replicas an important
field to call out here is this service
name field now each stateful set is
expected to have what is known as a
headless service associated with it and
so in this case I'm naming it engine X's
plural and it's plural because it's
going to be a headless service where we
are able to address each pod
independently the way that you create
this headless service is to specify a
cluster IP service but you specify the
the field cluster IP set to none in this
case it will not create an internal IP
address that load balances across the
resources instead we'll be able to
address each pod directly via DNS inside
the cluster so if I run the apply with
init
command we first created a regular
cluster IP service that would route
across all three of the pods in my
stateful set we then created The
Headless service service. engine access.
yaml and then finally we applied our
stateful set definition including that
in a container when we first created it
it's in a pending
State we see that the first pod has come
up and is running now the second pod
should be coming up and then the third
pod as I mentioned instead of a random
hash in the name we get these sequential
ordinal numbers as our
postfixes and we''ve got our two ser
Services here this is our normal cluster
IP service if we were to Route traffic
to that if we were to Route traffic to
that it would get load balanced across
all three of these replicas and then
because we specified cluster IP none in
the Headless service we don't have a
cluster IP specified however this will
set up the DNS required such that we can
address each of those pods independently
let's port forward to one of our pods
and now if we access it from the
browser and refresh we see hello from
pod zero if we were to instead port
forward to container number
one and reload we get hello from pod
number one and so the way that we set
that up was within our init container we
used the host name environment variable
stripped out that ordinal and injected
it into the statement which was stored
here that file exists on this volume
which is loaded by our primary container
as well and so when Engine X comes up
this is the default index file that
engine X is going to serve as I
mentioned we could spend hours on
stateful sets alone I'm not going to do
that in this course however I'll
reiterate that if you do plan to run
significant stateful workloads on top of
kubernetes I would certainly do a deep
dive on stateful sets and how to use
them effectively and safely now that
we've covered all the primary workload
resource types we can start to look at
how we would configure these for each
specific environment one of the primary
tools for doing this is known as a
config map it enables you to have
environment specific configuration and
decouple those from the deployment and
the container images that those are
running there's two primary styles of
config maps that you'll see the first
one is to use property like keys and so
in this case these Keys generally
represent environment variables that
you're going to inject into a container
running in a pod or file like keys where
you have a configuration file that your
application is expecting to load at
runtime I'm showing two examples here on
the bottom left the first one is the
property like Keys one where we've got a
name a version and an author
specified and then the second one is
more of that file like key style where
the key is conf. yaml and then the value
is a multi-line string containing those
same contents I've used all uppercase in
the property like Keys as a convention
if they're going to get injected as
environment variables but lowercase or
camel case potentially in the file light
Keys version based on how you might
expect to see a configuration file on
the right hand side is a podspec
consuming these two config Maps property
like Keys config map is used in the N
from field it's going to load all of the
contents of that config map in as
environment variables and then the file
like Keys config map is added as a
volume and mounted into the file system
at/ Etsy config within that POD at that
location in the file system there will
be a conf. yaml containing those values
let's jump to our code editor and see
how this works we'll navigate to the
config map
subdirectory we'll create our
namespace and as you can see I've got
those same yl configurations that I
showed on the slide here in my editor as
well as the Pod that consumes them I'm
going to go ahead and apply all three of
those
we can do K get config maps and see that
we have the file like Keys config map
the property like Keys config map and
then a cube root certificate that was
created by the system we can ignore that
for now the Pod is up and
running in order to show you that the
file like config map was actually
mounted into the file system I'm going
to execute a cat command inside of that
container to show us the contents of
that file so this Cube C exec command
passing in the name of the Pod the name
of the container within the Pod so that
was specified here and then the the
command cat Etsy config com. yaml prints
out the contents of that file from the
container's file system so as you can
see these data from the config map were
injected into that volume mounted into
the file system and accessible from our
application to showcase the environment
variables version we can run run a print
n command inside that same pod so again
we're using the cube CTL exec command
this is going to pass a command into the
Pod itself this is the name of our pod
and the name of the container within the
Pod and here's the command we want to
run print environment is going to print
all the environment variables active
within that container we can see some
things that would have been there
already however we can see the three
values that we injected author your name
name your app name and version
1.0.0 as seen in our config map most
common applications are going to follow
one of these two patterns for loading in
config at runtime either from a file or
from environment variables this enables
you to decouple your environment
specific configuration from your common
configuration that could be used across
environments inevitably there's going to
be some configuration that is sensitive
that you want to protect with a higher
degree of security than the rest of your
configurations for these you can use the
kubernetes secret resource now these are
very similar to config Maps uh you're
going to consume them in the same way
VIA either environment variables or
mounting them into the file system uh
the main difference in their definition
is that the data within them is going to
be base 64 encoded uh it's important to
note this is not a security mechanism it
is in order for the secrets to be able
to support binary data as well as string
data just because it looks like it's a
little bit scrambled when you view it
that doesn't mean it's encrypted uh and
you should still treat those encoded
data as sensitive when you are setting
up and managing a clust cluster you can
specify an encryption configuration that
tells kubernetes if or how they should
be encrypted in the etcd data store some
managed clusters are going to handle
this for you others are not definitely
look into these policies if you're are
trying to meet a specific security
standard with your clusters also because
they're a separate resource type within
kubernetes you can manage and control
them with separate authorization
policies than config Maps such that
certain users are able to read them and
certain users are able to write to them
control that dependently of other
kubernetes resource types I've shown two
definitions of Secrets here at the
bottom the first of which is using the
first of which is using the string data
type and so this is a convenience that
allows you to Define your manifest in
plain text as you can see I have the key
Fu and the value bar and then when you
apply this to the cluster kubernetes
will base 64 en code the value on the
right hand side I'm specifying the data
directly and in this case the key is in
plain text but the value is the base 64
encoded version of bar as you can see
from the podspec on the right you
consume them in pretty much the same way
you do config Maps either as environment
variables or as volumes mounted into the
file system however I've shown an
additional option here instead of
loading the entire contents of the
secret as an environment variable you
can specify the specific key within that
secret that you want to load in this
case I'm referencing the base 64 data
secret and loading only the contents of
the fu variable and and those will get
placed at the nvar from Secret
environment variable the M from option
that I showed for config Maps also works
I wanted to show how you would pull a
specific key value pair out of a secret
and how you would map it to a different
environment variable name within your
container let's jump over to our code
editor create some secrets and see how
they work first I'll navigate to the
secret
subdirectory and create my
namespace now let's start by creating
that secret as shown with the string
data I can do
T O2 so that's applying this file uh
you'll notice the type is specified as
opaque that is the default type of
secret and if I now get that secret and
do o yl to Output it in yl and I'll pipe
that to yq just so we get a nicely
formatted value you can see that even
though I'm specifying it in plain text
here within the secret itself when we
look at the value you see under data we
have the keyue and then this value bar
which is base 64 encoded if you ever
want to get the value out of a secret
and base 64 decode it you can use yq
similarly so we can get the secret we
need to pass the name of the
secret we'll do output in yo format
we'll pipe that to yq then we can get
the dash data key now we can get the
dash we can get the fu key within the
data and finally we can pipe that to
base
64- D and as you can see decoded we get
our value back so if there's ever a
secret where you need to look up the
contents of that's generally how I do it
we can create the same
secret we can create a secret with the
same contents using the data directly by
specifying this value as base 64 encoded
data in order to generate this value you
might think oh I'll just do Echo and
pipe that to Bas 64 however if you do an
echo in the Shell it's going to add a
new line to the end and that actually
gets included in the base 64 encoding
which will give you the wrong value when
you're trying to use that password or
something so instead it can be useful to
use print F instead of echo to base 64
and code we can do
T3 here I'm doing print F of bar piping
that to base 64 watch what happens if I
do Echo bar into base
64 we get a different value because
there's actually a new line character
being added by Echo and it's getting
encoded here so we want to make sure not
to have that happen so be careful when
you are generating your base 64 encoded
strings uh to not include new lines in
them if we tried to decode this and then
pass that to let's say our database or
something we would get denied because
it's the wrong password we could go
ahead and apply this secret definition
as well now we've got our two Secrets
here once again I can get the value
out by doing this great there's other
types of Secrets Beyond opaque for the
gener generic case where you're storing
a password opaque is going to be the
right type but there's also what is
known as a Docker config Json type
secret and this is used by kubernetes to
authenticate to a container registry so
if you have a private container registry
you'll be able to pull images and use
those images by specifying a secret like
this uh as you can see it is using that
file like syntax where we have a Docker
config Json file as the key and then
this is a base 64
encoded Json which will get used by the
container runtime to pull those images
so let's Echo this and we'll do a base
decode we'll pipe that to JQ and as you
can see we get our output in Json format
it contains a offs key and in this case
it's a username and password for the
dockerhub uh container registry just
using a dummy username and password as
an example uh this off block is again
Bas 64 encode
and just contains the username and
password together rather than try and
construct this with the exact right
format and then base 64 and code uh
there is a cctl command that allows us
to create such a file and so in this
case I'll do
t7 here I'm doing cctl create secret I'm
naming it Docker registry I'm selling it
to use the docker config Json type and
then as options on the command line you
can pass in your email your username
your password and the docker server so
in this case it is the dockerhub server
and it will create that secret for us so
I suggest you can use this style of
command to create it you could
even do a-- dry
run equals
client yo and now instead of creating it
on the server it's giving you this value
effectively using the cube CTL command
line to generate a properly formatted
value rather than creating that secret
imperatively this allows you to then
store these values in your secret
manager of choice for future
consumption now we've looked at opaque
secrets that's for arbitrary user
defined data so think username and
password for various sets of credentials
uh we just looked at the docker config
Json secret used for storing credentials
to container Registries the other ones
that are useful to know about are the
TLs type so these will be used for store
in TLS client and server data uh if
you're setting up applications that you
connect to over https potentially using
something like C manager you'll notice
that it uses these TLS type secrets and
then also the service account token type
secret uh kubernetes uses service
accounts to Grant access to things
within the cluster and the way that you
utilize those service accounts are via
these tokens those four types are the
most commonly used the other ones exist
but I don't use them all that frequently
all right we're in the home stretch only
a few more built-in resources that we're
going to cover here the next two are
related to how to get network traffic
from outside the cluster into your
cluster and Route those to your various
Services uh the first one is called
Ingress and the second one is a newer
API called Gateway API we'll be covering
them both here effectively Ingress
allows you to Route traffic from a
single external load balancer so this
could be something from your cloud
provider and those to a number of
internal cluster IP Services there's a
whole bunch of implementations of this
API that you can choose from uh the
most one of the most common is called
Ingress engine X but there's many
projects out there ha proxy Kong ISO
traffic uh that implement the Ingress
API and allow you to Route traffic in
this way I'll call out that the Ingress
specification only supports layer 7even
routing so think HTTP and https
but many of the implementations have
layer 4 routing so TCP and UDP uh with
additional configuration and often times
those additional configurations are
managed via kubernetes annotations and
so if it doesn't have a field in the
official schema the way that controllers
get around this is by enabling you to
provide custom configuration via
annotations which you can provide as
arbitrary key value pairs looking at the
definition here this is the most minimal
Ingress you can Define it's essentially
saying route all traffic because I have
the root path there and it's a path type
prefix so anything will match that and
it is targeting the enginex cluster IP
backend you specify information about
the request that should be routed and
then where you want that to go in this
case it's to that cluster IP on port
number 80 looking at the diagram you can
see that the traffic will come in from
outside of our cluster it will hit a
load balancer at which point it will be
routed to the Ingress controller pod so
that is a pod running internal to the
cluster that pod is looking at our
Ingress resources and setting up the
rules accordingly So based on our
Ingress let's say we're running Ingress
enginex it's going to read our Ingress
object and configure the the enginex
configuration internal to that pod
automatically to Route traffic
accordingly based on our rules within
our Ingress resource we can then use
information such as the path to Route
traffic between different services so
service a or service B which will in
turn send that traffic to our pods I'm
going to go ahead and cover Gateway API
here and then we'll jump into the code
editor and show examples of both Gateway
API is a newer kind of evolution of the
Ingress API and it came from the fact
that many people felt the Ingress API
spec didn't meet their needs fully it's
important not to confuse this with the
generic concept of an API Gateway uh
they have very similar names but Gateway
API is the specific kubernetes API an
API Gateway is the general concept of a
cloud resource that can take API calls
and Route them to various services so
one is kind of just a general concept
and one is the specific API this does
add official support for layer 4 routing
and it has support for more advanced
routing scenarios built into the
specification itself we can define
something similar to the Ingress we saw
on the previous slide where in this case
it's an HTTP route which is under that
Gateway API specification I'm matching a
path prefix of the root prefix so just
like before and I'm pointing it to that
backend reference of the engine X
cluster IP so this HTTP route is going
to behave pretty much identically to the
Ingress that we saw prior looking at the
diagram you can see again traffic's
coming in from outside the cluster and
hitting our load balancer it's then
routed to our Gateway controller that
Gateway controller is monitoring the
cluster for Gateway and Route resources
and configuring its routing based on
those resource rules and finally it's
able to Route our Network traffic
according to those rules to the
different Services which then send the
traffic to our pods Gateway API has been
in progress and under development for a
number of years uh it has it graduated
to Beta in 2022 and it graduated to
General availability in 2023 uh when I
did a poll across Twitter and Linkedin
asking the percentage of people that
were using Ingress versus Gateway API to
bring traffic into their clusters it's
still quite split I think more people
were still using Ingress uh just because
of the fact that it exists and there's
some cost to switching over um however
if you were doing Green Field
development it could pay to use to go
ahead and use the Gateway API because
that is kind of the standard moving
forward let's go ahead and deploy some
of these and see how they behave let's
start with the Ingress so we can
navigate to our Ingress folder we'll
create our
namespace and for this example I'm going
to be using our my gke cluster uh one of
the reasons is that it supports the
Gateway API out of the box whereas the
COO cluster does not we could still
install a third party Gateway API
controller however I'm going to start
with Google Cloud here because it does
support G the Gateway apis out of the
box it's a configuration we had to set
when we provisioned our cluster but it
doesn't require any additional software
installation we now need to create a
service that is going to listen and
reply to our traffic so I'll go ahead
and create a deployment for
that and then deployment is just going
to be a minimal engine X deployment with
three replicas and pretty much all
default settings now let's apply our
service the first type of service that
we're going to deploy here in front of
that deployment is a node Port service
and the reason for that is that the the
built-in GK load balancer type that
Ingress uses has to be of type node Port
so we'll deploy this
service which is going to Route traffic
to the PODS of that engine X deployment
and as a reminder we're using the
selector to match the labels on the pods
where we're routing traffic 2 we also
have an Ingress definition here and the
way that we tell the cluster that we
want to use the Google Ingress
controller is by specifying this
annotation so it is of kind Ingress but
we tell it that it is using the Ingress
class of GCE this GCE Ingress class is
going to set up a external load balancer
uh you could however instead use the GC
internal class and that would set up a
load balancer in gcp but it would not be
publicly accessible it would only be
accessible from inside your virtual
private Cloud it is important to call
out here that another way that we could
configure this Ingress class and we will
for another Ingress controller would be
to use under the spec field the Ingress
class name that's not supported for GK
Ingress and so that's why we had to use
this more outdated annotation approach
let me go ahead and apply
that we started here by applying that
node Port definition and then we applied
this minimal gke Ingress now I specified
this host here when it's looking at when
this Ingress is looking at inbound
Network traffic it's going to look for
this host
to decide whether or not to Route
traffic to this back end you could have
this match all hosts such that all
traffic would go there but in more I
think it's more realistic that you're
going to be routing traffic from a
specific domain name in order to
simulate this I don't own this
particular domain but I can modify my
local Etsy /host file such that when I
when I make a request to this domain it
will actually route it to the proper
place let's go into the Google Cloud
console and find the address of the load
balancer that it
provisioned we can see that Ingress we
created show up here in the UI and it's
in a creating Ingress
status now as I click into it we see
that it is finished provisioning and
it's given us this external load
balancer with this IP address
so if I were to navigate to this IP
address directly it doesn't work that's
because we specified that host name in
our Ingress resource so now I need to
take
that and update the IP address I have
mapping to that Ingress example.com so
let me grab the IP
address
copy replace
this and now if I navigate to that in my
browser you can see I get the default
welcome to engine X page I don't have
TLS set up so this is an HTTP request
not an
https however you can see how that
traffic made it from my computer to the
load balancer to the node port to the
Pod itself now what if you were not
running on gke or another cloud provider
or you didn't want to use they're
built-in in Ingress controller now the
option there is to install your own
Ingress controller into the cluster so
in this case let's go ahead and install
Ingress engine x one of the most popular
implementations to do this I'm using a
tool called Helm we're going to learn
more about Helm in the next lesson
however it's essentially a package
manager I'm saying install the in
Ingress engine X Helm chart this is
where you can find that the definition
for that chart I want it to go into the
Ingress engine namespace if that
namespace doesn't exist go ahead and
create it and use version
4.10.1 it looks like it went ahead and
installed properly it's giving us some
examples here in the output of the
command but if I go okay get pods now in
the Ingress enginex namespace you can
see this controller is
running with that enginex controller
installed I can now create another
Ingress object in this case though I
could use the same an ation style to
specify which Ingress class but also I
can use spec. Ingress class name and
tell it to use
inex my actual rules here are pretty
much the
same one difference being here that I'm
just showing another option for the
different types of path types that exist
we used prefix in the previous example
here there are some enginex
implementation specific ones that you
can look up in the docs of how that will
behave let's go ahead and apply that
so for this I created a cluster IP
Service as well as this Ingress resource
and the reason that this is a cluster IP
is that because that engine x controller
is running in my cluster I don't need to
use a node port to access it I can
access it directly over a cluster IP
instead again I'm going to modify my
Etsy host file to match the load
balancer that engine X Provisions if we
look in the Ingress engine X
namespace at the services
you can see it has created a service of
load balancer type which then the cloud
controller manager is going to go off
and provision a load balancer for and so
now we have a load balancer that will
route to this pod and it will in turn
route via the Ingress to our other
deployment so let's update that
file this is for Ingress example
enginex we'll save
that and now if we go up here and load
this in our
browser you can see the same result and
so this is just showing we have two
separate implementations of this Ingress
specification one provided by Google one
provided by the open source in Ingress
enginex project there's many more
choices but this just showcases how you
have choices around which implementation
of this API you actually want to
use now each of those external load
balancers that gka provisioned are going
going to be charged per month in
addition to your normal cluster uh
compute and so I'm going to go ahead and
delete those two ingresses just so I'm
sure that those get torn down in the
background and I'm not getting charge
extra for
them so I'll do K delete Ingress and I'm
in the proper namespace already because
when I created the namespace Cubs set it
as my default so I'll just say all and
you can see the two ingresses were
deleted I'm also going to delete the
Ingress engine X namespace because it
also provision that external load
balancer that should delete all the
resources inside of that namespace
including that service let's jump to the
Gateway API uh directory and we can see
how it behaves quite similarly but maybe
slightly different we'll create our
namespace and set it as the default so
now we're in that 04-- Gateway API
namespace we're going to create a
deployment just like before the
deployment is our basic three replica
engine X deployment
and just like with Ingress I'm going to
show two different implementations here
of
the Gateway
API specification the first one is going
to be the buil-in gke implementation and
if you'll remember let's just go look at
our setup for gke if I look at where I
provisioned the cluster I passed it this
Gateway API equals standard uh if you
didn't pass this at all it would not
enable the Gateway API here I'm saying
use the standard definition
the two resources that we need to deploy
to Route traffic via the Gateway API to
our deployment uh first we need to
deploy the Gateway and so in this case
we'll give it the Gateway class name
there's a few different names here that
you can look up in the gka documentation
effectively this is saying I want a gke
layer 7 so layer 7 networking Global
external managed load balancer so this
is quite similar to the the external
load balancer that was provisioned by
the Ingress controller it is important
call out here that the gke Gateway API
implementation does not support uh TCP
routes currently I think that is in
progress um but it only supports HTP
routes so that's important to call
out and so from that perspective it does
not fully support the Gateway API spec
however I believe they plan to support
that in the future so if you did use
this likely in the future that support
will be added you then set up a an array
of listeners in this case I'm saying I
want this to listen on Port 80 using
HTTP route types and then from this
Gateway I can specify any number of
these HTTP routes which will have the
actual routing rules that I want it to
follow let's take a look at what that
looks like note here the name of the
Gateway is gke so in the HTTP route
definition the parent ref here that's
what it's referring to the parent ref is
that Gateway resource
you can see it contains pretty much the
same information as the Ingress just
moved around a little bit we're saying
for the host name Gateway example gke I
want to import I want to follow this
rule where
any request is sent to my enginex
nodeport backend and again this only
supports nodeport types for that backend
service again let's go ahead and create
it we can see the Gateway resource
we can see our HTTP route resource once
that Gateway is healthy we should see
the stat the address and the programmed
status
change we can describe
it you see it was added 37 seconds
ago it was then synced a number of
times right now it's effectively waiting
for
the controller to go off and provision
that external load balancer let's go
ahead and look in the
UI under
gateways we see it here it says waiting
to be accepted not sure what that
means okay it looks like whatever it was
waiting on accepted it and it's now in a
healthy status and we have that external
IP address for the load
balancer it shows here the address and
it tells us that now it is
programmed once again I'll modify my
Etsy host
file with the Gateway example gke
entry we'll go ahead and load that in
our browser and once again we're routed
to our deployment perfect
now finally just as one more example
let's use a third party Gateway API
implementation many of the ones that I
found were only partially supported uh
or in various states of working SL
broken uh one that worked right away for
me was the Kong Gateway
API we're going to go ahead and install
the Kong Ingress
controller again we're going to use Helm
to install it uh we're passing it the
charts we're putting it in the Kong
namespace and we're installing version
0.12.0 Additionally the Kong
implementation uses different versions
of the custom resource definitions um
associated with the Gateway API we're
going to talk more about what custom
resource definitions or crds are down
the road um for now just notice that I'm
updating the versions of these to be
compatible with this new controller
if we look at the pods in the Kong
namespace we have our Kong controller
and our Kong
Gateway the three resources that we're
going to deploy alongside this to
actually use this implementation are the
Gateway class so in this case the
Gateway class for the gke one already
existed it was installed along with when
we set up the cluster um here we need to
tell it we need to create a Gateway
class which is going to say which
controller ought to be used and so you
can have multiple of these controllers
run alongside each other in the cluster
and specify which controller you want to
use via this Gateway class
mechanism so I'm telling it to use my
Kong Gateway class
controller the Gateway itself is going
to look very similar to the GK one the
only difference is that now instead of
specifying the Google specific Gateway
class name I'm specifying Kong as my
Gateway class
name and finally I'll have an HTTP route
which again looks pretty much identical
the one difference being I'm routing to
this cluster IP service because at this
point the Kong control is running in the
cluster and doesn't need to use that
node Port whereas gke is sort of
interfacing at the external load
balancer layer and configuring it so it
has to Route traffic to the cluster via
no Port the Kong Gateway controller is
already running in the cluster and so
it's able to use that cluster
IP I'll apply all three of those
resources I've added the this little
warning out of the box the Kong Ingress
controller does not support the TCP
routes similar to the GK one by default
it's only enabling it's only using the
HTTP type routes there's an additional
documentation here on how if you want to
use TCP routes you can set up the Kong
Ingress controller to do
so let's take a look at the
Gateway we can see the new Kong Gateway
is online it's given us an external IP
address if I look at the services in the
Kong name space we'll likely see a load
balancer type that matches
that yep see this Gateway is now using
this load balancer type service
perfect and let's look at our HTTP route
and we can see it's been created
here I'll add that entry to my Etsy host
file so I can access
it open a new browser tab paste it
in and there we
go I'll go ahead and delete this
namespace and the Kong namespace just to
clean things up
and make sure I'm not getting charged
for those external load
balancers but hopefully that gives you
an idea how to use Ingress and Gateway
API if you're building something new I
think I would suggest going down the
Gateway API route it will future proof
your system and allow you to take
advantage of those newer features if you
already are using Ingress and it's
working fine for your needs there's no
reason to switch over right away we
showed how to use the builtin Ingress
and gate API controllers on a managed
provider like gke but if your managed
provider doesn't include something like
that let's say you're working with civo
you would then want to install a
controller of your choice I believe SEO
clusters would have installed a traffic
Ingress controller by default I disabled
that so we could install our own uh but
you can pick whichever controller suits
your needs the next topic to cover is
how we can store data such that it will
persist across container restarts so
containers are great by themselves they
represent this ephemeral file system
that every time we create a new
container we're going to get a fresh new
system if we want data to persist across
those restarts we need to store those
data in what is known as a persistent
volume there are many different
implementations of persistent volumes
when you think of cloud providers these
are often going to be the block storage
devices that they offer so in Amazon it
would be EBS in gcp it's going to be a
compute engine persistent dis you can
also use things like Network file shares
as a persistent volume but essentially
the persistent volume and persistent
volume claims are kubernetes interface
for creating managing and consuming
storage that is going to outlive any
particular pod one of the most important
attributes of the storage are the access
modes so one of the most common ones
that you'll see are read write once and
that is saying that you can mount this
storage device with a single pod in a
read write mode so if it's already
mounted to a pod and you try to mount it
from another that second one would fail
this is how most of those block storage
devices are going to behave there's a
little Nuance here in that read write
once you actually could have multiple
pods mount it in a read write fashion if
they were on the same node uh because
it's associated with which node the
container is running on and so there's a
new version of this that is read write
once pod which actually limits it to a
single pod regardless of whether or not
the other pods are on the same node
there's also read only many and this
says you can have multiple pods mount it
but only in a readon fashion you would
use this if you needed multiple pods to
pull data from a single Source but the
underlying storage didn't have a way to
deconflict multiple rights at the same
time and then readwrite many is going to
be the case where you can have multiple
pods across multiple nodes all mounting
this volume and reading and writing to
it at the same time those underlying
implementations need to support handling
those multiple rights in a consistent
fashion these will often be things like
NFS systems which are already designed
to handle this type of use case but
generally we'll have limitations in
other areas such as the speed at which
you can access data and then another
very important configuration spec here
is the reclaim policy for the storage
class and this is whether or not when
the persistent volume claim is deleted
what should happen to the underlying
persistent volume uh in the retain case
that persistent volume and therefore the
dis that it provisioned or the volume it
provisioned in the cloud would remain
versus if it's set to delete when you
delete that persistent volume claim that
underlying persistent volume will also
go away so retain can be a bit safer but
may leave some unattached persistent
volumes that have no consumer in your
cluster that you'll have to clean up
manually if those data are no longer
needed you can provision persistent
volumes and persistent volume claims
directly or within a stateful set you
can provide a template that will
provision them dynamically in the
specifications here on the slide I've
shown a storage class so these storage
classes are going to be what Maps the
persistent volume to an underlying
implementation I'm showing here the one
for the Theo implementation of a
persistent volume that maps to their
volume object and then I'm showing a
persistent volume claim which uses that
storage class to provision a persistent
volume behind the scenes there you can
see that access mode as well as the size
of the volume that we will be
provisioned in our diagram you can see
that a
pod is going to specify one of two
things either a volume claim template in
the case of a stateful set that will
enable a dynamic provisioning of the
persistent volume or in other cases a
persistent volume claim which is
provision directly that persistent
volume claim is going to consume a
persistent volume and so persistent
volume maps to the underlying storage
and a persistent volume claim is the Tie
between that storage and the pods
consuming it the Pod consuming it is
either going to specify a storage class
which can dynamically provision the
underlying storage
or for example if you're operating an
on- premise environment in an on-
premisis environment you could
pre-provision the underlying storage and
then Define a persistent volume that
manually maps to that persistent
storage this is a case where the
underlying implementation across
clusters is going to be different and so
I'm actually going to demonstrate this
on all three of our different clusters
the kind cluster the COO cluster and the
gka cluster so we can get a feel for how
these
behave the first thing that we're going
to do is manually provision a persistent
volume and a PVC as well as a pod to
consume it using our kind cluster so
I'll switch to Our Kind
cluster I'll then create the namespace
and now let's look at the definition of
those in the kind subdirectory I've got
this persistent volume definition I'm
naming it manual kind specifying how
large it should be the access mode and
which storage class I can look at the
storage classes in my cluster by doing K
get storage classes as you can see I
have one storage class that was created
by default by my kind cluster using this
Rancher local path provisioner so it's
going to be a local path Within in my
host system for this type of storage
class I need to specify a path and so
here this could be anything but I'm
putting this sum path and container as
an example and I'm specifying that it
needs to be on a specific worker node in
my cluster now my persistent volume
claim is going to align is going to find
that persistent volume using the match
labels selector so as we
saw I have this label here on my
persistent volume
and then the persistent volume claim
uses that same label to find
it I'm saying that I want to use my
entire 100 megabytes that I provisioned
again specifying my access mode and the
storage class name finally I have a pod
here that I'm going to create which is
going to use the persistent volume
claim as a volume and mount it in at a
path within my container so let me go
ahead and deploy all that with T2
as you can see we created our persistent
volume we created our persistent volume
claim and our pod to consume it we can
look at our persistent
volume we can see that it has been
created and is in a bound status because
we're consuming it from that
po look at our
PVC you can see that it maps to our
manual
volume and then finally our pod
and it's running if we do- o
wide we see it's running on the specific
worker that I
mentioned that is where we provision
that manual persistent
volume let's exec into that
container and navigate to the Mount path
for the volume
if I cat that file hello from host we
see high from number
one when we set up our kind cluster that
is one of the things I did within the
kind config is put a host path this is a
absolute path on my host file system and
mounted it into the Container path at
the same path I used in my persistent
volume
because of this this file that exists on
my host system is now showing up inside
this
pod I can now create a new file
here go up here to my directory on my
host system and I see that file was just
created so this is just showcasing how
that host path volume connected between
my host system and the container if
you're working with a kubernetes cluster
on premises you may be using something
like this where you're creating volumes
that map to paths on your physical host
so that shows the manual creation of
persistent volumes and persistent volume
claims let's now look at how you can
dynamically provision these in this case
we don't actually need a persistent
volume we can specify a persistent
volume claim directly and use a storage
class
name such that kubernetes can go ahead
and provision that for us you'll notice
that we don't have a selector here
because there is no persistent volume
already in existence with a set of
labels we want to match to I'm also
finding a deployment
here which is going to consume that
persistent volume claim so here under
volumes I have my persistent volume
claim and the name that I gave
it and again mounting because this
volume type is readr once these pods can
only run simultaneously
on the same node if they were scheduled
onto separate nodes one of them wouldn't
be able to mount the persistent
volume let me go ahead and deploy
that you can see they were both
scheduled onto the same worker which
they had to be in order to be able to
mount that
same persistent volume and this is an
interesting thing about how deployments
versus stateful sets work with
persistent volumes in the case of a
deployment if you specify a persistent
volume claim all of the replicas are
going to mount the same one in the case
of a stateful set they will each get an
independent persistent volume
claim now like I said stateful sets
consume these slightly differ let's go
ahead and look at how a stateful set
would Define its persistent volumes so
now rather than needing to create a
persistent volume claim separate from
the deployment instead we have a section
of our specification called a volume
claim
template here you give it a
name and you give it a specification and
this will be used for each replica it
will go off and provision it its own
persistent volume claim using the
information
provided in this case I'll have two
replicas and I'm creating my headless
service just because every stateful set
is supposed to have
one with the deployment both of those
replicas came up right away with a
stateful set set they come up in
series okay the first one is
running the second one is running and if
we look at the persistent volume claims
now you can
see for the for the dynamic PVCs from
the deployment there's only one which is
shared across the two pods for the
stateful set each one gets its own
individual PVC
each of these will have a corresponding
persistent
volume and they're all bound to the four
pods that are currently
running hopefully that gives you an idea
of the different paths for which you can
provision these types of things you can
manually specify them you can
dynamically specify them and there's a
different Behavior between those
dynamically specified deployments and
stateful sets let's also go ahead and
deploy a version of the stateful set
onto coo and onto gke
to do this I'll switch to my coo
cluster and I'll deploy
T5 if I navigate to the COO
subdirectory you can see I've got my
stateful set defined here it looks
identical to the one I deployed into my
kind cluster with the only difference
being the storage class name is
different if I get the storage classes
within this cluster
you can see it has that SEO volume that
was provisioned by default by the by SEO
when the cluster was created it's using
this coo CSI provisioner remember we
talked about the container storage
interface in the previous lesson this is
where that comes into
play where a different driver can be
used to interact with the different
underlying implementations of that
storage
provider if I look at the pods
now we see it's in a container creating
state
we can see the underlying PVC here now
if I go to the UI I can see that volume
created within the SEO Cloud outside of
my cluster let's see if it has fully
spun up with the
Pod still in container creating State
let's describe
it it's saying unavailable volume not
available presumably that will resolve
over time let's give it a little bit of
time let me check
again okay so now my first pod is
running and my second pod is creating
that should have created the PVC behind
the scenes and so let me refresh here
and see if another volume has been
created there it is it should be
spinning up and so because these behind
the scenes are going off and
provisioning another resource within the
cloud provider it can take a little
longer on my behind cluster I was just
mapping to a path on the host file
system and so it was very very quick in
these cases I need to make an API call
to the COC Cloud the volume needs to
provision it needs to be attached to the
cluster Etc so there can be a little bit
more of a delay when provisioning these
Cloud resources however they do enable
you to scale much more because you're no
longer tied to the specific storage
devices on your system uh you're
provisioning and attaching as much
additional storage as you want via these
volumes all right now both of our pods
have come up they dynamically provision
the underlying PVCs let's do the same on
Google it's going to look almost
identical but just showcasing how it
would work I'm going to delete this
staple set I'm going to go ahead and
clean those
up and we can move over to the uh GK
cluster we'll create our
namespace if we look at the storage
classes here there are three different
storage classes provided the standard
which uses the kubernetes io Google
compute engine persistent disc one that
one is included in the kubernetes
Upstream so before the CSI existed the
implementation for these lived in the
kubernetes project themselves uh and
then afterwards the individual CSI
storage drivers were created and so
there's three classes this one uses the
older implementation these two use the
newer implementation as you can see the
standard read write once is the default
and so in my storage class name here I'm
using that standard read write once
option otherwise it should be pretty
much identical to my SEO one let's go
ahead and deploy
it okay as you can see the first pod is
already up so the volume creation on gke
was quite fast it's creating that second
one now and if we navigate to the cloud
console
and go to compute
engine here are the two nodes in our
cluster but if we go to
diss these two are the discs attached to
my two nodes and these two are the discs
that I just provisioned for my stateful
set awesome let me go ahead and delete
my stateful
set those are now
gone there is a configuration on the
persistent volume claim itself uh that
defines
what the behavior is when the underlying
resource consuming it is deleted
historically this would just remain now
you can specify both when deleted and
when scaled what will happen and so the
when scaled makes sense in the case
where you have a stateful set which may
be scaled up or down let's say you had
five replicas you scale to four what
should happen to that fifth persistent
volume claim uh and then the when
deleted is if you delete the stateful
set
entirely in this case the default
behavior is to retain if you wanted them
to be cleaned up automatically you could
specify it as delete as you can see I
did not include this in my specification
here and so it defaulted to retain and
it stayed in place right so the the
reclaim policy on the
PVC specifies what happens when we
delete that PVC should the underlying
persistent volume and therefore the dis
in the cloud provider remain or should
it be deleted as well whereas the
persistent volume claim retention policy
specifies what should happen when the
consumer is scaled or deleted let me go
ahead and delete these two PVCs to
delete the underlying volumes hopefully
that gives you a sense of how to work
with persistent volumes in the various
different configurations and how you
would use them to store and persist your
data outside the life cycle of any
particular pod as you host stateful
applications on kubernetes understanding
these behaviors is going to be very
important to to ensure that your data
are safe the next topic that we need to
cover is how you can grant access to
either applications or users to the KU
API so each of these resource types that
we've been talking about you can Define
permissions associated with them and
allow or disallow access based on those
permissions for your applications to be
able to make calls to the kubernetes API
and interact you can grant these access
on a per namespace basis or on a cluster
wide basis and we're going to show how
to do both of these as an example to
demonstrate this I've written a very
simple job in the bottom right here
which runs a container using the cube
CTL command line which is just going to
is issue a cube CTL get pods command
either in the default namespace and then
I have a variant that tries to get them
across all namespaces if you didn't
include any additional information about
a service account the default
permissions would deny this access and
this job would fail however we can grant
this access by creating a service
account in this case namespace pod
reader creating a role which gives
access to get list and watch pods in the
default namespace and then binding that
Ro and service count together via a role
binding then within the template in our
job definition we can use that service
count and tell it to Auto Mount the
service count token so that our Cube CTL
command can use it and succeed I think
this will make more sense as we create
these roles and see how to behave when
they succeed and when they fail in an
actual cluster environment I'll navigate
to the arbac
subdirectory create my
namespace first let's create that job
with no service account and therefore no
permissions to query the kubernets API
if we take a look at what that job looks
like it's like the one from the slide
but we have not specified a surface
account and we've not specified anything
about that surface count token now if I
do a k get
pods we can see it's errored it's tried
again and errored if we look at the logs
the error message tells us that the
surface account that's being used in
this case the default surface account in
my namespace is not allowed to run the
get pods command
if we want to Grant access to make that
command let's first start by doing it at
the namespace level so I'll start with
this surface account called namespaced
pod reader I'm also going to create a
role called a pod reader and so a ro
applies only within a namespace whereas
a cluster R applies across the entire
cluster and then I'm going to bind that
podre reader roll to my namespace pod
Reader Service account using this Ro
binding finally within my job
specification I'm now using the
namespace Pod Reader Service account I'm
specifying that it should Auto Mount the
service account token this was a change
that came into kubernetes a few versions
ago where historically it would
automatically mount a token associated
with the service account just by
specifying it now you have to set this
to true if you want that to happen and
then I'm issuing the get pods command
within specifically the o4 rback
namespace that I'm operating in so if I
do
T3 we created this we created the
service account the roll the roll
binding we created this job and then we
also created this job here I'm modifying
the command that I'm running so instead
of only trying to get pods in the
current name space I'm also trying to
get pods across all the
namespaces so if I do get pods
now this was my first job that failed
let me delete that just to clean it up
we have the first one which operated
only in the 04 rback Nam space and then
we have the second one which failed
retried and failed again and the reason
we only see two copies is because we set
this back off limit to one so that means
it fails once it tries one more time and
if that fails it stops let's look at the
logs from each of
these you can see the logs from the
successful pod show the pods that exist
within this namespace because that's
what the command was running and if we
issue
this we can see it is not authorized to
get Pods at the cluster scope because
the role that we specified only had
access within the namespace if we did
need access at the cluster level we
could use a cluster roll and a cluster
roll binding so now I have another
service account that I'm calling cluster
pod reader a cluster roll which has get
list and watch access to pods and this
will apply across all namespaces
and so you can specify any number of
rules here within a cluster R here I'm
granting access to pods but these could
be any kubernetes resource or any custom
resource which is defined down the road
also these verbs I'm specifying here
that it should have read access but if
you needed to have WR access you would
specify that in the verb section we then
have our cluster roll binding tying
together the surface count with the
cluster roll and finally we have
our job specification where we're
referencing the cluster pod reader and
accessing pods across all the name
spaces so I'll go ahead and apply
that we can see it is
running it has
completed it completed
successfully and let's look at the
logs here you see pods from across a
bunch of namespaces looks like this one
I hadn't cleaned up yet the current
namespace and the system
namespace and so it succeeded in getting
pods across all the namespaces so if you
ever need your workloads to access the
kubernetes API and resources within the
kubernetes API arbac and service
accounts are going to be the mechanism
to do that also while this course is not
focused on administrating kubernetes
clusters as you grant access to users of
the kubernetes cluster arbac is going to
perform in the same way where you're
going to specify which resources any
individual user or group of users is
allowed to access and what actions or
verbs they're allowed to take against
those resources the specific mechanism
for how you create a user account and
how you map it to a role or a cluster
role is going to are going to differ
across different managed clusters but
you will be using this rback system
under the hood and now that actually
brings us to the end of the built-in
kubernetes resource types that I wanted
to cover hopefully that gives you a lay
of the land of the different types of
resources that are available and how you
would use them to build out your
application architectures before we move
on though I do want to call out labels
and annotations we've used labels a
little bit throughout this section
specifically to tie things together and
allow referencing between for example a
deployment and the pods that it's
managing but in general labels should be
used for attaching key value pairs to
resources that can be used to identify
and organize kubernetes resources so
that example where you're tying a
service to a pod or a deployment to a
pod or perf examples where those are
identifiable labels that you have to
attach to these resources you also can
use labels when you're making your Cube
CTL queries or querying the API server
to filter the result often times you'll
include a label specifying what
application it is associated with so for
example you might have the name of your
application on it or you might specify a
version that the application is
running annotations similarly live
within the resource metadata however
they should be used for information that
is non-identifying the kubernetes system
often uses annotations to do things like
store configuration details or
deployment history we saw in the Ingress
section that many controllers use
annotations to add configuration beyond
the default specification I just wanted
to highlight the difference between
labels which should be used for
identifying information and annotations
which should be used for non-identifying
information and while annotation can be
used to configure behaviors like we saw
in the case of
Ingress it's important to call out that
they are arbitrary untyped strings with
no schema enforcement and so it is very
easy to make a mistake and fairly hard
to debug those mistakes and so when
using annotations in that way you'll
want to just be careful that you're
double-checking the values that you're
putting in and making sure that they
they're valid and perform the way that
you would like them to now it may felt
like we took forever in this section
that's because there are a ton of
built-in resources that kubernetes
provides I did want to call out a few
things that I am not covering here and
I'm I'm leaving these as an exercise for
the viewer they're useful to know about
but I didn't deem them critical for this
particular course and those are limit
ranges a limit range allows you to as a
kubernetes administrator govern the
number of resources that a particular
object kind can request
to prevent resources from being deployed
that take up the entirety of the cluster
resources Network policies are a
mechanism to control access from a
network standpoint across different
boundaries so you can say this set of
pods are the only ones that are allowed
to talk to this set of PODS it allows
you to declaratively specify the set of
allowable Network traffic patterns and
so applying Network policies can be a
great way to increase the security of
your cluster by preventing connectivity
from pods that shouldn't be talking to
each other other anyways the next two
mutating web hook configurations and
validating web hook configurations are
ways that you can either enforce
specific standard about characteristics
of the resources that you're deploying
for example you could have a validating
web hook configuration that required
every deployment to specify its memory
request and limit you could reject any
configurations that did not meet those
rules and so you can use validating web
hooks to enforce specific standards that
you care about and then mutating web
hooks actually allow you to take a
request to
deploy some resource and make a change
to it on the Fly this allows for some
really interesting Behavior Uh for
example you could automatically inject a
sidecar container that is performing
some functionality without the end user
needing to know about it or include it
in their definition the horizontal pod
autoscaler is a tool you can use to
automatically scale the number of
replicas within let's say a particular
deployment or stateful set based on
metrics that you define so you could
Scale based on the CPU usage uh that's
kind of included out of the box or you
can have custom metrics let's say you
have some Q processing workload the
length of that queue you could include
as a custom metric and scale accordingly
and then custom resource definitions are
one of the more interesting pieces of
kubernetes they essentially allow you
to extend the kubernets API and Define
resources that are not in this built-in
set that can be used for the specific
purposes of your application we're going
to cover this a little bit in a later
section because this is a really key
aspect of many of the tooling that is
built on top of kubernetes if any of
these additional resources sound like
they would be useful for your particular
application I Ur you to go look at the
documentation for them and figure out
how to use them for your particular use
case the final module in this Foundation
section is going to cover Helm in the
previous section we used Helm a couple
of times to install various tools such
as the engine X Ingress controller but
in those cases I kind of gloss over the
details and so I want to spend a little
bit of time getting you familiar with
Helm and how to use use it uh and what
Helm charts look like so that we'll be
able to use them effectively moving
forward there could be an entire course
on Helm I'm going to cover it relatively
quickly here and just touch on the most
important features you need to know
about in order to use the tool Helm has
become the de facto standard for
Distributing software that's going to
run on kubernetes uh many open- Source
projects or thirdparty tools that you
run in your cluster the way that you
will install them is via a Helm chart
it's kind of a combination of a package
manager and a templating engine so if
you're familiar with npm in the nodejs
ecosystem or maybe your package manager
for Linux or Brew for Mac OS uh it
allows you to take a set of resources
that you would deploy bundle them up and
store them in a repository somewhere
that other people can consume it also
has templating built in which allows you
to use a single Helm chart and specify a
configuration that will be relevant for
a particular environment so you can use
the same chart and container images
across different environments the
primary use cases are going to be
application deployment so as I described
installing thirdparty tools into your
cluster and environment management
meaning configuring applications across
different environments using the same
underlying resource there is a command
line tool called Helm that you will use
to interact with Helm charts uh we're
going to look at the install and upgrade
commands as well as the rollback
commands and then the diagram here on
the right shows how all the different
pieces of a Helm chart come together at
the top level you have a repository this
can either be a Helm repository or an
oci open container initiative repository
you can store Helm charts in either of
those within that will be one or more
Helm charts the helm chart itself is
structured having some metadata as well
as some templates and so those templates
are where the kubernets resource
definitions are going to live this will
be things like deployments Services
config Maps
Etc and then in the metadata there's a
values. yaml file this is going to be
the interface with which you can
configure and customize your templates
so you're going to specify a set of
values in that values file or pass them
in at runtime and those will get
templated in to your templates hence the
name and rendered out as kubernetes
manifests when we install a chart it's
going to create an object called a
release within our cluster and that
release will have the rendered version
of those templates and deploy them into
our cluster now the templating when when
you first look at it seems pretty simple
here we've got a pod and we're
substituting in whatever version is
specified in that values. EML file so
here you would use enginex and then the
tag is going to be whatever version
specified seems simple enough however
these templates can get pretty gnarly
pretty quickly uh this is an example I
think pulled from the MySQL Helm chart
and as you can see with all of those
curly braces it very quickly becomes
hard to interpret what the heck's going
on some of these sections are only going
to be included Ed conditionally others
are going to be using templated values
and the customization interface that
chart authors are defining can get
complex very quickly because they need
to account for all of the different
deployment scenarios that end users
might want to have and that is just one
aspect of working with Helm that can be
somewhat of a challenge there's a number
of features within Helm I'm going to
cover four that I think are the most
important in terms of templating uh the
first one is how to reference metadata
within your template you can reference
the chart object the release object or
the values object you can see here on
the bottom right under app version we
can actually
reference capital chart. apppp verion
and that's going to pull information
from our chart itself and pull that into
that templated value similarly we can
reference the release as you can see in
the name of my config map here I'm
templating in the release name as a
portion of the name that's going to get
rendered for the config map and then
with my values file I can reference any
field that's defined so here I'm using
values. config data or on the left I'm
using values. environment and checking
if I'm in the production environment or
not variables are also an important
concept on the left hand side I'm
defining a variable called n short it's
just going to be a shorter version of my
environment so if it is production I set
it to prod otherwise I set it to
non-prod then within my templates I can
reference that as you can see the nend
short field pulls that template in
references it and uses its
value in the config map Helm also
includes features for control flow so
conditionals meaning I can have values
that only render under certain
conditions so for example on the left
hand side when I'm defining that
variable I'm using a conditional on
whether or not the values. environment
value is production on the right hand
side I'm using a conditional to check if
a feature is enabled or not we also can
Loop over sets of values and the syntax
for that is the range so here I'm Val
I'm looping over some number of values
in the config data field within my
values. and for each of those I'm going
to add a new key to this config map
using these four Concepts you'll be able
to cover most of the templating
scenarios that you care about and you'll
be able to understand and parse most of
the templates that you read I've pulled
out a few examples that we can run
through in our clusters to get some
hands-on experience with Helm charts
both consuming a third party chart as as
well as authoring some simple charts of
our own now the first thing that I want
to do is navigate to my Helm folder and
then within this folder uh there's a
postgres folder and a charts folder
let's start with the postgres one this
one will be consuming a thirdparty Helm
chart so I'll create a namespace just to
isolate
things then the first thing that I need
to do is add the repo now before we do
anything else let's confirm that you
have Helm
installed this should be installed by
devbox here I'm using version 3 .1
15.0 this is Helm version 3 which runs
only as a client side tool many years
ago there was a previous version of Helm
that had a component you installed into
your cluster called tiller I think
that's old enough now that any chart
relying on that should be deprecated so
we're not going to cover it in detail
but just know that moving forward you
should be using at least Helm version 3
and it only operates on the client side
the first thing thing that I'm going to
do is issue the helm repo ad command
hand uh this adds the repo to my set of
Helm repositories in this case I'm
referring to a public repo hosted by
bitnami which is a company that gen that
develops many uh Helm charts and
referencing their repository here as you
can see I had already added this you
should add it to your Helm
configuration the next thing that I want
to do is issue the helm search repo
command on the bitnami repo and the
postgresql chart specifically asking for
the different versions that are
available so as you can see this chart
has been upgraded many times as well as
the application so this is the version
of postgrad that it's going to install
and this is the chart version associated
with that so as you can see there's many
versions available we're going to
actually install one of these newer
versions but not the newest version so
that we can show the process of an
upgrade I mentioned that there's both
Helm repositories and oci repositories I
just want to showcase there's a slightly
different approach you use when
interacting with oci repositories when
you're looking at the documentation for
a particular Helm chart it should tell
you whether or not it's a Helm repo or
an oci repo some tools actually offer
both in this case I can log into an oci
repository by issuing the helm registry
login and here Docker Hub is actually an
oci registry you'll use your dockerhub
username and password to log in great so
my login
succeeded and then we can't actually use
that Helm Search Command against an oci
repository there is a c I that was
installed via devbox called oros or ORS
I'm not sure how to pronounce it and you
can use this to interact with these OC
repos directly here I'm asking for the
set of tags within the dockerhub bitnami
charts registry for the postgressql
chart this should be the same set of
tags that are available via the helm
repo because bitnami hosts both as their
own Helm repository as well as an oci
repo on dockerhub now if you want to
view a local copy of the helm chart if
it's hosted on GitHub or something you
can go find the repository and look at
it directly there but you also can pull
the chart so I can issue a Helm pull
command referencing the repo and the
chart and a particular version and
you'll see within my postr SQL directory
I now have this tarball which contains
the contents of that chart I can unzip
that by issuing a tar dxcf and then the
name of my tarball and this will produce
a directory called postgres
which has the contents of the chart so
if I look at the chart. here is the
metadata associated with this chart you
can see the version you can see the name
of the chart you can see who is
maintaining the chart additional
keywords for Discovery purposes the
application version so this is the
application this is the postgres version
included in the chart Etc we also can
then look within this templates
subdirectory and we see that if we
deploy this it's going to deploy some
combination of a bunch of ro-based
access control things it's going to
deploy a stateful set a service some
monitoring capabilities a network
policy a configuration each of these is
going to have all sorts of templating
built in this Helm chart also has the
ability to deploy a backup Crown job to
help you back up your database and so by
pulling it you can explore locally and
also look at the values. file so this is
going to contain all of the available
configuration options that that we can
modify for our specific purposes so we
could pass in things like what we want
the password and username and default
database to be we could store those in
an existing secret so that we don't have
to pass them directly in via the chart
they could be stored as a secret within
our cluster and just reference those if
we wanted to override the image that was
being used instead of using the default
image let's say we had our own version
or we're hosting it in our own uh
container registry we could do so here
and so there's all sorts of values that
you may want to override hopefully the
chart authors provided a good set of
defaults but you should always review
the available configurations and see if
any of them need to be set to meet the
needs of your deployment there's also
this values schema file this is not a
required file but it can be very useful
to help enforce a schema on the values
of the chart otherwise people can
specify uh anything they want in the
values file and let's say they had a
typo without any validation that typo
might go unnoticed and just not impact
the deployment whereas if you include a
schema Helm is able to enforce that
schema in addition to the values. emo
file in the chart itself or the value
schema file you can also issue the helm
show values command and that will also
specify the available values without
necessarily needing to pull the chart
okay that's a lot of Preamble but let's
go ahead and install this Helm chart in
this case we're going to issue the helm
install
command passing it the name of our chart
passing it a version and here I have two
versions specified in my task file I'm
starting out with version 15 15.4.1 uh
and then I'm going to upgrade in the
next step to 1542 just to show you how
that upgrade process works I'm telling
it to create the namespace if it doesn't
exist and then I'm passing it a values
file if I go to the values. yl I'm
giving it a common annotation that I
want to apply to all resources and this
is going to be substituted in Via those
templates to apply this annotation to
all the resources that the chart is
deploying it has some helpful
information here that is being printed
out after the deployment was successful
it's telling us how I can access this on
DNS within the cluster so this is the
name of the service this is the name
space and then service cluster local so
we can see it created this cluster IP
service behind the scenes we can see
that it stored our password in a secret
here and because I didn't specify a
password I believe it generates One
automatically a random one let's go
ahead and do K get
pods and as you can see we have a single
replica from that stateful set that's up
and running I'll do kg get all in my
current namespace
and you can see we've got our stateful
set we've got a single pod and we've got
a service as well as a headless service
now let's see if this common annotation
got subbed in and applied to my
resources so if I do K get St set- o
yaml pipe that to yq and here is my
annotation that I provided via that
values. yaml file that was injected into
the stateful set itself as you can see
it was also injected into my service so
I just wanted to Showcase how setting a
value and passing it via that values.
AML file gets applied into the various
templates otherwise this was a
completely default installation it's
using my Cube config credentials and
using the Nam space that I configured as
default which in this case was my 05--
poster SQL namespace so what if I want
to upgrade this I can issue a Helm
upgrade command whenever I do a Helm
upgrade in in command I generally also
include this D- install and that's
because this allows you to use the same
command whether it's the first time
you're installing it or if you're
upgrading uh if you didn't include
this-- install flag and the helm release
did not exist yet it would fail and so I
just use this one command to always
install or upgrade here everything is
the same as before my only difference is
that I'm passing in a new version so
before we had 15.4.1 now I'm passing in
15.42%
to have been successful it's also useful
to know that Helm stores its history of
the releases within secrets in the
cluster so if I do K Secrets now in
this in this namespace I can see I have
two releases I have this initial install
and then I have this uh upgrade and so
this is how as a client side only tool
it's able to store some history such
that we can do things like roll back so
let's say the new version we upgraded to
didn't perform as expected we needed to
roll back to the previous version we
could do Helm roll back postgres and
this is the name of the release so if I
do Helm list we can see this is my
release that I have in the cluster and
so I'm doing Helm rollback release it's
going to take my current version and go
back to the previous one and you can see
it's now referencing the original
version 15.4.1 that I had deployed into
the cluster now I use this command
already but if you do Helm list and
specified namespace this is going to
show all the releases
within that namespace I can also ask
Helm to provide me with this specific
set of values that were provided for
that deployment it's going to provide me
with the specific set of user supplied
values the rest are going to use the
defaults but these are the ones that I
provided via my values. file at runtime
so this is very useful command if you
need to figure out the configuration
that was deployed hopefully those are
all stored within your git repository
and are up toate but this can be a way
to validate that the deployed version
matches your expect
and then you also can run the helm get
manifest command and this is going to
look at the deployed release and give
you the set of rendered out manifests so
taking all the templated values and
rendering out the actual deployed
versions that you want to have in the
cluster and this is a great way to see
all of the Manifest that that Helm chart
is deploying in their rendered form now
finally let's say you are no longer
using whatever tool you had installed
with Helm there is an uninstall
command that's just Helm uninstall and
then you pass it the name of the release
Here the release is uninstalled and if I
do K get all in my current namespace
those two Services the stateful set and
the corresponding pod were all cleaned
up awesome so that covers kind of the
types of interactions that you'll have
with a third party Helm chart how to
access the repo how to install the repo
how to look at the different
configuration values that are available
and then how to interact with the
releases on the cluster side once you've
deployed things let's take a brief look
at how we might author some charts of
our own so I'll navigate to the Chart
subdirectory I'll create a namespace now
I've included a couple of things here um
the first one is this what I'm naming
Helm create unmodified there is a Helm
create command so I can do Helm create
Fu and it will create a new chart with a
bunch of default
values and all of the necessary boiler
plate for using Helm uh I'll go ahead
and delete this Helm create unmodified
is exactly that I ran Helm create Helm
create unmodified and It produced this
chart so if you wanted to explore the uh
set of default configurations that it
provides it showcases a bunch of the
different features of Helm how you would
use them uh Etc you would then go in and
take these templates and customize them
to meet your needs I've also included a
super minimal Helm chart that doesn't
include all of the boiler plate but it's
just enough to get started and showcase
some of the different uh templating
options that we have I'm calling this
Helm chart chart minimal you can see
here in the metadata chart. yaml we've
got the name a description um there are
two Helm chart types there's application
type and so if your Helm chart is
deploying an application that is
generally the one that you're going to
want to use the other one is a library
type and so that is if your chart is
defining resource Primitives that are
then going to be consumed by other
charts so you can have a dependency
hierarchy where one chart depends on
another and so there are Library charts
that are not meant to be installed in
and of themselves but are used by other
charts to provide kind of foundational
resource types let's look at the default
values yl file here here I'm specifying
a an environment as well as an array of
config data and then in my templates
directory I have two things I have a
helpers file this is the same variable
definition I showed on the slide based
on the environment in my values file
Define an N short variable so it's
either going to be prod or nonpr and
then within my actual templates that are
going to get rendered I just have have a
config map and this config map is going
to be named based on my release name
it's going to include an app version
it's going to include the environment
and put quotation marks on it it's going
to include that end short variable and
then it's going to Loop over the set of
values in my config data and decide
based on those values whether or not
they should be included in this config
map or not also in the notes.txt file
that you include in your templates this
is going to get rendered out after you
install or upgrade the chart and so this
is where you can provide that helpful
information like the postgress chart
gave us information about the service or
the or this the password Etc kind of
getting started information is what you
would put here now I want to install it
with the default values so to do that
I'm going to do Helm upgrade install
like I said I use this even when it's
the first time I'm installing something
because it's valid in either case I'm
passing it the name of the release that
I want to use and then here I'm passing
it a relative path to where the chart
lives in the file system so I haven't
this chart to any repo so instead of
pulling from a repo I'm also able to
reference a local chart within my file
system you can see that the release was
installed in my 05 chart namespace and
we got that note from my notes.txt
telling me which environment I deployed
you see it rendered out that M short
because my default values file was
production we deployed prod let's look
at the config maps in my namespace to
see what was actually deployed okay
we've got our config map data here we
can see that included the app version
the environment and the M short in this
case it was PR and then also based on
this Loop here so this enabled key was
true we got a conditional key with this
string as the value conditional key this
will be included let's go ahead and
deploy our chart again using our
alternative values file here now because
it's the staging environment we'll
expect the M short to be nonpr we'll
expect this conditional key not to show
up because I have this enabled false
meaning that this conditional is going
to skip over it the way that you pass a
specific set of values again it's the
same command here except now I'm passing
a values file as well you can see our
notes was templated out properly and we
can get our config map and look at the
values so now we no longer have any
conditional key from our config data and
we only have these three keys because
this enabled field was false awesome
I'll go ahead and clean up that
namespace and so that is a speedrun of
Helm and using Helm one thing we didn't
cover are Helm hooks Helm hooks allow
you to specify resources that should be
deployed either before you install
something or before you upgrade
something or afterwards often times
there's some sequencing that is required
when you're rolling out applications
let's say you need to do a database
migration that you might put as a Helm
hook that is deployed before install or
before upgrades or there could be some
cleanup actions that need to be deployed
after those could also be a different
hook and so just wanted to call out that
hooks exist even though we didn't cover
them here but hopefully that gives you
an idea of how you'll use Helm which
will be a very common occurrence as you
install third party tools into your
clusters at this point we've built out
our understanding of the fundamentals
and the Baseline knowledge necessary to
start using kubernetes effectively now
we need an example application that
aligns with what you would see in the
real world and so in this module I'm
going to Showcase a bare bones but
representative application that we can
use to apply all of the knowledge we've
learned thus far into deploying it onto
our kubernetes clusters if you took my
Docker course this demo application is
going to look very familiar I've made a
few small tweaks uh but it is mostly the
same base application and that is a
three- tier web application we're using
react on the front end we'll have two
separate API implementations one in
node.js and one in go and then that will
talk to a postgress database on the back
end the two new elements here are that
I've added one additional service and
that is a python load generator that
just spins up and calls the apis
repeatedly and then additionally I'm
storing each request to these apis as a
row in a database table such that we can
keep track of the number of requests
that have been made to each of them on
the right hand side you can see what the
UI for this application looks like it
takes the responses from those two apis
and displays them on the page we get a
timestamp from the database as well as
the number of requests that have been
made to each of those apis because this
course is not focused on application
development I'm not going to go too deep
into all these configurations but I am
going to quickly walk through the
applications and show you how to run
them so that you're familiar with the
underlying implementation the first
thing that I'll do is navigate to our
module 6 directory and we're actually
going to start at the bottom and work
our way up so the first thing that we're
going to need to do is deploy our
database I've got a number of tasks here
in my T task file to do so first thing
that I'm going to do here is execute
this
postgres run postgres
command and you can see it's issuing a
docker run command and passing the
environment variable of postgress
password we're setting that to Fubar baz
we're creating a volume to store the
underlying data and we're mapping
that to this path within the container
which is where postgres expects its data
to be stored and finally we are
connecting Port
5432 on my local host on my system to
Port 5432 in that container and this is
the image that we're running postgres
version 16.3 with an Alpine base image
okay I'm going to leave that terminal up
and running and open a new one now as I
mentioned I'll be storing information
about each request in a table in the
database and so I need to create that
table and the schema for it I have this
migration file here create users table
up and create users table down so an up
migration is going to create it and if
something went wrong I would run that
down migration in here you can see I'm
going to create a table named request in
the public schema that has two different
columns the First Column is the created
at column which is going to be of type
timestamp and it's going to use the
timestamp when any given row is created
and the second column is API name and
that is going to be either node or go
depending which API is calling now to
run this I can issue this I can run this
particular
task which as you can see first I'm
getting the container ID by doing a
Docker PS command and filtering down to
the particular image that I'm running
I'm then copying this migrations file
from my Local Host system into that
container and finally issuing a Docker
exec command using that container ID I
grabbed in the first step using the psql
command line with the user postgres and
executing this SQL script based on the
logs it successfully issued this create
table command and now that should exist
in my postr database now with my
database running and with the schema
created I can spin up my two backend
applications so we'll move one layer up
the stack to our backend apis the go API
lives in this API goang subdirectory the
dependencies are defined within this
go.mod file I'm using two top level
dependencies the Gin API framework and
the PGX postgres client in order to
install these dependencies locally I can
run the install command which under the
hood runs go mod tidy in this case I
already had all these dependencies
installed so nothing happened if you ran
this for the first time it would install
the dependencies onto your system now I
can run it with I can then run the
application with the Run task which
behind the scenes passes in a database
URL containing the credentials for my
database as well as where on the network
you can find it because I'm running
postgres in a Docker container map to a
port on my Local Host I can connect to
it at this address and then finally
calls go run main go which is going to
compile and run the application it's now
listening on Port 8000 so let me go
ahead and access
that you can
see it g gives me the current time from
the database and the number of requests
I've made so each time I refresh this we
get an updated time as well as an
incremented request count great in the
console we can see it logging out these
200 responses are successful API
responses and because I don't have a
favicon defined it's giving me a 404
when the browser tries to request the
favicon looking at the source code
briefly my main function is very simple
we load in that database
URL either from an environment variable
or from a file we then initialize a
client to connect to the database and
finally set up two API endpoints the
first one is just the root endpoint so
when
I when I request that API with no
additional
path we do two things one we insert a
row into the table saying hey a request
was made and then two we load the
current time and select the EST count
from the database if I jump into these
two functions the first one we're
inserting into the request table the API
name here is going to be go and the time
stamp is going to be picked up
automatically we then issue this
function where we select the current
time and then we count the number of
rows where the API name matches my
current API name so that's all there is
to it with this API we also have a
health check endpoint that checks if it
can make a database connection and if so
it returns a 200 we can now jump to the
nodejs application I'll leave this
running and create a new
terminal navigate into the API node
subdirectory start my devbox shell and
then we're going to install our
dependencies this calls npm
install okay our dependencies should be
installed now and then we'll call npm
runev passing in again our database URL
containing the connectivity information
this is now listening on Port 3000 let's
just validate that it's
working okay we get back the current
time and the number of requests as we
request more and more the request count
climbs and as you can see request count
is independent between the two apis it's
what we want we're seeing the responses
as before like with the go Application
200s on the API requests and 404s on the
favicon because there is no fabicon 44
meaning not found looking in my
package.json you can see that I'm using
Express as my API server Morgan is a
logging utility and PG is a postgres
client so we now have our postres
instance and our two backend apis
running let's set up the react client
that lives in the client react
subdirectory start my Dev boox shell
we're going to install our
dependencies runs an npm install and
then an npm run here we don't have any c
credentials required it's calling our
backend apis which don't have any
Authentication we can navigate to our
browser and see here's the application
it's making a request to both of these
apis and returning the results to the
front end as I refresh the page each one
is going to increment a single time
because they're both making a single
call looking at the source for this it
is a very simple react app we have our
top level
app.jsx it has a function current time
which is going to be used for both of
those components we have two instances
of that current time
component with two separate apis the
first one is calling our go based API
the second one is calling our node API
the data from those get returned and
populated into this react component
there we go now the final service here
is written in Python and it is just
going to make repeated requests to one
of our backend apis let me create one
more terminal I'll start my devbox shell
we're going to install our
dependencies now I'm using a package
manager called poetry to help manage my
python environment here I'm calling
poetry install no root in this case all
of my dependencies have already been
installed so that works fine and then
finally I'll issue my poetry run
command and in this case that behind the
scenes calls poetry run python on my
main.py and specifically is calling
Local Host 8000 so if you remember 8000
was the port that my goang application
was serving on and we can see in this
terminal over here the goang application
now is getting hit repeatedly by that
load generator if I load my page in the
front end you can see the goang API
request count is climbing rapidly
whereas the node API is stable until I
make another request we've made 300
requests to the goang API it's now up to
340 if we take a look at the source code
of the load generator it's very simple
within our main.py we're importing some
dependencies we have two things we have
our load generator function so this is
just going to Loop forever until this
terminate value is false for each of
those Loops we're going to try to make a
response to the API that's provided
we're going to log some info to console
and if for some reason it fails we will
we will catch that exception and keep
trying then we sleep for in this case a
configurable number of milliseconds and
then the only other piece of this is
handling termination signals meaning if
we want to kill this application with a
control
C it will catch that signal it will
catch that signal log the fact that it
has done so toggle the terminate value
to True which will end this Loop and the
process will terminate here at the
bottom I'm just setting up some basic
logging loading which API I want to call
as well as how long it should sleep
between iterations setting up my signal
handling and then calling my run load
generator function at the
bottom and that's really all there is to
it while each of these Individual
Services is quite minimal they cover a
variety of different languages
and many of the different types of
configuration that you might want to
handle within a microservice based
application that you're deploying onto
kubernetes before we can go about
deploying our application onto
kubernetes we need to build our
container images that kubernetes is
going to use while I'm not going to do a
deep dive on building container images
like I did in the docker course I'm
going to go over them briefly and
showcase how we can build and push them
to container Registries here as a quick
reminder the general way that we Define
a container image is via a do file this
is a text file containing essentially
the steps of instructions required to
build out the application you're usually
going to start with some base operating
system install maybe your language
runtime if you're running in python or
node.js you'll install your application
dependencies copy in your source code
and then set up the necessary commands
to run the application once we've built
an
image we then need to store it somewhere
that our cluster can use the place that
we do this is called a container
registry Docker Hub is a great example
of on but there's many others including
GitHub container registry many of the
major clouds have their own container
Registries Etc so you'll build these
images either on your laptop or maybe
within a continuous integration server
you'll push those to a registry and then
our cluster as a production environment
is going to pull an image from the
registry with a given configuration I'll
call out here that it is important to
think about the Build architecture of
the images your development system may
or may not match the architecture of
your staging or production servers for
example if you're building on a Apple
silicon laptop but you're deploying to
an x86 server by default those two would
be incompatible however there is a way
to build multi-architecture
images where you're going to emulate
these other architectures during the
build such that the container image can
be run across multiple different
architectures for each of our
applications I've set up one version
that's using Docker build that's going
to be a single architecture that matches
the architecture of your development
system I've also set up a build X
command which is going to allow us to
build multiplatform images across a
variety of architectures in order to run
on kubernetes we do need to build all of
these into container images let me stop
all of these processes and we'll take a
look at how we can build the container
images that we're going to use in our
kubernetes cluster if you want a deep
dive on how we wrote the docker files
and optimize the build process you
should go check out the docker course
but in this case I'm just going to
quickly run through them and showcase
how we can build them and push them to a
registry in the case of postgres the
database that we're going to run in
kubernetes is going to use that Public
postr Image however we do need to be
able to execute our migrations against
that database to do that I'm starting
from this base image which is using the
goang migrate package it's a CLI and
goang Library used for running database
migrations and from that base image I'm
just copying in all of the migrations in
my migrations file so very simple Docker
file in order to build that I can run T
build container image which is going to
issue a Docker build- T here I'm tagging
it with a dockerhub container image name
if you wanted to build and push this to
your own container image registry you
would need to replace this and then I'm
passing it the context for the build
which is my current directory looks like
that built successfully in today's world
where many people are developing on Arm
based architectures because of the Apple
because of Apple silicon or potentially
deploy to Arm based servers it can be
useful to build multi-architecture
container images that can be used
against either amd64 or arm
architectures in order to do this we can
use Docker build X the first thing that
we're going to want to do is bootstrap a
build X Builder to do this we're going
to issue the docker build X create
command we're going to give it a name
we're going to tell it to use the docker
container driver we're going to allow it
to connect to our host Network and then
we're going to specify it as the default
Builder looks like that successfully and
now we're configured to use that when we
issue Docker build X commands now if I
go back into my postgress directory I
also have this build container image
multiart task and we can see it's
issuing a
Docker Docker build X build command
passing two platforms both the Linux
amd64 as well as the Linux arm 64
passing in the image tag and then
automatically pushing it to that
registry if we go to that registry on
dockerhub you can see it pushed the foo
bar as tag just a few seconds ago great
and it has both of the architectures
that we specified available so you could
pull this image and run it on either
type of system if we go to the go API I
do have a Docker file here specified
this is the one that I used in the
docker course however there's a really
cool tool called Co KO that allows you
to build goang applications without
needing to build or optimize your own
Docker file so in this case when I issue
the build container image task it calls
co- build with a couple of options
enabled in this case platform all is
going to do both arm and
amd64 and I'm passing it the name of the
docker repo that I want to use and then
without it even needing a Docker
file it will go off and build my
application we can go to dockerhub and
look at that
repo and see in this case not only did
it build the amd64 and arm 64 it also
built an arm V7
a ppc64le and an s390x architecture so
with that one simple Co command and no
Docker file at all I was able to build
for all these different architectures
and and you can see it's just an 8
megabyte image so it's it's fairly
optimized for nodejs this is going to be
the same Docker file that we used in the
docker course uh we've got our base
image which is pulling from an official
Upstream node image we're setting some
environment variables installing our
dependencies copying in our source code
and then issuing the command to start
the application we have the two tasks
again the first one builds a single
architecture image using the docker
build
command and the second one uses our
build X Builder to build the
multi-architecture
version now it is important to note that
you can't use build X to build the
multi-architecture version without this
push command and so if you didn't have a
remote registry on dockerhub or
elsewhere set up you could a local
registry using the docker run command on
the registry image listening on Port
5000 and running in the background you
could then use this registry and tell
Docker X to push your multi-architecture
images to this local registry so that
can be a good way to validate your
process without having to have a remote
registry authenticated okay that was the
API node one within client react we've
got the same deal our Docker file looks
quite similar to our nodejs application
we're starting from an official Upstream
image we're installing dependencies
we're copying our source the one
difference is that instead of serving
this as a nodejs application we run the
npm build command which outputs our
static HTML JavaScript in CSS and then
we're going to serve those from an
engine X container you could serve them
from a container like this or you could
distribute them via CDN finally for our
python application this one did not
exist in the docker course so I wrote
this Docker file just for this purpose
you can see we have a multi-stage Docker
file we're starting from this first
stage where we're going to generate the
requirements needed in our application
to do that we install poetry we then use
our P project toml and our poetry. loock
file to generate a requirements.txt file
then within our second stage we copy
that requirements.txt file in install
via pip copy our source code in and then
specify the command that's going to be
run we do it this way so that we don't
need to include poetry and all of that
development Machinery in our final image
the build command and the
multi-architecture build commands are
going to be the same a Docker build and
a Docker build X command so as you can
see by defining things in a similar way
across all these different Services the
actual build commands end up being
identical whereas we can use Docker
build for a single architecture or we
can use build X to build a
multi-architecture image the go API was
the one slightly different one because
we're leveraging that third party tool
Co to handle all of that for us and so
while I went quickly there hopefully
that gives you an idea of the
configuration surface area of the
various Serv
and how they all fit together in this
puzzle so that you have the context
required as we now take all of these
services and figure out how we're going
to deploy them into kubernetes once we
have our container images built and
pushed we need to translate the
different components of our architecture
into a set of kubernetes resources that
we can deploy onto the cluster for the
various stateless components those would
include our two backend apis as well as
the server for our react client files
and the load generator none of those
have any state that we need to store in
the cluster so those we can use
deployments for our database represent a
stateful application and therefore
should be deployed as a stateful set in
this case we're going to use a Helm
chart to do so we'll deploy services in
front of each of our deployments and
stateful set to provide stable Network
endpoints and then we'll deploy an
Ingress controller and Ingress routes to
Route traffic from outside the cluster
to the appropriate Services inside the
cluster finally We'll add config maps
and secrets for any configuration that
we want to decouple from our application
deployment let's jump in Define these
resources and apply them to our cluster
all right let's navigate to our 07
deploying demo application directory as
you can see I've got a number of tasks
defined for each service I have an apply
command that's going to run a cube C
apply on all the underlying resources I
also have a common subdirectory which is
going to deploy my Ingress controller in
this case I'm going to deploy an Ingress
controller called traffic just to show
another example of a different Ingress
controller and then for postgres I'm
going to install it via Helm chart as
well as apply my initial database
migration let's start at the bottom of
that architecture diagram and work our
way up so we'll start with postgres in
this case we'll run the postgresql
install postgres
command it's going to add the helm repo
and then call a Helm upgrade install on
version
15.3.2 using the set command to pass in
off. postr password to the value that I
want it to this-- set command is another
option instead of passing in a values
file you can set specific values via the
command line in this way for a
credential like this where you don't
necessarily want to store it in a file
passing it at deploy time can be a good
option you can see that was deployed
into the postgres
namespace and the helm chart deployed a
relatively small but it'll work for our
purposes persistent volume claim
associated with that stateful set now in
order to run the database migration the
type of kubernetes resource that makes
the most sense is a job it is a task
which we want to run one time to
completion and so what I did here is I
defined a kubernetes job I'm calling it
The DB migrator I'm putting it in the
demo app namespace and so before I can
deploy this I'll need to create the demo
app namespace I have this common apply
namespace which is going to apply the
namespace
yl and that namespace yo contains demo
app all the services are going to go
into the demo app namespace except for
postgres which is going into its own
names great now that namespace exists
let's take a look at the template here
for the job it's going to have one
container which I'm naming migrate it's
using that container that I built and
pushed which has all of my migration
scripts in this case it's just that one
in this case it's just this one create
users table script and then the args for
that migrator command line tool I'm
giving it a path in my container this is
where the migrations live slapp
migrations and then I'm passing in a
datab datase URL as an environment
variable containing the credentials and
host name for my database I'm also
turning off SSL mode because I'm not
running SSL on the database I also want
to run the up migrations rather than the
down migrations in order to get this
database URL into the Container I'm
passing it a reference to a secret named
DB password which I've defined in this
file here I have a secret named DB
password in the namespace demo app and
I'm using string data to Define my
database URL this is the password that I
created if I look at the services in the
postes namespace I've got a cluster IP
service and a headless cluster IP
service in this case I want to address
the normal cluster IP service so this is
the name of the service the name space
service cluster local on part 5432 in
the postgis database awesome so let me
apply both of those files it's starting
with the secret and then it's creating
the job let's look at the pods it's
already
completed we've got one of one
completions great and let's look at the
log from that
pod it created our user table in 14
milliseconds awesome so now we've got
our database running and the initial
migration has run now this migration job
we would want to run every time we have
a new migration uh before we make the
corresponding application deployments
now I'm going to move on and deploy the
things in my common subdirectory so we
already deployed the name space however
I want to also deploy the traffic
Ingress controller so I can do that with
t common deploy traffic
I'm adding my Helm repository and then
I'm running my hel upgrade install
command naming my release traffic from
this Helm chart using version
2880 I'll look at everything in the
traffic Nam
space we can see it created a deployment
which in turn created a replix cassette
which in turn created a pod we also have
a load balancer typee service which will
deploy in this case I'm running in my
gke cluster so that will deploy a Google
Cloud load balancer calling that command
again the external IP has been set up
there's one additional common element
that is shared between my two apis and
that is a middleware um the middleware
is a is a custom resource that is
defined by traffic which enables us to
do things like strip a path prefix from
the incoming requests uh so for example
if I navigate to my whatever my domain
name is and go to/ API node I'm going to
Define an Ingress to route that traffic
to my node.js application however my
nodejs application is not expecting to
have that prefix in the request so this
middleware allows me to strip that out
so that by the time it hits my node API
it'll look as though it's coming from
the root path so I've created that
middleware let's now take a look at the
Go API resources we've got a deployment
this will look very familiar to the
deployments that we learned in module 4
I'm calling it API goang it's in my demo
app Nam space I'm including this app
label just to say that this resource is
associated with my goang API it's going
to have a single replica and then I'm
specifying my selector which this label
needs to match the label on my container
as specified here the container image is
the one from dockerhub that I built and
pushed I'm specifying to listen on Port
8000 I'm pulling in my database secret
from a secret named API goang database
URL which is defined alongside it here
I'm specifying a container port
listening on Port 8000 and a Readiness
probe for the cuet to Ping to check if
my application is healthy I'm specifying
the resources that this application is
requesting in this case 100 megabytes of
memory and 50 millor of CPU I'm limiting
the Privileges of the Pod just from a
which is good from a security
perspective and that should be about it
I also have a service defined so this is
just a standard cluster IP service
listening on Port 8000 and passing the
requests to Port 8,000 in my pod using
that same selector that the deployment
is using in order to connect it to those
underlying pods so if I run T API goang
apply it's going to call cctl apply DF
on that directory if you do a cube CTL
apply on a directory it's going to try
to apply every yaml file within that
directory so I've created my deployment
my Ingress route my secret and my
service if we look at the pods in the
demo app the DB migrator is the one we
created a a few minutes ago and then my
goang API is up and running if we look
at my Ingress route you'll notice this
is a little different than the Ingress
that we deployed in module 4 in this
case traffic has defined their own
custom resource to avoid having to use
those annotations for all the custom
behaviors and instead you can Define
this Ingress route and traffic will
interpret it to determine where Network
request should be routed this is the
domain that it's listening for and this
is the path prefix that it's using to
send to decide if a request should go to
my go AP I I'm using that common
middleware that I deployed to strip out
those prefixes and then it's routing it
to the service that I've defined
alongside this and one thing I just
noticed here is that this port should
actually be 8,000 um I had it going to
8080 but I've updated my application to
be listening on Port 8,000 so I'll save
that and then apply just to validate
that things are working I'm going to
port forward to the service then we can
access it on Local Host 8,000 there we
go we've got our API responding I can
then take this external IP address go
over to my DNS provider of cloudflare
update my a record to point to that IP
address and then if we navigate to
kubernetes course. devop direct.com
aigang we can see the traffic is getting
routed to our API okay let's move on to
our node.js application the resources
are going to look pretty much identical
to the goang one the main difference
being that we're running our API node
container
image and and we're listening on a
different port that's Port
3000 we have a secret which has the same
contents it's just pointing us with the
credentials to the proper service inside
the cluster and our Ingress route
instead of using the path prefix API
goang it's using the path prefix API
node let we go ahead and apply
this we can see our pod being
created it's now
running let's try and access it
okay we see the node API giving us a
response now for our client react app
it's going to use that engine X
container that we built which contains
the output of our npm build process
again it should all look very familiar
the main difference here being we're
using the specific container image
associated with this application I'm
listening on Port 880 I've got my
Readiness probe set up I've got my
resource requests and my security
context set up I'm also mounting in this
config map as a volume so this config
map is mounted in as a volume and then
is located at Etsy engine X compd which
is the default location that engine X is
going to look for a configuration file
and then within that config map I'm
defining that it should listen on Port
880 I have my health check route here
these two locations are not actually
necessary here because the routing to my
backend apis is happening at the Ingress
layer and then this tells us where the
files in the container for my react
client live and that should be
sufficient so we've created our config
map we've created a deployment an
Ingress route so this Ingress route is
essentially saying match all traffic to
this domain and is not specifying any
sort of path prefix so any request to
the root path is going to get routed
here I'm pointing it to my service
that's defined right here that's in
front of my deployment and that should
be sufficient to get traffic into my
application so if I remove this prefix
now you can see there's my
application the final service that I
haven't deployed yet is the load
generator for this I have a deployment
I'm specifying the labels accordingly to
indicate that it is its own application
I'm using the container image here
specifically the version that I built
and pushed pointing it to the cluster IP
service for my node API and specifying a
half-second delay between each call if
we wanted to we could move these types
of configurations into a config map in a
simple case like this it's okay to
Define them directly here in the
deployment if there were many different
environment variables it might make
sense to extract them out and put them
into a config map I've got my resources
defined as well as my security context
now this is an important one on
dockerhub I have the registry containing
this container image specified as
private now I did that so that I could
demonstrate how image pull Secrets work
and show you first it's going to fail to
pull then we'll create an image pull
secret and then it will succeed so let's
start by commenting out this image pull
secrets and we'll deploy those resources
now I've got this warning here warning
you about the fact that this is a
private container image repository if I
now look at my pods this pod is now in
an image pull backoff State meaning it
tried to pull the image and it failed if
we describe
it you can see failed to pull that's
because it's a private container image
registry so in order to solve that we
need to do two things we need to
uncomment this we need to create a
secret containing the proper credentials
that this can use in order to do that I
can use this task load generator python
create image pull secret but it's
expecting me to specify the following
three environment variables Docker
username Docker email and Docker
password so I'm going to specify those
and cut that out I'll rerun this command
now that I've exported those environment
variables this command can
succeed it's calling QBE Cube CTL create
Secret in my demo app
namespace it is of type Docker registry
I'm naming it Docker config Json and
then passing in all of the values that
it needs and with our Docker config Json
secret created we can now reapply our
load generator configuration you can do
kg pods and we can see it was able to
successfully pull and run our container
image and now we have our load generator
pod let's check the logs of it as you
can see it's just requesting over and
over on that internal cluster IP and so
if we go back to our website here we'll
expect the request request count for the
node API to grow much faster than that
of the go API it's set to delay a half a
second between each one so it's not
going to climb super rapidly but you can
see those requests are happening in the
background it's at 182 and now it jumps
up to 200 to recap we created our four
stateless applications using deployments
three of them have cluster IP services
in front of them we've got our traffic
Ingress controller installed routing
traffic via those Ingress routes we've
got our postgres database that we
installed via the helm chart and then we
did our We performed our database
migrations via a job and those
credentials for the database are stored
within Secrets one for each service the
Ingress controller provisioned an
external load balancer for which we were
able to create a public DNS record and
now access the application because the
load generator python container image
registry was Private we had to create
that image pull Secret in order to pull
it successfully and now everything is
running within the cluster one nice
thing about gke
is that out of the box you get log
aggregation I can go here to my cluster
and get logs from the control
plane
or I can go to the logging
page and get logs from all my different
Services I could filter down to specific
ones and so this is important previously
we've been only looking at logs by
issuing a cube TL log command those logs
would only persist through the life
cycle of the Pod and so you want to ship
your logs to some log log aggregation
system here Google is handling that for
us and pulling those logs off of our
containers into its loging platform
where we can then observe and search
over time as well as see them all in one
aggregated place if we click into the
workloads tab here in the overview it
shows all the different services that
we've deployed as well as their status
we can then click into the observability
tab and see the usage of various
services in this case let's narrow down
to our demo app namespace and now you
can see the various apps that we've
deployed it also gives us different
events that we've created so here I've
this is showing me when I've modified a
deployment or when I've deleted a
deployment and so if you're if you're
looking at this and you see a spike you
can you can very easily dive in and see
whether it corresponded to some action
that you took maybe you upgraded a
deployment and and that caused your
memory usage to spike you could then go
back and look at what changed in that
version of your application and figure
out why that had happened of the manage
cluster offerings I would say Google's
observability tooling is the most mature
that I've seen uh on coo there is some
log aggregation that's still in kind of
a beta state but I don't think they have
anything quite like this in terms of
being able to see your metrics and
correlate those to events in the cluster
you could deploy your own observability
stack you can deploy something like
Prometheus to collect the metrics and
grafana which is a a tool for building
dashboards and you can query Prometheus
and build dashboards like this but
having it work with no additional
configuration on our end is pretty nice
here within
gke so far we've mostly been using
capabilities that are built into
kubernetes itself with some additional
functionality provided by drivers for
those common container interfaces now
let's take a look at the ways in which
you can extend the kubernetes API to
adapt the system to fit the needs of
your particular application when people
talk about kubernetes the first thing
that comes to mind is that it is a
container orchestrator it allows you to
take containerized workloads and deploy
and schedule them across a number of
different compute resources however it's
not just a container orchestrator
kubernetes effectively provides an API
for declaring a set of resources you
send those resources to the kubernetes
API server it stores them in NCD and
makes sure that the state of those
resources is shared across all the
control plane nodes and accessible via
the API the second piece that kubernetes
provides is this concept of a control
Loop that is continuously observing and
acting upon those resources let's take
some of the built-in resources that we
learned in module 4 and think about how
this plays out in those cases if I
create a deployment I have my
deployment. file it defines a whole
bunch of configuration for that
deployment I send that to the kubernetes
API with the cube CTL apply command it
gets stored in ETD and then that second
part kicks in we have the kubernetes
controllers that look at that deployment
M say oh this is a deployment I need to
create a corresponding replica set and
it will do so then there's another
controller that looks at that replica
set and says oh this is a replica set I
know what I need to do I need to create
a number of PODS to go along with this
replica set the behaviors that the
system should take for those built-in
resources are all provided by these
controllers that come with kubernetes
out of the box however you can Define
your own custom Resources with whatever
schema you want tell kubernetes how to
interpret that schema and it will
happily accept those custom resources
store them within ND and maintain their
state you can then write your own
applications in this case we call them
controllers which will query the
kubernetes API to find out which of
those custom resources you have deployed
into your cluster and take whatever
action you want this may sound a little
bit abstract but let's break it down
like we did for the built-in Resources
with a couple of use cases one example
is a project called Cloud native PG
which is designing a system for
deploying postgressql databases onto
kubernetes that we're going to take a
look at in the following section and
actually deploy it into our cluster what
they've done is created a set of custom
resources associated with postgres
clusters backups of postgres Etc and
then the logic of what maybe a human
database admin would perform is encoded
into a custom controller such that you
can execute many common workflows in a
declarative fashion by deploying these
custom resources another great example
is management of TLS certificate there's
a project called CT manager which I'm
not covering in this course but I would
certainly suggest you often take a look
at it and they use custom resources for
managing certificates so they have one
for certificates one for let's say an
HTTP challenge one for a certificate
provisioner that is pointed at let's
encrypt for example and so they have
those custom resources and then they
also have implemented a controller such
that when you deploy those custom
resources to your cluster that
controller is able to go off and take
action such as provision a new
certificate and store those credentials
in a kubernetes secret another great
example is a project called crossplane
it enables you to deploy infrastructure
simply by creating custom resources in
kubernetes they have what are known as
managed resources which map on toone
with let's say an infrastructure
providers if you're deploying something
on AWS maybe you have an ec2 instance
custom resource that lives in your
cluster crossplane controller sees that
is able to interface with the AWS API
and actually create the corresponding
instance with all the configuration
you've provided in your AWS account as
you can see these three use cases are
incredibly varied and hopefully that
Sparks the idea that you can take this
pattern of defining a set of resources
and then writing an application or a
controller to observe and act upon those
resources to handle all sorts of
different scenarios there are many
different projects that help with
providing the tooling required to build
these types of controllers some of the
most popular ones are Cube Builder
operator SDK meta controller or you can
use the kubernetes client code that's
provided for many popular languages to
bootstrap your own if you wanted to get
started with building out your own
kubernetes operators Cube Builder has an
excellent tutorial in which you
literally go through the process of
writing a replacement for the built-in
Cron job controller so you're
effectively solving the same types of
problems that the people building
kubernetes were and learning the
underpinnings of how this operator model
works by building out your own
implementation of Aon job on top of
kubernetes to make this a little more
concrete I wanted to just show what a
custom resource definition looks like it
is an open API schema that defines all
the fields that are allowed required and
or optional for your custom resource and
so this example here is the Ingress
route and we actually used this in the
previous module when we were deploying
our Ingress for the application we
deployed traffic and it defined these
custom resources which it then used to
define its routing configuration if we
look down here at the schema you can see
all the different properties it tells us
what the resource is it tells us that in
order to create an Ingress route object
we need to Define an API version a kind
a metadata a spec within that spec we
need to have routes we can have a TLS
configuration and so these projects or
you define a custom resource like this
and that gets stored in your cluster
just like any other
resource so if I do K get crd here are
all the custom resources that are
installed into my cluster you can see
that traffic deployed a number of custom
resources you can see that Kong reused
in the Gateway API section of the
built-in resources module deployed a
number of custom resources and then
because this is the gke cluster Google
has also deployed a number of custom
resources that it's using on the back
end hopefully this description of a
variety of different operators and how
they tie into this control Loop model
that kubernetes provides will get you
thinking about how you could apply this
pattern to your own application
scenarios building operators is a
relatively Advanced topic and Falls
outside the scope of this course but we
will be deploying and using some of
these operators in the following section
to get a feel for how they work and how
you should interact with these custom
resources now that we've learned about
the idea of extending the kubernetes API
and how to build systems on top of
kubernetes let's take a few examples of
that type of project and deploy them
into the cluster these are going to be
applications that enhance our usage of
the cluster in one way or another there
are many companies and open source
projects that are building this type of
tooling and so you'll want to take a
look across the landscape to understand
if there are tools that would make your
application platform on top of
kubernetes even better if we think about
how we would operate a database for an
application that we're running in
kubernetes there's four main options the
first of which is to keep the database
outside of the cluster entirely you
could deploy it on your own or you could
use a database as a service so if you're
operating in AWS that could be an RDS if
you're in Google Cloud that could be
Cloud SQL if your cloud provider offers
a database like this it can be a great
way to go to shift some of that
operational overhead of managing a
database and backups and ensuring
everything is working and testing those
things onto the cloud provider and so
that can be a great way to reduce the
amount of time and effort that you and
your team need to focus on the database
itself however if you do plan on hosting
it within the cluster there's three
primary options you could write your own
stateful set you could use a Helm chart
like we did previously where someone
else has written a stateful set for you
that you just configure or there's also
this project Cloud native PG that has
built an operator that you Deploy on
kubernetes and then you can
declaratively manage your postgres
clusters via kubernetes custom resources
what does this actually look like uh you
will deploy the oper into your clusters
this green box is the operator pod along
with it are a number of custom resources
for example there's a cluster resource
up here at the top that you can see you
defined how many instances you want how
much storage you want on the back end
along with a number of other
configuration options when you create
that custom cluster resource the
operator will see that and based on the
configuration provided it will create
one or more pods a primary pod that is
read and write and one or more secondary
or replica pods that will be readon
within your cluster it also has custom
resources for backups where you can
specify that you want to back your
cluster up to an object store of you're
choosing so on Google Cloud that's going
to be Google Cloud Storage COC cloud has
an object storees well Amazon has S3 and
so you can Define your backups or a
scheduled backup for your database in a
declarative fashion let's go ahead and
jump over to our code editor and deploy
Cloud native PG uh and see how we can
set up this type of thing I have a
number of tasks defined here within my
task file for the uh module 9
subdirectory the first thing that I'm
going to do is create a
namespace that is the 09-s cnpg
namespace next up I'm going to install
the operator to install the operator I'm
using a Helm chart so I use Helm repo ad
to add the repo to my Helm configuration
and then I call the helm upgrade install
command giving it a name for the release
putting it in the cloud native PG system
namespace creating that namespace and
specifying which chart to use I'm using
all the default values here if you do
need to do some customization take a
look at the helm chart values to figure
out what you might need to change it
then outputs a sample cluster that we
can use if we look at the
pods in the cloud native PG system
namespace we have one pod and it's up
and running great we can then also look
at the custom resources that this has
deployed into our Custer by doing a by
doing K API resources
and then grapping
postgres you can see we have a cluster
resource a backup resource a scheduled
backup Resource as well as image
catalogs and cluster image catalogs I
believe those are how you define the
container images you want to use for
each particular version of a cluster you
want to deploy and then this pooler's
resource which I believe uses PG bouncer
to set up connection pooling for your
cluster with that installed we can now
deploy a cluster custom resource I'm
using the absolute minimum configuration
here the goal of this section is not to
teach you how to deploy the optimal
postres database with Cloud native PG
it's to show you how you can use cloud
native PG and interact with these custom
resources so if you're using this you
should look into the options that the
cluster crd provides uh and I believe
Cloud native PG even has a Helm chart
with some of the best practices for
deploying a cluster encoded into it so
that could be a good place to start
let's go ahead and deploy this minimal
cluster into our kubernetes cluster if
we now look at the cluster we can see
that it's setting up the primary if we
get the pods in our
namespace there's this init DB job which
is executed first before it spins up our
primary replica looks like that pod
associated with the job has completed
and now here's our primary replica for
the database coming up we should see if
we do KET PVC we can see that it has
created two PVCs the first of one the
first one for our primary replica is
bound to the Pod that we just saw the
second one because that second pod
hasn't come up is still an appending
status our primary replica is now
running and we have a join job which is
going to allow that additional read
replica to join our cluster that is now
done and now our read replica is coming
up we can see the two instances but only
one of them are ready so far and now
both of those replicas are healthy and
our cluster is in a healthy State we can
also look at the services that it stood
up and see that we have a read WR end
Point that's going to Target our primary
replica and then we also have a readon
endpoint that's going to Target our read
replica interestingly if we do K
stateful
sets there are none so the cloud native
PG project has decided to skip stateful
sets entirely and manage its pods
directly presumably this was due to some
of the limitations with how stateful
sets work within kubernetes and they
found that the those limitations were
easier to overcome by directly
controlling the pods themselves
specifically most Fields within a
stateful set including things like the
size of the volumes that it's
provisioning are immutable even though
volumes can be dynamically expanded now
in kubernetes they have chosen as a
project to skip stateful sets and manage
their pods directly so just an
interesting call out there now let's
take a look at what we need to do to set
up backups for our postgres cluster here
is a configuration for a cluster that
looks quite similar to before we're
going to have two instances a very small
volume size but I've added two things
here one I've added this backup section
along with a Google Cloud Storage bucket
that I'm about to create I'm specifying
that it can use the Google credentials
that it finds from my GK environment and
telling it to retain backups for 30 days
next I'm setting up a service account
template and this is necessary to use a
feature within jke called workload
identity that will allow me to link
together a kubernetes service account
with a Google identity and access manage
service account such that my kubernetes
service account can leverage the same
permissions and roles that the IM
service account has and this will allow
me to access this bucket to store my
backups without needing to store any
sort of static credential into a secret
in the cluster the way that that works
is you put an annotation on the
kubernetes service account that looks
like this this will be my IM service
account name this is the uh gcp project
that it is associated with let's go
ahead and create those resources so
first we can create the bucket here I'm
running gcloud storage buckets creat
create and passing it that name we can
then go over to the Google Club console
click refresh and we see this bucket was
just
created with nothing in it now let's add
the necessary permissions on the Google
Cloud side to enable us to store objects
in that bucket this is going to do a few
things first we're going to create a
service account named cnpg
backups then we're going to attach two
roles to it the uh storage object admin
Ro as well as the Legacy bucket reader
Ro and those are specifically for the
bucket that I just created so I'm using
the gsutil command line tool to add
those two roles associated with the
bucket that I just created it's
important to call out here that this
bucket name needs to be globally unique
so you cannot share the same bucket name
as me if you're following along you'll
need to modify the name of this bucket
maybe add a postfix maybe put your own
name in there somewhere and that will
allow you to have your own globally
unique Google Cloud Storage bucket with
those two roles associated with the
bucket I can then add this role the
workload identity user to the IM service
account and this is what allows the
kubernetes identity to assume the IM
identity and specifically you need to
give it this member where I'm saving the
service account within this Google Cloud
project specifically in the namespace
that I'm working in and this service
account name is allowed to use that IM
service account looks like that was
successful we can see all this set up on
the Google Cloud side we click into
permissions and scroll down
here is the account here's the service
account that I created and here are the
two roles that I attached to it for this
bucket if we go over to the I am page
and click under service accounts we can
see the service account created here if
I click into it go to
permissions here is that workload
identity user which references our Nam
space and the the name of the surface
count that we're going to create in the
kubernetes cluster and then the final
piece that we needed to make this happen
that I set up quite a while ago in
module three when we created our cluster
was we we used this workload pool option
which passes our Google project ID do
service idid Google and that enables the
GK cluster to utilize identities in this
workload pool that can be seen in the
cluster configuration here where
workload identity is enabled and the
workload identity name space is the one
associated with this gcp project with
that all set up we can now apply this
cluster config with the backup and this
did did three things one it applied this
file and earlier I didn't call out what
this stood for Barman is the backup and
recovery manager you'll see Barm man a
few times here in the backup
configurations that's what Barman stands
for so I applied this cluster with
backup configuration I then applied a
scheduled backup file so this is
essentially a Cron job that's going to
use the backup configuration in my
cluster on this schedule so it would run
at midnight UTC daily and then just so
we'd have something to look at and have
to wait until midnight I also added a
backup resource which will run right now
in this Nam space pointing it at my
cluster so first let's do K get clusters
looks like this cluster is still coming
up let's do K get backups it's in a
running phase our cluster is now
healthy and our backup is completed
let's go look in the bucket and see what
it has created so we click into our
bucket this is the name of our postgres
cluster we've got both our base data
backup with a timestamp and then any
information that was still in the right
ahead log that hadn't been fully synced
into the primary database storage would
be here in the walls subdirectory great
so just like that we were able to deploy
Cloud native PG operator into our
cluster deploy a couple of postgres
clusters set up backups using workload
identity to store those data into a
Google Cloud Storage bucket and utilize
the effort and the testing that has gone
into that Cloud native PG Project
without needing to Define our own
stateful set or rely on that Helm chart
for this logic it's also possible to set
up backups in a cloud like sio store you
can use any S3 compatible Object Store
as the destination for these backups uh
in this case you do need to give it this
endpoint URL because it is not using the
default AWS S3 endpoints and there's no
workload identity feature on civo so you
would as you create your bucket you
would create a set of credentials with
an access key and a secret access key
and store those within a kubernetes
secret but other than that it would work
in the same way next tool that I want to
add to my kubernetes cluster is a tool
called trivy operator uh trivy is a open
source project from a company called
aqua security and it is used for
scanning container images and cluster
configurations and so by deploying this
into our cluster it's going to
automatically detect every container
image that is running in the cluster and
scan it when it is detected but then
also it's going to rescan every 24 hours
or whatever time period you specify and
so this is really awesome one because
you're going to get automatic visibility
into all of the container image whether
they're your first party container
images or third party container images
and also if you were to scan images
within a CI pipeline for example often
times vulnerabilities are discovered
after you have deployed an image and so
that initial scan result may become
outdated and need to be superseded by
one that includes the latest
vulnerability database it also exposes
metrics that you can for example send to
Prometheus or data dog
and use those to alert your security
team based on certain criteria we're
going to deploy the trivia operator into
our cluster it's then going to watch for
any job replica set demon set or
stateful set extract the image and tag
from that and that will trigger
kubernetes jobs that are going to both
do a vulnerability scan as well as a
configuration audit which then produces
additional custom resources that'll be
stored in the cluster and we can view a
vulnerability report as well as a
configuration audit report so let's go
ahead and install trivy and then view
what these look like we're going to
install the trivia operator with Helm so
we're doing a Helm repo ad for the aqua
repo and then a Helm upgrade install for
the trivia operator we're using the
default values again there's a number of
configuration options but for this use
case the defaults work just fine and
we're specifying a version if we do K
get pods in the trivia system Nam
space you can see first here's the
operator pod which came up 26 seconds
ago but already in this first 30 seconds
of its life it has spun up a number of
vulnerability report scan jobs one for
each image that it's detecting in the
cluster we can then do K get
vulnerability reports none of those scan
jobs have completed yet but as they
complete trivia is going to write to
these custom resources we be where we
will be able to then take a look at the
specific vulnerabilities that our images
have we can see that as those
vulnerability scan jobs complete more
and more of these vulnerability reports
are added it started with the cube
system namespace and now we can see some
of the images that we built are now
included you can also use the- o wide
flag we now in the output get a summary
of how many vulnerabilities at each
severity level trivia has found so for
example in our migrator job we see that
there is one critical vulnerability what
if we wanted to dive in and look at
specifically what that was we can do K
get vulnerability report in the demo app
namespace give it the
name and now if we do o yl and pipe that
to yq now we get all of the details
about the vulnerabilities that it found
I can search for
critical and we can see that there is a
standard Library vulnerability in goang
1222 associated with the net net IP
module that was fixed in 122.4 so if we
wanted to fix this we should upgrade the
version of go that our base image is
using in order to get that updated
version we can click in to the link
provided to see the aqua security
summary of the vulnerability
or we can search this cve
number and see the
official
nist details about the cve it describes
what the cve
is has some additional resources and
again tells us which configurations it
has been fixed in and so with that basic
install of the DET triy operator we got
these custom resources that are now
giving us deep insight into
vulnerabilities across our workloads
there's many other projects that uh you
should consider taking a look at I just
wanted to highlight a couple that I find
very valuable and showcase how you go
about installing and then working with
the custom resources that these systems
deploy a few that I would just call out
here quickly are cert manager which is a
tool for provisioning and managing uh
TLS certificates the external Secrets
operator we're going to Showcase in the
the developer experience module but that
allows you to store the source of Truth
for Secrets outside of the cluster and
then pull those in and mirror them as
kubernetes Secrets which you can consume
from your workloads there's a number of
uh monitoring observability tooling
there's paid versions like data dog or
grafana Cloud there's self-hosted
options if you if you want to go the
open source route such as Prometheus
grafana Loki there's geit Ops tooling to
enable you to automatically keep your
cluster State synced with a uh with the
state of your configurations in git
there's service meshes from a networking
standpoint open policy agent from a
compliance and specifying rules for what
types of configurations can be deployed
in your cluster I mentioned cross Plan
before uh which is an infrastructure as
code tool that runs on top of kubernetes
K native is a serverless platform that
runs on top of kubernetes cubt allows
you to deploy and manage virtual
machines with kubernetes and then Valero
is a backup uh and restore tool for your
kubernetes cluster so I just want to
give a speed run of a bunch of valuable
tools that you should look into as you
build out your application platforms on
top of kubernetes explore the landscape
and hopefully you can find projects or
companies or tools that meet the needs
of your specific use cases at this point
we have our application running in
kubernetes we have a number of auxiliary
tools that are running to make our
experience better however there's still
a handful of developer experience
challenges that I want to call out and
address here in this module specifically
I want to look at iteration speed so how
long it takes you from making a change
to your application to being able to
test that change in a representative
environment and two Secrets management
every time we've shown a secret I have a
big warning that says Don't store this
in Version Control Etc and so we're
going to take a look at how you can
manage Secrets effectively without
needing to put them at risk in terms of
the iteration Loop or the speed with
which you can make a change and and see
that change represented in your
application
there's a number of different approaches
that people take some people do their
development outside of containers and
just ride the processes local on their
system the big challenge with that is
now your Dev environment is can be
significantly different than your
staging or production environments and
eventually you're going to hit edge
cases where the application behaves
differently based on those
differences a next approach that I see a
number of teams taking is using Docker
compose and Docker compose allows you to
declaratively specify a group of
services defined as containers along
with networking and configuration it
does allow you to test your applications
in their containerized form however
because you're configuring it with a
different tool the configurations and
networking and things like Ingress
anything that lives at sort of that
cluster layer are going to be different
in Docker compos versus kubernetes so
you're going to have some while it's
more similar than testing without
containers you're still going to have
some differences between your Docker
compost environment and your kubernetes
environment that you're deploying into
that being said Docker compose is very
easy to get started with and therefore
can be a good option early on the next
four tools all use kubernets directly
and have some variation on detecting
changes and automatically rebuilding and
pushing images to enable those changes
to show up in that cluster environment
as quickly as possible some of them you
work with local clusters others you set
up a proxy to a remote cluster and they
do some technical magic to sort of
intercept Network requests and Route
them to the right places as you're
figuring out how your team is going to
work with kubernetes and develop
applications for kubernetes I would
explore these options as I said we're
going to Showcase how to use tilt to
build out an environment like this
locally let's jump over to the code
editor and do just that let's go ahead
and navigate into our module 10
directory into the Tilt subdirectory and
take a look at our tilt file this top
level tilt file just references for
additional tilt files one for each of
our services that we're developing so
we've got one for our go API one for
node one for client react and one for
our load generator now you could set
this up to also deploy things like the
helm chart for
postgres tilt does support Helm out of
the box but for this demo I just wanted
to Showcase a basic setup where we're
going to deploy everything into the
cluster and then run tilt to iterate on
our services let's go take a look at
what the node API tilt file looks like
like so that lives in module 6 alongside
the code and I put it alongside the code
just because it makes it easier to
detect changes and rebuild and that's
where the docker file lives so if we go
here and open our tilt file this is
about as simple as it gets we specify
how to build the image in this case I'm
giving it a container registry name
giving it a build context and telling it
to use Docker it's going to use the
docker file that lives alongside this
tilt file I'm then telling it where the
yaml for the kubernetes resource using
that container image lives so this is is
the module 7 API node deployment. that's
the consumer of the container image and
then I'm telling it to port forward Port
3000 such that we can access this API
the goang one is going to look just a
little different and that's because
we're not using Docker build we're using
Co to build it so if we open up this
there's an extension for tilt that uses
Co runs the co build command again we
pass it some arguments tell it where the
yaml for the consumer of the container
image lives which port we want to
forward Network traffic the Tilt files
for the other two resources are going to
look quite similar so we don't need to
go through them we're going to make sure
we're pointing to the kind
cluster then we're going to make sure
that we've deployed our base resources
so as I mentioned currently the Tilt
file only deploys the four those four
Services we want to make sure we have
postres already running uh we want to
make sure we have traffic already
running Etc so let's go ahead and do
that by navigating to the module 7
then I can do a te apply all it's going
to install postgres install traffic
configure all my services Etc we can see
here all the services are in a running
State except for the load generator
which is in an image pull backoff State
it's because I haven't created that
Docker config Json Secret in order to
pull the image from the private Docker
registry I'm going to ignore that error
for now because tilt is actually going
to build a new version of the image
locally and push that to my container
registry so it's not going to be a
problem in order to access this
application we can look at the services
in our cluster and remember in order to
get a external IP for a load balancer
type service we had to run this cloud
provider kind software on the host so
I'm going to run that in the
background and that's going to allow
traffic sent to this IP address to be
routed to my Ingress
controller I've added this to my Edy
host so that when I access access
kubernetes course devops direct.com
it'll route that traffic to this to this
local IP address so now if I access this
in the browser I'm getting back my API
responses at this point we're ready to
run our tilt up
command so just running tilt up in the
context where that top level tilt file
lives it's going to bring up this
dialogue in this case I'm going to hit
space it's going to open up a browser
and we can see the services defined
within our system if we click into the
detail page we can see logs associated
with the various Services as well as any
logs coming from the Tilt system around
changes to those systems one thing I
noticed here is I had forgotten to
change the text that's displayed in the
browser bar here this still says devops
directive Docker course let's go ahead
and make that change and see how tilt
rebuilds and updates our image so I'll
go here into my
browser search for do obstructive Docker
course here it is
change it to
kubernetes save it and now let's go back
to our tilt window you can see client
react detected that change rebuilt our
image in 5 seconds and now if we go back
to this tab and click refresh we get the
updated text here and now any change we
make to any of our services tilt is
going to detect that and make that
modification you can see the load
generator is querying our node API and
so we're getting the logs from both of
those this is collating all those logs
together we could filter it down to a
specific service or we can get all of
the logs in one window we can also
filter by reg regular expressions or
whether the logs are coming from the
Tilt system or applications if we go
into our go Application let's just
change the health check uh to instead of
return pong return blah blah blah and
then we click save you'll see
immediately tilt detects the goang
change it's rebuilding our image you can
see the logs from that build process
and with that in 12 seconds it rebuilt
our image also now that my Docker cache
is hot let's change that back and see
how long it takes to
build if I go back over to
tilt
updating and it looks like the time was
cut in about half also some of these
other services are building much quicker
and so this is where you really want to
optimize your Docker file so that your
Docker image cache is working as
efficiently as possible and tilt also
has a concept of live updates which
allow you to specify certain files
within a project that will get synced
directly into a container without
needing to rebuild it for an interpreted
language this can make a huge difference
you may be able to skip the docker build
process entirely and sync changes
directly into your running container for
example if you were working with python
you could specify that anything under
the API directory should perform a sync
whereas any change to the dependencies
via the requirements.txt file that will
run a full build for a compiled language
it's a little less intuitive how this
works but as you can see in this Java
example it's syncing in some of the
compiled class files from the build jar
directory and then restarting the
process following these steps they were
able to optimize their build time for
this Java application from their initial
naive approach of nearly 90 seconds
which is clearly unacceptable for a
local development Loop all the way down
to under 5 Seconds there's docs for
using and optimizing tilt across a
number of different languages such as go
python node Etc as you're setting up
tilt make sure to go here and follow
their best practices to ensure that your
iteration speed is as quick as possible
we can also take a look at our
deployments to see how tilt is working
behind the scenes so if we scroll up
here to the image now instead of using
the tag that I had specified in my emo
file tilt has gone and built this
specific image and updated my deployment
such that it uses the new image rather
than the one I had specified if we are
done with our development we can just
kill this process and so by using
something like tilt you can now develop
directly against a kubernetes
configuration that will match as close
as possible to what you're going to run
in production this will allow you to
identify and debug issues that live not
only at your application layer but also
at that kubernetes layer or maybe in
your Ingress controller so I would
definitely take a look at tilt scaffold
mirror D or maybe telepresence and see
if one of those meets the needs of your
development teams the other major
developer experience issue that I've
hinted at throughout the course is
managing in of secrets so we for all of
our kubernetes configurations we are
able to declare them within our G
repository that serves as a source of
truth that we can then use to deploy
from and interact with however for
sensitive information we don't want to
store those in plain text in a git repo
and this leads to some friction or some
challenge in terms of managing those
Secrets there's a number of approaches
that I have seen used some of them work
better than others the first one that
many teams get started with with is to
manually create and update Secrets
separate from whatever process they're
updating and managing their other
configurations maybe they store the
secret. yaml in their password manager
and then whenever they need to make an
update someone has to log into that
password manager pull down that yaml
make some updates apply it manually to
the cluster this is how many teams get
started because it requires no
additional effort upfront however it
quickly becomes a nightmare to manage
and it's very easy to have a human make
a mistake in that process forget to
update the source of Truth or forget to
apply it to the cluster at the right
time I suggest that teams look at some
of these other options rather than stick
with that initial approach the second
option that we're going to leverage here
and demo is the external Secrets
operator so this allows you to store the
source of Truth for a secret in a system
outside of the cluster such as a secret
manager from a cloud provider uh could
be hashicorp Vault there's a number of
sources that you can use but this allows
you to have a non-sensitive
configuration in your repo that points
to an external configuration that has
the sensitive data and then it will
mirror the value from that external
secret into a kubernetes secret for you
to then consume within your cluster
another couple of options are sealed
secrets and Sops these are both
mechanisms to encrypt your secrets and
so if you encrypt your secrets with a
secure key the encrypted version then
becomes less sensitive and you're able
to store those encrypted versions in
side of get along with your other
configurations and then the key to
unseal those Secrets or decrypt them
will live only in the cluster and so
this can provide a mechanism to keep
your secrets in your git repo and manage
them just like all your other
configurations the challenge with these
workflows is that now in order to create
a secret you need to have access to that
encryption key and there's also some
challenges with rotating those
encryption keys if you need to down the
road you also could skip using
kubernetes Secrets entirely uh and use
something like hash Corp Vault or AWS
Secrets manager or Doppler and then you
can have your application query those
systems directly and pull in the
credential values at runtime avoiding
the need to deploy kubernetes Secrets at
all there is sort of a bootstrapping
process right where you need some
credential to get access to the system
at which point you can pull in the
credentials you need depending where
your Secret store lives that could be a
kubernetes secret that also could be
using workload identity like we did for
the cloud native PG backups where we
we're able to use a kubernetes service
account and tie it to a Google cloud
service account to leverage those Cloud
resources one good option here that
avoids the need for any static
credentials is to use your Cloud secret
manager and then use workload identity
to access those Secrets using either a
tool like external Secrets operator or
pulling them in at runtime from your
application directly the version of this
that we're going to implement for the
course is using external Secrets
operator with the Google Cloud platform
secret manager
so on the left hand side we've got we're
defining a secret in gcp secret manager
it's called external Secrets example the
value is the secret is stored in Google
Secrets manager we we then can define a
manifest within our git repository for
this external secret and it's going to
reference the Google Cloud secret pull
those values in to a kubernetes secret
we deploy this external secret resource
to our cluster the external Secrets
operator will be running in that cluster
see our new custom resource go over R
the value and populate a kubernetes
secret
accordingly let's go ahead and set this
up navigating into the external secret
subdirectory the first thing that we're
going to do is switch over to our Google
Cloud
cluster the reason we want to use our
Google Cloud cluster is that we can
leverage that workload identity feature
to access our secrets manager with no
static credentials now we can install
external Secrets which we're going to do
via Helm we're adding the external
Secrets repo and then we're installing
it with say Helm install command with
our external Secrets operator installed
we're now going to follow the same set
of paths we did for the Google Cloud
Storage bucket permissions we're going
to create an IM service account we're
going to tie that to a kubernetes
service account and then we can go ahead
and use that to access Google Cloud
platform secret
manager so we're creating a service
account named external secrets with the
g-cloud command line we then need to
Grant access for that I am service
account to access Secrets within Google
Cloud so we tie our service account that
we just created to that role so that we
can access secrets we then need to
attach the workload identity user role
to that service account that will allow
us to tie together our kubernetes
service account with the IM service
account and specifically we give it the
context of the kubernetes service
account that's going to be the consumer
in this case it's in the external
Secrets name space and it's named
external secrets we then need to an
our kubernetes service account with the
appropriate annotation to enable that
connection to take place if we look here
at our service account The annotation we
provided is for the gke IM Service uh
specifically we can we want to be able
to use the IM service account named
external secrets in this gcp project now
if instead of defining this service
account yaml in our repo and applying it
after the fact we could have handled
this within our Helm's installation
directly and so to do that we would need
a values. yo file and specifically we
would set the looking at the helm chart
here we can see that there's a service
account uh field and within that there's
an annotations object and so we can set
service account
annotations and then here is our
annotation and now within our
installation command we're going to make
that an upgrade install command and
let's pass it our values file
and now if we
reinstall now that annotation would
automatically be added to our service
account without needing that extra
step the next piece of the puzzle is to
create uh what is known as a Secret
store and so this is the custom resource
within external Secrets operator that
tells the operator where to find the
secrets and so for this use the cluster
Secret store kind you could also use a
Secret store which is namespace scoped
I'm calling this the gcp key store uh
and specifically I'm using the Google
Cloud platform Secrets manager within my
particular project so if I apply
that it's come up it's come up it's
ready and it has readwrite capabilities
great now we can apply an external
secret configuration and so this is the
same configuration I showed here on the
slide and let's take a look at what's in
here I'm naming it example it's going
into the external Secrets name space
every 1 hour I want the operator to
check for new values and automatically
pull those in there is a way to add an
annotation to our external secret to
force it to sync sooner but 1 hour is
fine as a default I then reference that
cluster Secret store that I just created
and here I'm specifying which kubernetes
secret I want external Secrets operator
to populate using these data and then
finally I specify where external Secrets
operator should find the values for this
particular secret so I'm saying look for
the secret in Google Cloud Secrets
manager name external Secrets example
and then where within the kubernetes
secret I should store those values so if
you
recall if we go back to the secrets
manager I've prepopulated this secret
it's called external Secrets example
gcp and the value
here is
this if we look at that external secret
I just created we can see that it has
successfully synced and is ready and
what that means is if we now look at the
secrets in this namespace
here is the secret here's the secret
that it created based on the target
name if we look at the
values and specifically under the data
key and under this key so here is the
key that I specified it should store the
value at
and then we'll base 64d
code and we get the value that was
stored here on the secret manager side
within our kubernetes secret and so now
we can store this external secret
resource which has no sensitive data in
our git repo alongside with the rest of
our
configurations but store the source of
Truth within Google Cloud secret manager
which is purpose-built for controlling
and managing sensitive information the
team can go into Google Cloud secret
manager and update and manage Secrets
accordingly you can control access to
those Secrets directly via Google Cloud
am but you also get the benefit of
automatically syncing those into your
kubernetes secrets that you can consume
from applications this is a pattern that
I use quite frequently uh for managing
Secrets as long as you're on a cloud
provider that has a secret manager like
this and AWS Google and Azure all do
this can be a great option to streamline
Secrets management and avoid that manual
out ofand process that you may have
started with so hopefully that gives you
an idea of how you can solve some of the
developer experience challenges
associated with kubernetes both the
iteration speed so that process of
building pushing and deploying new
images into your cluster as you iterate
as well as the secrets management
problem of how you can efficiently
manage Secrets while also keeping them
secure in the next module of the course
I want to take a look at how to debug
applications running on kubernetes if
something is going wrong and
specifically I want to focus more on
issues at the kubernetes layer that
would be preventing your application
from running or causing them to crash
rather than at the application layer
there is an awesome visual flowchart
guide published by learn cuberes doio if
you go to this URL you can find it there
there's an accompanying blog post here's
the full resolution version of that
you're almost always going to start with
a get pods command this is going to give
you a high level overview of what pods
exist in the cluster and what state they
are in then based on their state you'll
follow the path and try and figure out
what exactly is going on by looking at
the logs you might see that there's an
application issue by looking at the
description you can see all the
different events that the cluster issues
about the pods if your pod appears to be
ready but is not working you could port
forward to that pod and access it
directly from your system and so while I
don't use this directly anymore and
generally just know these commands this
going to be a great starting point as
you're looking at debugging an
application for the first time and
you're not sure what to do next to use
as an example for trying this out I'm
going to deploy an example application
from Google called the microservices
demo it is a pretend online shop made up
of a number of different microservices
as you can see here there's one for
checkout one for currency one for
sending emails one for generating load
Etc and I have purposefully taken their
configurations and made a handful of
changes such that when you try to deploy
it it will break let's go ahead and
deploy that broken version of the
microservices demo into our cluster and
then try to walk through and figure out
what specifically is going on and how to
fix it uh let's just use the SEO cluster
for this one one any of the Clusters
would be fine and then we'll navigate to
our debugging module we'll start by
creating a namespace and then we're
going to install our microservices
demo to do that I'm just going to
apply run a cube CTL apply F on the
microservices demo yo file in the
subdirectory there's a note here at the
top which references both the original
project from Google Cloud platform as
well as the fork that I made where I
introduced these braks if we look at all
the different services in our cluster we
can see that the microservices demo
created a number of services within our
cluster it provisioned this load
balancer service here and so let me just
access that from the browser and see
what's going on okay so we're able to
use the load balancer to access
something but it's surfacing this 500
internal server error uh it looks like
it's trying to connect to one of the
services in this case could not retrieve
currency so maybe it's the Currency
Service uh it looks like that failed and
so this front end is bubbling that
application error back up to
us let's check the status of the pods
this is also a good opportunity to
showcase a tool called K9s which is a
text user interface for kubernetes and
so if I just do
K9s it will start a a Tue a text text
based user interface and I can navigate
around via my keyboard and so rather
than having to issue a whole bunch of kg
get pods K describe pods Etc I can just
run K9s and navigate around accordingly
you can see the current Cube CTL context
at the top and as you can see four of my
services appear to be broken the one
that we saw on the front end was
referencing a currency so it's probably
this Currency Service I can hit the D
command to describe it and now we're
dropped into a description of that pod
if we scroll here to the bottom we can
see all the events that kubernetes is
publishing about this pod and these will
by default persist for one hour so after
an hour these would get wiped out but we
can see 2 minutes ago it was assigned to
a specific node we then pulled the
container image it started but then the
Readiness probe failed so let's take a
look at what's going on here if we
scroll through
the definition for this pod for this
deployment we can see the reason here is
that this was O killed that means out of
memory killed they tried to use more
memory than the limit that was specified
and so if we look down here in the
request section it's only requesting 5
meges memory and it has a limit of 10 so
why don't we bump those up and give it
additional memory and see if that solves
the issue I'll open up my microservices
demo. I'll search for
Currency Service find that
deployment and as you can see I've
commented out the original values and
have replaced them with
these insufficient values so if I
replace the original values and then do
an apply buy
again now let's go back into
K9s you can see the Currency Service
original pod was crashing we have a new
replica coming up from that modified
deployment the new one appears to be
healthy and the old one was taken down
okay so that's one of our four issues
solved let's load the application on the
front end again and see what happens and
see if we get a different error okay uh
so we're still getting 500 error but in
this time it's talking about the cart
service let's take a look at the cart
service it is indeed in a non-ready
state and we can see that it has been
restarting over and over and over okay
let's go ahead and describe that we're
going to take a look at the events we
assigned it we pulled the image we
started and then the liveness probe is
failing if the liveness probes that we
specify are not passing then kubernetes
will assume that the application is
unhealthy and will kill the pod in order
to try again if we scroll up to look at
our Readiness and live Ness probe
definitions here we see that for livess
it's checking on our pod on port
8080 and our Readiness is the same and
so why might that not be working if we
scroll up here to The Container
definition we can see that the actual
Port that's specified is Port 7070 the
cuet is trying to check for liveness on
port 8080 but the application is
actually listening on Port 7070 let's go
ahead and fix that
to our definition we go to the cart
service scroll
down and as you can see I had commented
out the original version and replaced it
with this bogus Port now we'll
reapply and we'll go back into K9s to
see if that fixes
things we've got our new pod coming up
associated with that modified deployment
it appears to be running but it's not in
a ready state
yet and now our cart service appears to
be healthy we've got two additional pods
that seem like they're having issues uh
let's take a look at the reddis cart we
see that it is in an image pull backoff
state so that means that kubernetes is
unable to pull the image associated with
the container we look at the events we
can see more details about that pulling
image reddis deian failed to pull image
redis Debian
so let's go to the dockerhub page for
the reddest container image look under
tags and so we're trying to pull the dbn
tag no tags found so perhaps this tag is
just simply invalid instead let's take a
look at one of these other versions
let's use version
7.2.5 we'll go into the AML file we'll
search for reddis cart we'll find the
container image and yes so here's the
bogus image that I had added to make it
fail it looks like the original
definition uses this redus Alpine image
let's go ahead and use that we'll apply
go into
K9s and now our redis cart service has
come up healthy uh and finally we have a
our load Generator Service oh
interestingly the cart service is still
failing let's take a look at
that um oh it looks like I maybe
modified only the Readiness probe and
not the liveness probe so let's go and
fix
that uh yeah so I modified one of these
back to the original value but not the
other so hopefully that fixes our cart
service and then the load generator is
the final one not working let's go ahead
and describe it if we scroll down look
at the
events two nodes have insufficient CPU
so zero of two nodes are available for
scheduling this pod two have
insufficient CPU let's go ahead and look
at the CPU required and we can see that
the limit is specified as requiring up
to five CPUs virtual CPUs and the
request is specified as needing up to
three CPUs and I believe these nodes
that I provisioned in SEO have only two
CPUs each so that makes sense that the
deployment is requesting at least three
CPUs just for this application but none
of the nodes have capacity to satisfy
that so it gets stuck in this pending
State let's look at the load generator
service and here you can see the
original CPU request was 300 I had up
that to 3,000 the original CPU limit was
500 I'd up that to 5,000 and those
values were just too high and so our
cluster could not meet the demand we can
now apply one more
time go into
K9s looks like our load generator is
coming up now it's healthy and now all
of our services for our application are
healthy let's go ahead and access it
from the browser refresh the page and
now this is what the demo application is
supposed to look like we've got our
products different pricing we can choose
any number we can add them to the cart
those will get saved in the cart we can
switch to a different currency and so
now all of the microservices appear to
be functioning correctly and that's
represented both by the fact that our
pods are all running and healthy and by
the fact that we can access our
application success F from within the
browser now all of these breaks were
within the uh deployment definitions
there could also be issues obviously uh
maybe let's say between the services and
the deployments if you specified the
wrong set of selectors or the wrong
ports my goal here was to give you an
idea of how to look at the information
that the kubernetes cluster provides
either via the qctl command line or via
a tool like K9s if you prefer and walk
down all the potential different issues
identify them and fix them and so as you
work with kubernetes inevitably you're
going to run into some issues make sure
to take a step back think about what the
root cause could be and systematically
work through the different avenues for
gathering information and identifying
and fixing those bugs up until this
point we've had a single configuration
that we've been deploying into a single
kubernetes cluster this is valuable but
in any real world scenario you're going
to have multiple environments that
you're going to want to deploy your
applications to this can be long-lived
environments like a production
environment or a staging environment
there also could be short-lived
ephemeral environments that you want to
spin up and spin down quickly in order
to do this we need to have some approach
that allows us to take a common
configuration and reuse it across
multiple different places there's a few
popular tools that I'm going to cover
here in this section describing the
trade-offs between them and eventually
building out a fully working example of
our demo app that we'll deploy to
multiple clusters the first tool that
I'll cover is customize uh it is a
command line tool that is built into
Cube CTL it also can be installed as a
standal and binary and it uses what is
called a base and overlay model you
start out by defining some base
configuration this is going to have all
of the common fields that all of your
environments use and maybe some default
values as well then for each environment
you want to deploy into you will specify
an overlay so only fields that are
different for your particular
environment need to be specified in an
overlay so it can ideally be a much
smaller configuration customize then
takes those two and merges them together
to get your end resulting configuration
it's very easy to get started with
conceptually as well as the fact that
you already have the tooling built in to
cube CTL however there are some major
limitations that you'll run into
eventually related to how it handles
arrays within yaml and and if you need
to replace a specific value within a
yaml array or if you need to do patching
for multi-line Strings within
yaml there's no support for that so
you'll have to replace the entire
multi-line string block that is
particularly relevant if you use file
like config Maps where you're defining a
config for a particular file as a
multi-line string within your config map
yl another very popular tool that is
used uh to handle deploying into
multiple environments is Helm we looked
at Helm earlier in this course and so
this is just taking that tool and
applying it to your first-party
applications Helm uses a templating
model so you'll have your chart which
includes a number of templates for all
the resources you plan to deploy within
those template files you can specify
variables that you want to be able to
substitute in values for and then for
each environment you'll have a custom
values. file containing the specific
values for that environment when you do
a Helm install or Helm upgrade it will
take those values substitute them into
the template files and pass the
resulting hydrated
templates into the cluster one nice
thing about Helm is it has this concept
of hooks hooks allow you to specify The
Ordering of deployment of resources and
so if there are dependencies between
certain things let's say you need to run
a migration job before you upgrade your
application you can use hooks to encode
that logic Helm charts do represent sort
of another deployment artifact that
you're going to need to build publish
and manage so it's just another process
that you have to deal with and
potentially automate I think some
challenges with Helm are that the
templating style those go templates
quickly become hard to read as you add
more and more templating to your chart
Helm also adds a significant amount of
boiler plate even for the most simple of
use cases and so if you only need to
substitute in an image tag and maybe a
few other values like resource requests
and limits um Helm can feel quite heavy
for that and then another challenge can
be crd management so we talked about
custom
resources earlier in the course and how
tools use them while you can install all
crds via Helm there's not a lot of
control over how you would upgrade those
crds with Helm and or if you had
conflicting Helm charts that were trying
to install different versions of a crd
that could become an issue as well now a
third tool that I want to highlight and
one that I'm particularly excited about
so much so that I sponsor uh the creator
of this tool on GitHub is clue control
or clue cuddle it also uses a templating
model similar to helm
uh and also has hooks for configuring
the order of deployments it it requires
much less boiler plate than Helm when
implementing it for a project you will
have a number of template files kind of
like Helm you'll have a clue control.
yaml file that you define your
environment in and then within that file
you'll specify the different
environments you want to deploy to and
you can have variables at that top level
that get templated in or you can use
those top level environments as sort of
an entry point you store a configuration
for each of those environments within
the templates themselves it integrates
nicely with Helm and customized so if
you're already using those tools it's
not too difficult to migrate over piece
by piece as you see fit and there's a
built-in giops engine which you can use
as an alternative to something like flux
CD or Argo CD that allows you to
leverage all of the features that clue
control has there's also just a ton of
nice developer experience features
within this tool that I think will
become apparent as we start to interact
with it I do want to call out a few
other options that I've seen in the wild
some people will Implement their own
sort of templating solution with bash
and M stubs or using yq to substitute
values within the AML this generally
works and is fairly simple to get
started with but over time you end up
with this very complex convoluted uh
setup that's hard to maintain uh there's
a tool called timoni which is a quite
powerful application packaging system
that allows you to package up both your
application container images as well as
all the configuration for the different
environments as oci artifacts it uses a
language called Q which can have a bit
of a steep learning curve but it's worth
looking into if you have nuanced
application packaging needs there's also
uh providers for infrastructure as code
tools like terraform and palumi that
allow you to provision kubernetes
resources via terraform or via palumi
and then CD Kates is a tool which
enables you to write and deploy
kubernetes configuration
using general purpose programming
languages like typescript python or go
and by doing so which allow you to use
the control flow within those languages
to produce configurations unique to any
particular environment let's go ahead
and jump over to the code editor uh and
take a look at what some configurations
with customize Helm and clue control
will look like for our demo application
okay let's navigate into the module 12
subdirectory within this directory we've
got a Helm directory Dory a clue control
directory and a customized directory
we're going to start with customize by
looking at the structure here we can
see I've built out a configuration for
all of my services I haven't included
for example the helm installation for
postgres or the helm installation for
traffic however this should give you an
idea of what a customized overlay model
would look like for your first Party
Services as you can see within the base
directory I have one subdirectory for
each of my services here uh within that
I have the resource yl files these are
going to be very similar to what we saw
in module 7 where we deployed onto
kubernetes in a single environment I
then have in addition to my base I have
a production subdirectory and a staging
subdirectory each of these contains only
a subset of the resource definitions
that need to be modified from that base
so let's take a look at our go based API
and so let's go into the base for our
goang application this is a deploy yaml
file that is actually identical to what
we saw in module 7 we're defining a set
of containers including the one that we
built and pushed we're specifying the
port we're giving it some resource
limits we're specifying the security
contexts so this is all stuff that we've
seen before however this image tag is
something that's going to differ between
environments right so how can we write
an overlay that will allow us to modify
just this subset of the Amo file if we
go into our production overlay for the
goang API we have a few files we start
out with this customization this is sort
of how you tell customize which files it
should reference in my base I say each
of these files represents a resource
within this section is going to be the
base definition of any of your
kubernetes resources however within our
overlay under the resources section we
pass a path to the base folder and
that's going to pull in all of those
resources from that base folder and then
I have a number of patches here so the
first patch is my deployment. yaml let's
take a look at what that looks like and
so in my patches I'm changing two fields
from my deployment. yaml I'm specifying
instead of one replica I want two
replicas for production and instead of
version Fubar baz I want version
production version when we go to apply
this to the cluster using customize
customize is going to take that base and
then replace those two particular Fields
within this yaml such that the resulting
deployed specification will have these
values if we look at our stage overlay
in staging we're going to run a single
replica and we're going to run the
staging version so this shows you that
we can share most of that configuration
in that common base and then only modify
the fields that we care about via these
overlays the other patch that I'm making
is replacing one of the routes in my
Ingress rule for production the host is
going to be kubernetes course. DAV
obstructor and for staging I'm going to
postfix this Dash staging to the end of
it now you'll see you'll notice that
this Pat looks a little different and
this brings up that limitation that I
mentioned around customized not having
great capabilities
for merging together configurations
using yaml arrays So within the Ingress
route the routes are a yaml array and so
in order to figure out which rule we
want to modify we have to use this style
of patch where we specify an index
within that array customize is not able
to automatically align our Pat to a
particular entry within the array that's
why we had to use this style of patch
for that particular use case because we
didn't specify patches for any of the
other resources such as the secret or
the service those values are going to
get deployed as is from the base into
all of our environments the other
services look quite similar we're going
to be patching in a new image tag and
maybe modifying the resource requests or
the replica numbers I'll let you review
those on your own time let's look at how
we would interact with these setups if
we want to render out the values but not
apply them to the cluster we can do a
few things so let's render out the
production values to do that we can call
Cube C customize and then pass it the
path to the to the overlay environment
we want to render and then I'm just
piping that to yq to get uh the nice
syntax highlighting here as you can see
let's scroll down to the API
goang we've got the host that got
patched
in and if we find the deployment we can
see we got two replicas and our
production version is the one being used
let's instead render out staging and see
the difference so for staging our
deployment has a single replica uses
staging version and if we look at the
Ingress
route and if we look at the Ingress
route oh looks like I have a bug where I
didn't patch that properly in one of my
overlays looks like for node I
did for goang I did and for client react
engine X I did not so let's take a look
at fixing that so if we go into our
staging
overlay for client react Ingress route
this was incorrect and should be
staging let's render it and now our
Ingress route for the staging
configuration is correct if we wanted to
apply these to the cluster we could
navigate to the corresponding directory
do Cube
c-k and then pass it the path to that
directory uh because I don't have real
image version t I had that production
version and staging version as
placeholders I'm not going to do that
right now but that is how you would and
so as you can see getting started with
customize is quite easy and so I think
it's a great place for people using
kubernetes to get started with deploying
into multiple environments the next tool
that I mentioned is Helm which I've
already covered quite a bit we'll take a
very quick look at what a Helm chart for
one of our services might look like the
types of values that we might expose as
the interface so under the helm
subdirectory you can see we have chart
directory we've got our chart. yaml um
within the templates is where you define
the resources that will be deployed and
so here I just have a single example if
we were defining a Helm chart for our
goang API so under here you can see this
deployment. again is going to look very
similar to what we saw before the main
difference being now we've got this go
templating that allows us to specify
number of replicas in the values.
replicas and a tag that we want to use
for our container image as values.
verion in our Ingress route we're able
to substitute in an environment postfix
and then our secret and service our
static yo that have no modification
between environments if we now look at
the values. yo I've got three values
specified I've got an environment
postfix a replicas and a version the
values. within your chart are going to
be the default values for everything so
I've specified default version one
replica and an empty string here such
that the Ingress route template
collapses down and we get kubernetes
course. devops.com then I've got these
example values file that will show how
you can pass these in when you're doing
a cube control install uh such that they
get used as we render out those
templates let's start by rendering out
the different values files and seeing
how that impacts our manifests to do
that we can use the helm template
command so here I'm calling Helm
template passing it the path to the helm
chart and then piping that to yq just so
we get nice
syntax highlighting and this will render
out the values based on those
default based on the defaults in our
values. AML so we would expect the image
tag to be default version a single
replica and an empty string used in that
Ingress route if we go to our deployment
you can see default version was indeed
used we have a single replica and our
Ingress route did not have any postfix
on our subdomain great if if we then
want to render out production for
example we want to pass that Helm
template
command the-- values option passing it
the
values file that we want to use in this
case it's the values. production. yaml
so we're going to expect two replicas
and production version to have been used
scrolling but down we see that's exactly
what happened two replicas and the
production version was used now if
instead of Helm template we used a Helm
upgrade D- install like we've been using
for a lot of our third party Helm charts
we would pass it that D- values option
pass it our values file and these would
get applied to the cluster as a Helm
release now the other things that I
mentioned about Helm is like this is an
additional artifact that you need to
build and publish and version Etc uh so
we have a package command so if I do a t
package that runs the helm package and
passes it the path to our chart using
the using the version that's in our
chart. yaml it will then create a
tarball containing our Helm chart so
here we see API goang Helm chart version
0.1.0 so it bundled up our Helm chart
into this package we can then take that
package and push it to a registry of our
choosing so if I do T push it will do
Helm push passing it the tarball that I
just generated passing an oci registry
where I have created a reposit itory for
this particular chart so I had created
this repository on dockerhub and as you
can see I just pushed this version a few
seconds ago now others could connect to
this repo and pull down that version to
consume within their clusters hopefully
that gives you an idea of how you could
write Helm charts for your own services
and choose the specific configurations
that you want to expose now let's use
clue control to do the same thing and
for with clue control we're actually
going to build out a full version of our
application including the third party
dependencies we'll deploy a staging
environment to our SEO cluster and we'll
deploy a production environment to our
gke cluster now before we build out the
entire project let's start with a single
service and see how we would use clue
control to Define our templates and
environments that we're going to deploy
our goang application into from there
we'll extend it and add all the other
services including our third party
dependency so I'll navigate into the
clue control single service directory
and we'll open up this clue control.
yaml file which is where you define all
the different environments as you can
see I've defined two targets targets are
the language used by clue control to
Define an environment you're going to
deploy into often times this will
correspond one to one with a kubernetes
cluster so a single Target may represent
a single cluster however that's not
required you can have multiple targets
that go into the same cluster into
different name spaces for example and
all the examples here I'm going to have
that one to one mapping from Target to
Cluster there's a really nice feature
within a Target that you can specify a
context this is the context within your
Cube config file by doing so you can
avoid the potential for you being
authenticated against the wrong cluster
and applying an incorrect configuration
which could be catastrophic if you did
so against the production environment by
adding a context here you're able to
eliminate that whole class of bugs
entirely in addition to targets you can
Define arguments these are top level
global variables that can be used
throughout the entire clue control
project in this case I'm passing a
single argument and that is the name of
the environment so I'm going to pass it
either production or staging using that
argument I'm going to be able to load
additional configurations that will get
injected into my templates this
discriminator field is how clue control
keeps track of which resources it is
managing so you need to have some sort
of discriminator here which will allow
the tool to uniquely distinguish between
different targets if you're into
separate clusters this is less critical
but still best practice if you're
deploying into the same cluster this is
the only way that clue control can know
which resources it is managing for a
particular configuration and that allows
it to do things like prune and delete
resources safely so here I'm templating
in the name of the target itself into
this discriminator so this will be clue
control- staging and clue control-
production as my discriminator the next
important concept and file to look at is
the deployment. yo file this is separate
from the concept of of a kubernetes
deployment so you'll see these
deployment. yo files throughout the clue
control project within my repo I'm using
lowercase deployment to mean a clue
control deployment and then as I have
throughout the course I use the
uppercase D deployment to refer to a
kubernetes deployment if we look in this
file it has a few things first it's
loading in additional variables so like
I said that single argument at the top
level you could put more arguments at
the top level but it can quickly get
quite noisy if you put all of your
templating configurations within your
clue control file so instead I've opted
to have just the environment name there
and then I'm able to use that
environment name to load in an
additional configuration file so within
this I'm loading in a file at config SL
staging or production so if I go in my
config subdirectory you can see I have a
production file and a staging file and
these configurations at this top level
are going to be sort of variables that
are shared across different services so
for example I have my host name which is
shared between my two backend Services
as well as my
react client and so by putting it at
this location I'm then going to be able
to reference that shared vs. host name
across all those different manifests and
so depending which Target I choose I'll
either load in kubernetes course. Devas
direct.com or I'll postfix that- staging
just like we saw in some of the other
tools also within deployment I have
further deployments listed and so you're
able to reference other deployments to
recursively go through your directories
and Define how you want all the
resources to be applied in this case I
have one path called names spaces that's
this subdirectory and I have another
path called Services here I then have a
barrier and what a barrier does is
ensures that items that come prior to it
in this list will be executed first such
that my name spaces will be created
before my services try to spin up and
then finally you can place a common
label so these will be kubernetes labels
that get applied to all the resources
that are being provisioned by this
deployment we can then take a look at
these sub deployments so if we look in
nam spaces it's just a single namespace
object because namespaces just as
Manifest at the top level it will
automatically pick it up in the services
subdirectory I'm going to have multiple
Services here so I have my API goang
folder and then the deployment
references that subdirectory and finally
within there I have one more deployment
here I'm passing it a path to the
Manifest file manifest is where all of
my kubernetes manifest are going to live
and then I have another config
subdirectory and these will be
configurations that are specific to this
application so if I load that one up I'm
loading in a version and a number of
replicas that will get used in my
deployment. yo file so if I go here in
my deployment. yo I can see I'm
referencing that API go lang. replicas
that's going to get loaded in from this
config it's going to be two for
production or one for staging as well as
the version is going to get used from
this uh API goang specific configuration
but then if I look at the Ingress route
here I'm using using that shared vs.
host name which is coming from my top
level configuration files so that's
coming from this top level configuration
and so this while it's a relatively
minim minimal example shows a lot of the
different ways that you can handle
templating and managing configurations
for different environments including
sharing some of those configurations
across Services while having others
being service specific similar to helm
template or cube C customize clue
control has a render option so we're
going to pass it DT flag to specify
Target most of the clue control commands
will require this target flag and that's
because you need to know the context of
the Target that you are trying to
execute that command against so here
we're going to render out the production
configs print them all to the console
and then pipe that to yq to get syntax
highlighting as we can see we get all of
the resources associated with our with
our go based API and also we get that
name space at the top of the list
because that's what's going to be
deployed first it's adding some
convenient labels you can see this
common label that we had specified if
you recall within our top level
deployment. yl we said we want this
kubernetes course label to be applied to
all of our
resources and as you can see here it is
here it is you can see our number of
replicas was injected as well as the
version that we
specified let's now render out the
staging values you can see our host name
indeed has this post fix like we would
want and then then our deployment has a
single replica and is using a different
version that it's picking up from that
staging specific config and so that's
how we can configure a single service
let's take a look at what the clue
control configuration looks like when we
add in the remainder of the services and
start to add third party Helm charts and
configuring those as well so I'll
navigate up One Directory to the clue
control directory and let me just show
you what the directory hierarchy looks
like as you can see I've added a whole
bunch more things
the API node client react uh load
generator python etc those are going to
look quite similar to what we just saw
with the API goang where each of them is
going to have a config subdirectory with
a production and a staging yaml file one
for each environment they're going to
have a manifest subdirectory containing
all of the kubernetes resource manifests
with those template placeholders that
will be overridden at deploy time what's
new here is that I have this thirdparty
directory where I'm now installing Cloud
native PG as well as traffic from a Helm
chart let me look at my top level
deployment and we can compare it to our
deployment from before so previously I
just had namespaces and then a barrier
and then Services now I have name spaces
a barrier now my thirdparty applications
and I need to have another barrier
because my postgres cluster that I'm
deploying will need to use the custom
resources that cloud native PG is
installing and then finally my my first
party services are going to run last
once all of that base layer of
infrastructure is deployed going into
our thirdparty
subdirectory we've got two things we've
got our traffic installation and our
Cloud native PG installation and then
we're specifying that we want to wait
for cloud native PG to be ready before
this deployment is declared as ready
clicking in here you can see we have a
few things we have one the name space
that will be that it will be deployed
into two we have a Helm values file that
if we wanted to use any non-default
values we could specify them here and
three we specify the chart so we've got
our Helm repo name the version we want
to deploy what we want the helm release
to be named the name space we want to
deploy into and then this output file is
an optional field but it is where a clue
control will render out the contents of
the of the helm chart clue control the
way that it interacts with Helm is
actually to render out the contents and
then apply them via its own mechanism
rather than calling out to helm directly
and so this is a file name where the
rendered out contents will temporarily
live we then have a customization yaml
which tells clue control how to apply
the final resources in this case we're
going to deploy the the name space and
then we're going to deploy that output
file that I just
mentioned which will have the rendered
contents of our Helm chart this does
mean that the behavior of Helm hooks may
be slightly different when using a Helm
chart with clue control uh they do their
best to maintain behaviors across those
two and there's similar hooks within
clue control that it will use but it may
not be exactly one to one uh in terms of
the behavior of those hooks so that's
just something to call out here the
cloud native PG subdirectory looks
pretty much identical we have the name
space it's going into we have the helm
chart itself including version repo name
Etc and then we have any values that we
would want to apply in this case we're
installing with all the default values
now the one subdirectory of our services
that's going to look a little different
than the others is the postgres
directory um this is because here we are
deploying a cloud native PG cluster
that using the custom resource
definitions that the cloud native PG
operator is
installing so again we have a specific
configuration just for the subdirectory
here we're saying in production we want
two instances so we'll have a read write
instance and a readon instance in
staging we're just going to have the
one and then our manifests here are
going to be a cluster so this is using
this Cloud native PG custom resource
deploying it into the postgres namespace
setting up a super minimal
persistent volume and referencing a
secret where the password is going to be
for the super user If This Were your
actual application you would not want to
use the super user you would need to
have likely a much larger disc you would
probably want to set up backups the goal
of this is to get a baseline cluster
setup that we can run our application
against so let's go ahead and deploy our
staging configuration onto the SEO
cluster this was the context name for
that cluster in my Cube
config to Showcase that the context set
in this configuration does indeed get
applied let's do a cube
CTX uh for My Kind
cluster so even though my default
context is this kind cluster clue
control is going to use the context
specified
here we'll do T deploy
staging and that just does clue control
deploy passing it the staging Target you
can see that when you run this deploy
command it goes through a number of
steps to figure out what it needs to
deploy it then will give you a diff
against the current state of the cluster
and your proposed deployment so in this
case all these objects are new it's
deploying all of our application
resources it's defining the custom
resource definitions for thirdparty apps
Etc one thing I didn't call out that I
will look at now is the hooks that I use
to ensure that my migrator job runs
before my applications
if we look under our goang application
under manifest the DB migrator
job has a hook specified as
predeployment
or it's a little bit less realistic you
should not have two services that are
depending on the same API schema um in
this case the node API is not coupled to
when this migration job runs but I just
wanted to Showcase how you could apply
this pattern and you would follow the
same approach if it were more realistic
and you had each service talking to its
own schema or its own database entirely
but that's going to ensure that the
migrator runs before the service is
installed and or
upgraded it's giving us some warnings
about uh validation web
Hooks and the fact that some of the
custom resources don't exist in the
cluster so the dry run can't validate
them let's go ahead and
proceed here we started it created our
two name spaces it's now applying our
thirdparty services because of how they
were they were next in that top level
deployment. yl it waited for our Cloud
native PG deployment to become healthy
and now it's
applying our application manifest it's
deploying that migrator job let's go
ahead and
look in the demo app
namespace uh let's look at the logs for
that K logs DV
migrator okay we got a connection
refused I wonder if that is just that
the
cluster the clust cluster itself wasn't
healthy
yet yeah so it looks like our cluster is
still coming
up looks like my postgres instance is
now up and running let me go ahead and
just rerun the clue control install and
that's the nice thing about having
everything defined declaratively we can
just reapply that same configuration and
ideally issues will self-resolve as the
resources come alive we can see the
missing objects from last time are the
ones that we're trying to wait for that
migrator job to finish so if I run
this we've got our migrator job should
be coming
up looks like the migrator job completed
successfully then created our go API
deployment so that's great our react
client is in a crash loop back off State
let's look at the
logs it was not finding our go API
running now that it is running the next
time kubernetes tries to restart it it
should come up
healthy or we can speed that along by
doing a k roll out
restart deployment client
react great looks like it came up
healthy that
time now the final issue is that our
load generator python is in an image
pull back off state that indicates to me
that the secret that should be used for
the dockerhub Repository is not working
properly off screen I just added that
secret let me go ahead and do a roll out
restart for
that pain creating
State and we're in a running
State okay and so now our application
appears to be healthy let's look across
all the name
spaces if we find our public endpoint
for the load balancer here it is this is
what traffic is going to be listening on
so let's go ahead and modify our Etsy
host
file we could also set a public DNS
record for this but it's just faster to
do it this
way now if we navigate in our browser
zoom in and there is our first manual
human request to our API so we see the
request count one for our goang API uh
but the load balancer sorry the load
generator has already made a number of
requests to our node API let's refresh
again we see a second request here and
this continues to tick upwards so there
we have it our staging configuration
deployed to our SEO cluster
now and now just to showcase the power
of why we set this up in the first place
let's deploy our production
configuration to the GK cluster to do
that we can just switch to
our GK
context I have it specified here in my
top level clue control config file let's
just modify this let's do a
deploy again we got the same listing of
objects we've got uh some warnings about
the custom resource definitions not
existing we're going to proceed
anyways now once again it's going to
need this job is going to fail until
that uh postes cluster is healthy and so
let's just let it sit here for a minute
and see if the retries on that job will
be sufficient it should retry I believe
six times by default uh will be
sufficient to have it run successfully
on this first go it looks like the first
of my two replicas is now healthy so
let's see now
if the next time this job
executes if it will succeed I think it
will it did succeed however it looks
like it looks like the clue control
command timed out so I could either
extend the Timeout on the clue control
command I could add an additional
dependency to ensure that the migrator
job didn't execute until my cluster was
up uh but in this case this is really
only going to happen the first time we
deploy so I'm just going to I'm just
going to go ahead and rerun my apply
command and allow it to proceed a second
time
looks like everything was applied I'm
not sure what
this uh issue here at the end I'm seeing
something about how the command line is
trying to access the secrets that it's
provisioning um but it looks like
everything applied
successfully uh once again my low
generator is in an image pull back off
State this is a fresh cluster with
no with no image pull secrets in it let
me deploy that off screen and then I'll
roll out restart the
deployment our load generator is now
healthy also you can see that I have two
goang apis here because I implemented
that configuration with the
production instance having two replicas
and the staging instance only having the
one I can grab my external IP for that
load
balancer modify my Etsy
hosts now we can navigate to the
production
URL there we go we're live in
production and so I now have a single
configuration that I can use to very
easily template the specific values that
I want to change across environments we
saw the now let me make just a trivial
change to one of our applications for
example let's add another replica here
to production and deploy again
this diff feature is incredibly powerful
and can help you from making stupid
mistakes because we can see exactly what
is changing between resources here we
see the number of replicas in this
specific deployment is going from two up
to three
great I haven't seen any other tools
that do this good of a job against of
diffing against the live state of the
cluster when you're using gitops you can
see a git diff that's still one layer
removed from what could from what is
deployed in the cluster it should match
but it doesn't always now if we do a get
pods in demo app
namespace we can
see three pods including the one that
just came up 16 seconds
ago hopefully that gives you an idea of
how powerful clue control is in terms of
it gives us that templating power of
Helm but without a lot of the overhead
and boiler plate that comes with it it
kind of gives us it's it's basically as
easy to get started with as customized
there's a few additional files we need
to use and we do have to install the
clue control binary given the power that
it brings I think that it's totally
worth doing
so pretty much any Green Field project
that I'm building out right now I try to
use clue control unless there's some
reason that I can't and I would urge you
to as well we'll see in the cicd section
that there is a built-in gitops
controller so we'll be able to take all
of that all of those capabilities that
we just learned about and apply them
automatically to our cluster using the
clue control gitops controller and
really take our
automation of deploying to different
environments to the next level another
important operational consideration with
kubernetes is ensuring that your cluster
remains up to date both the control
plane as well as your worker nodes
kubernetes the project releases updates
every 3 or four months generally about
three times a year and after a certain
period of time they stop maintaining
those older versions that means those
older versions won't get security
updates and as you build out on top of
kubernetes you're NE going to find a
feature that was released recently that
you want to leverage this module I'm
going to take a quick look at one
possible procedure for updating your
cluster and nodes safely this is a
procedure that I've used a number of
times in certain cases your managed
cluster may not provide the level of
control that is required to do this and
you may have to upgrade in place but if
possible I suggest using an approach
like this the first step of any upgrade
is to check and see if you are utilizing
any of the apis that may be removed in
the version you're upgrading to so as
the kubernetes apis Evolve they add new
versions old versions may get taken away
and so you want you want to make sure
that you do not have any of those older
resources deployed into your cluster and
if you do you should upgrade them to the
newer versions they have an upgrade path
where they wait a few versions before
they remove any deprecated resources to
allow you to move to the new version get
the new resource type get the new
resource version upgrade your resources
to unblock the next upgrade there's an
open source tool to that can help to do
that called Cube NT or cube no trouble
here's the GitHub repo for it I'm going
to run it against my clusters just to
verify that I'm not using any this will
scan your cluster check what API version
you're using uh and check all of the
kubernetes resources that are deployed
to make sure that none of those are
being removed and it will warn you if
they are once you're sure that you're
not using any of those deprecated apis
you want to upgrade your control plane
now your control plan can be ahead of
your worker nodes in terms of version uh
but it used to be by one minor version I
believe they've relaxed that to now be
two minor versions so you'll want to
upgrade your control plane version first
and then once your control plane is
upgraded you want to upgrade your nodes
there's two paths to doing this you
could either upgrade the nodes in place
usually what this means is that the
cloud provider such as in gke has a
concept of a node pool with multiple
nodes in it it will add a new node with
the newer version cordon and drain the
older node move which will move traffic
onto the new one and cycle through the
nodes in your node pool one at a time or
multiple at a time depending on the
configuration settings you've applied
the other option which I think is safer
is to deploy an entirely new set of
nodes using the newer version once those
have come up and are healthy you can
then shift the workloads that are
running in your cluster onto those new
nodes and once that is done you can you
can delete the old nodes this blue green
approach is safer because if something
goes wrong in that upgrade process it's
very easy to shift the workloads back
because you already have a set of
healthy nodes and you're much less
likely to encounter downtime due to
having an upgrade issue and not having
available capacity at the ready I'm
calling out here that some people do
away with this problem entirely by uh
moving to an entirely new cluster so
rather than upgrading your control plane
some people back up the state of an
entire cluster and shift it over if you
have a bunch of stateful workloads
running your cluster this is much more
difficult to do with no downtime but I'm
just calling out there that some people
feel that that is safer so not only just
shifting on to a new set of worker nodes
but also shifting onto entire entirely
new cluster is a different approach also
it's important to call out here that the
blue green approach that I'm talking
about of creating new nodes and
destroying the old ones is much easier
to achieve in a cloud environment than
in an on premises environment because of
that you're more likely to upgrade in
place with a longlived physical server
that you're managing on premises rather
than needing to have a whole new set of
Hardware to move your workloads onto and
so with that let's go ahead and upgrade
our gke class cler using this process
we'll start by navigating to module
13 the first step is going to be to run
Cube no trouble against our cluster
let's make sure we're pointed at our gke
cluster it will use your default Cube
config context so I'm running just the
cube NT command that should have been
installed by devbox here it's using Rego
which is a language that you can use to
specify types of policies it's checking
against all of the different kubernetes
apis that were deprecated in each of
these versions or that are planned to be
deprecated in the future we got no
warnings back so that means we are good
to go and there are no deprecated apis
being used so we can proceed to the next
step if we look at our kubernetes
cluster in the console and click into
it we can see I am on version
1296 then we want to list the available
versions that we can upgrade to gke
maintains three release channels there's
a stable which upgrades the most slowly
regular a bit faster and Rapid has even
more versions available as you can see
only the rapid channel can you use the
1.30 versions so let's make sure that
our cluster is indeed using that rapid
version so we'll update the release
Channel
accordingly that runs the gcloud
container clusters command and passes it
the rapid Channel and let's pick one of
these versions that we want upgrade to
let's grab the default version for the
rapid channel that seems fine and let's
specify it in our task
here paste that
in and so this version variable is going
to get substituted in when we call our
container clusters upgrade command and
specifically I'm telling it to upgrade
the control plane so let's do that so
here it issued that command passing it
the
version It's warning me that this is
going to block other operations on the
cluster that's
fine now this is just upgrading the
control plane it shouldn't impact the
worker nodes at all so I wouldn't expect
any of my workloads to move uh and they
should continue running just fine while
this upgrade is happening if I reload
the page here on Google Cloud you'll see
that my cluster is now in an upgrading
State this will take a few minutes
behind the
scenes so after about 5 minutes that
control plan upgrade completed you can
see here this warning you can see here
this note that if Auto upgrade is in
enabled uh that node upgrade would
happen in the background and GK has been
around enough and has tested enough of
these upgrades that auto upgrade in
place for a node pool is generally
pretty darn safe but if you want to take
one extra degree of safety you can do
what I'm about to show you and provision
a new node pool on that new version and
shift the workloads onto it to do that
we're going to run the node pools create
command it's going to be the same
machine type as before two nodes within
it and pass at our cluster and Zone just
as a reminder previously we had just the
default pool now we have the default
pool and the updated node pool you can
see the versions are different because
the new node pool is going to use the
same version that the control plan is
using if we do kg get nodes within the
cluster we can see the four nodes here
uh three of them are ready and one of
them is
not now all four nodes are ready at this
point we want to shift the workloads
from the old node pool to the new one I
have this this command here to you can
do what's called coordinating a node and
that will apply a taint such that new
workloads will not be scheduled onto it
then you can issue the drain command
which will terminate all the workloads
on an existing node there's some add
additional options here that can help uh
if things are getting stuck around if
there's empty directory volumes that
would prevent a workload from being
deleted or getting stuck for another
reason you can add the force flag the
first thing that I'm going to do though
is to just cordin the nodes so if I just
want to coordin the two old nodes let's
do K get nodes let's do K get
nodes and then we'll issue a k
Cordon on that
node
and that node you can see that the
status has changed from ready to ready
scheduling disabled because this is now
Cordon new workloads will not be
scheduled onto it if I do a kg pods if I
do a kg pods D
wide you can see that these are
currently all scheduled onto the default
node pool but if I do a k roll out
restart on a
deployment as you can see they were now
scheduled onto the new node pool great
any workloads that you worried about
having downtime for you would roll out
restart and as those new pods are
scheduled because we've coordin the old
nodes they'll get scheduled onto that
new updated pool now just to force
everything else once you've moved the
workloads that you're worried about
downtime for you can issue this drain
command and specifically you can pass it
to force flag which is kind of like
taking a sledgehammer to it just saying
terminate all the pods regardless of
their current state so let's go ahead
and do that just to force everything
else
over it's evicting a bunch of PODS and
So eventually once you've restarted all
the workloads that you're worried about
downtime for the only things running on
your old node pool are going to be demon
sets and that's okay because we already
have one copy of that running on each of
our new nodes as well so we can delete
that node pool safely
so we can issue a g-cloud container node
pools delete we'll say
yes and at this point Google's going to
go
off and delete this node pool from our
cluster now a few minutes later the
original default node pool is gone we've
got our upated node pool here if we look
at the nodes in the
cluster we see only the two nodes
awesome and so like I said doing an
inplace upgrade can work and it will
cycle one note at a time however having
that additional capacity ready to shift
the workloads back to if something were
to go wrong is a nice Safeguard to have
okay we've reached the final module of
the course and this is the one that
takes a project from kind of a oneoff
hobbyist project where you're manually
deploying things into a more production
ready system where you have automations
that are enabling you to push your code
to get and have those changes be
automatically built into container aages
have those images be automatically
deployed into your clusters that's what
we'll be looking at in this continuous
integration and continuous delivery
section and specifically it allows us to
reach these higher levels of
capabilities where early on in the
course I showed you how to use the cube
C create command from the command line
we never want to be doing that in
production it's only really useful for
learning purposes the next level we
progress to in module 7 a manual Cube
control apply command we got our
configurations ready we apply them in
module 12 we defined our configurations
to be able to apply to multiple
environments however it was still a
manual application the next level beyond
that would be to run a cube control
apply or a clue control apply from an
automated pipeline like GitHub actions
or circleci and then kind of the next
level beyond that that has become a deao
standard for companies managing
kubernetes resources is something called
gitops and gitops is the idea that you
have all your manifest in G which we
already do however now you're
automatically syncing the state of that
repo into the cluster and applying those
manifests such that your cluster State
and your repo State maintain parity
automatically for continuous integration
we'll be using GitHub actions and
generally the types of things that you
would want to run in continuous
integration pipelines are things like
your test Suite so when people are
trying to merge new code from a pull
request into main you want to execute
all the tests that you have against
those to to make sure they don't break
anything things like linting and
validation as well you would generally
want to build your container images and
then push those container images to a
registry for your kubernetes clusters to
consume on the continuous delivery side
here we're thinking about how we get
those changes into our kubernetes
manifests and then how we apply those
kubernetes manifests to the Clusters we
also would want to validate that those
deployments are working as expected in
this case we're going to use clue
control and it's built in gitops
capabilities combined with a GitHub
action that automatically updates our
manifest within the git repo to achieve
this automation you could use something
like renovate bot to achieve this as
well I've implemented kind of a hacky
GitHub action that does a find and
replace on the specific versions that we
care about for the Manifest and so let's
jump over to our code editor and get
this working now GitHub actions for a
repo live in a top level. GitHub folder
within there there's a workflows folder
and any number of yo files in this case
I have a single workflow that I'm naming
image CI for a workflow you can specify
triggers so here I'm saying every time
someone pushes to the main branch in
this repo I want this workflow to run or
anytime someone pushes a tag that
matches this number do number.
number format so those will be my
production releases whereas I'm going to
deploy to staging with each push domain
and then I'm specifying this path key
here and this says only rebuild images
when the application
themselves change so because I've got so
much stuff in this repo I didn't want to
rerun this workflow every single time I
changed something in module 4 for
example so this says only run this
workflow when the module 6 files change
because that's where the applications
and their Docker files live within a
workflow you can specify any number of
jobs we're going to start with the job
that's going to generate the image tag
so this is going to be the tag that we
use for those container images and it
has just one output that output is the
image tag itself and then the second job
is going to take as an input that image
tag and it's going to build tag and push
all of our container images the reason
that I separated this as a separate job
is so that the second job can run in
parallel using this Matrix strategy so
we'll have five pipelines running in
parallel building our container images
all at once whereas the image tag
generation only needed to happen a
single time if you had separate image
tags for each of your services for
example you were able to release them
independently you might need to generate
an image tag specific to each service
and therefore they could live in the
same job the third job what I've named
here update tags and this job
specifically goes into the repo finds
all of the kubernetes Manifest that use
those tags and updates them before
creating a poll request such that I can
go in as a human review the tags that
have been modified and merge that pull
request to deploy to to production let's
look at the specifics of what's
Happening Here the very first step is to
check out my code and because I'm using
the git tags as a mechanism to generate
the image tag I need to use this fetch
depth zero this will ensure that the
GitHub action workflow has all of the
git tags available to it rather than
just the latest commit I'm then
installing task this task Runner that
I've been using throughout I want that
available in the runner because I've
actually defined the commands that are
executed by this workflow in task and
then I'm going to generate the image tag
here I'm specifying a working directory
so this is my module 14 directory and
specifically I'm calling the task
generate version tag task so let's take
a look at what that actually is
let me navigate to my 14 to module
14 we'll navigate to GitHub actions
within
that and you can see I've got this
generate version tag command let's
execute it so it output
05044 G and then a hash the command that
it's running is get
describe looking at all the tags and
finding the first parent of any
particular tag matching on this pattern
and so if I run get
tag you can see here are all the tags
I've applied in my cluster ranging up to
050 the most recent one is this tag and
so then when I do this get describe
command it starts with that most recent
tag it tells me I've made 44 commits
since that tag and then this is my
latest
Commit This 51b 89 and so this command
gives me a mechanism to have my image
tags
increment with each new commit on Main
and also anytime you have a release this
prefix will change and so this makes it
very easy for me to see from my image
tag what's the latest version on
production and how many commits away my
staging version is if I was on a commit
with a specific tag Instead This would
just return
050 okay so we generated our image tag
we stored that in a variable and then we
echoed that out into the GitHub output
at the key image tag
because we specified this output
specifically calling out the step that
we should grab it from that value of
05044 g51 would then get
passed into the next step this needs
command ensures that this job won't run
until the previous job has completed and
then we'll have one copy of this job for
each of these paths let's take a look at
what steps are going to be
run again we start by by checking out so
this will give me the code associated
with the event that triggered the
workflow I'm installing task I'm setting
up qemu or Kimu this is a Computing
architecture emulation capability such
that I'll be able to build both
amd64 and
arm versions of my container images I'm
then setting up Docker build X and these
are third-party GitHub actions that you
can pull in as you can see with just
these just a couple lines there is a
GitHub actions marketplace with all
sorts of third party actions that you
can take a look at and see if they meet
your needs and so if there is a action
that's available that meets the needs of
your particular workflow you can
leverage those open source projects and
avoid having to write a bunch of custom
scripts yourself so we're going to set
up Kimu we're going to set up Docker
build X we're then going to log into
dockerhub passing it a username and
token If this job is specifically
associated with our goang API we need to
set up go in order to build it we also
need to set up Co which is that tool
we're using to build the container image
only if this copy of the job is running
for our goaling
API and then finally We Run The build
image command we pull in that image tag
from the previous job we specify a
working directory of the path of the
particular copy of this job that we're
running and then we actually call out to
task running our multi-architecture
build task from that module we're
leveraging the work that we already did
in these other earlier projects to
execute this task and because we have
the same task Name Across each of our
services that's why we're able to run
this one command and have it work across
all of those different projects simply
by specifying a different working
directory one thing we're not optimizing
here is saving and restoring the docker
cache across GitHub action workflow runs
that's something you could do if you
wanted to speed up the build times have
it cach those Docker layers between runs
now if you recall when we issued these
build X multi-architecture build
commands they included a push to the
registry so that's why we don't have an
additional push step these tasks build
and push those images now the final job
that I talked about is this updates tag
job and this is where we want to take
the tag that we used for building these
images and update the corresponding
kubernetes manifests within our repo
here I'm saying that both of these
previous jobs need to complete before
this one will execute and then taking
the following tasks we check out the
code we install task this is where the
bulk of the work is done in this update
image tag step we get our tag from that
initial job and we run two tasks the
first one we update our staging tags and
this will run every single time this
executes whether it's on Main or from a
release and then if this workflow was
triggered by a tag then GitHub ref will
look like this it will save refs tags
and then have the tag number and if this
is true then we'll also run task update
production tags with the new tags let's
go look at these tasks and see how they
work I've got this task called update IM
update image
tags and it as it described recursively
updates tags and files with the
specified comment and so this looks this
takes an input of a path and then
recursively goes through every file in
the repo looking for a specific comment
to identify which lines to modify and
then replaces those with the version
specified I've included this particular
task file as exclude Ed because
otherwise the identifier comments that
I'm using here would get Modified by
itself so this is just a a way that I
can prevent that from happening and then
I run a series of commands this first
one is just error handling saying you
have to specify an identifier comment
and you have to specify a starting path
otherwise it won't work uh and so that
is just there to provide a help
statement for people to use this command
I'm then specifying out some information
and then this is where the actual
execution of the replacement takes place
I use the find command using the
starting path as the entry point looking
for any yaml file searching for using
grep the identifier comment and then
taking the output of those and looping
over them for each of those items as
long as the file is not within my
excluded files
list then I update that file using said
or stream editor I find the version tag
that exists and the identifier comment
and replace and replace the version with
the new
tag once I've looped through everything
those files will now be updated in place
because I Ed the - I command and we can
proceed I then have two additional tasks
which call this top task so first I
check that you have a new tag specified
as it is required and then I call the
update image tag specifying the two
inputs in this case the identifier for
staging is staging image
tag so looking for those across our repo
we can see within module 12 in my clue
control services directory specifically
in my staging doyo config I have a
version with a tag that looks like the
one I've been generating followed by
that identifier comment and so when I
issue this command it will find all of
these similar definitions and up update
them all accordingly so let's try this
locally also for my starting path I'm
using the git rev parse command to give
me the the absolute path of the root of
my git repo and so this allows it to
work regardless of whether it's on my
system and I've cloned the repo into one
location or it's on the GitHub action
Runner and it's cloned in another
location or it's on your system this
will still give you a proper starting
point to Traverse through your repo and
find all of these versions so let's try
this locally we'll start just by running
it this task failed new tag is required
because I didn't specify new tag it
didn't know what to update to and so
that error checking we had did its job
and so let's rerun this but we'll set
new tag equals whoar
baz here it looped it found all the yaml
files looped through and we see here it
tried to update all those files let's go
into this one and we can see that now
instead of the previous version it is
specified as Fubar baz across all of the
those staging configuration files if we
look at the production ones because they
used a different identifier comment it
would not have changed we can instead do
update production tags with Fubar baz
Bing it will Loop through and now the
production versions match that while the
staging versions are still on Fubar baz
this would work perfectly fine um but
does make a few assumptions around how
you're storing things but as long as you
followed the conventions of using these
identifier tags this a this is a
reasonable approach for updating tags if
we now jump back to our GitHub action
workflow so on every single run of this
workflow we're going to update the
staging tags to match on the workflows
triggered by release tags we're going to
update both the staging tags and the
production tags and so this allows us to
and so at this point those tags have
been updated but only local to the
runner within that git repo so now we
need to get those local changes pushed
back up to GitHub so that we can merge
them into Main and get them deployed and
so this final action is a third party
action called create pull request it
does require a personal access token you
can't just use the token associated with
the workflow a PR request against
whatever base Branch you specify in this
case main containing those changes and
so why don't I go ahead and make a
commit to the
repo and we can watch this workflow
happen and you'll recall that I have
this paths filter here so it's only
going to rebuild these images when I
modify something something in this path
so why don't I go into module
6 and I will create a trivial change to
the read
me I'll just add a
period now we can commit that and we'll
push
it and so if we go to the repo now under
actions you can see a new workflow run
has been
created we're starting out by generating
that image tag we then are running our
five build jobs in parallel if we click
into one we can see the tag that it
received was 0 05045 because now it's 45
commit since that latest release two of
our applications have now built and
pushed successfully let's go over to
dockerhub and see that it was pushed we
see this
version 05045 was just pushed a minute
ago awesome okay our build jobs have
completed after a few minutes and now
we're in that update tags job we can see
that it updat
our staging configuration files like we
would expect and now created a pull
request we should be able to go under
pull requests and see here the title the
tag is
correct and my personal access token
that's why it shows my name pushed the
latest to this branch and if we look at
the
changes it contained changes to all of
those staging configs just like we would
expect now because this was a push to
Main and not a push due to a release tag
that's why it only updated the staging
ones and so that showcases an endtoend
CI workflow for generating useful image
tags building all of our container
images across a parallel set of jobs and
then going and updating those tags
within our kubernetes manifests
automatically you'd obviously want to
have additional workflows for things
like running your unit tests and
integration tests but I just wanted to
focus on how we get code changes into
container images now we can shift Focus
onto our git Ops installation to get
those versions that are now represented
in that poll request into our cluster
when it comes to gitops there's two
names that people will always reference
Argo CD and flux CD those are both very
popular and very powerful projects
however I'm going to Showcase a third
approach using clue cuddle glit Ops one
because I think it's awesome and we can
leverage all of that multi-environment
configuration capability that we
showcased in section 12 and two because
I want more people to use this project I
think the developer experience is
actually better in many cases than or
Argo and because of that I wanted to
highlight it here and hopefully convince
you that you should use it as well the
concept behind G Ops as I mentioned
before is that you're going to have a
controller running in your cluster that
is able to pull updates from git now
that can be triggered via a web hook to
increase the speed with which updates
make it into the cluster that's not
super important the important piece is
that we have this operator which is able
to pull in updates automatically and
keep those updates in sync with the
deployed state of the cluster Within in
the clue cuddle giops subdirectory we've
got a few things defined we've got our
top level clue control file so we're
going to define a deployment just like
we did for our multicluster deployment
but in this case the deployment is
controlling the clue cuddle giops
controller we've got our two Targets
again staging is pointing to the COO
cluster and production is pointing to my
gke cluster the args that we're going to
pass into this deployment are just going
to be the cluster name and we've got a
discriminate using that cluster name to
enable clue control to properly prune
and delete resources the deployment
specifies we're going to start with our
name spaces we have a barrier and then
we're going to deploy our clusters so
Nam spaces here there's two Nam spaces
that clue cuddle uses for G Ops we have
our clu cuddle giops namespace as well
as our clue cuddle system namespace so
those will be deployed first and then it
will look into this clusters
subdirectory where we find the following
deployment and this is another
interesting thing about clue control
that we didn't look at in module 12 in
module 12 all of our deployments we're
referencing things in our file tree
we're referencing a subdirectory however
we can reference a git repo public or
private we could specify credentials to
access it here and so these
configurations don't even need to live
in our repo they can live in for example
the clue control repo and specify that
it should install the controller and the
web UI so let's go to this repo and see
what those contain we're also specifying
a tag directly it's leveraging gets
ability to have versions and releases
and serve us these files rather than
needing to pull those in locally so if
we go to this repo and then to the
install directory the two things it was
referencing were controller and UI so
the controller one is going to deploy
this and the web UI is going to deploy
this the web UI is a stateless
deployment that will allow us to
visualize the state of our clue control
resources and the controller is the
brains of the operation that's going to
actually be performing the command line
executions that we would have done
locally but now they're going to happen
inside of the cluster so these are kind
of the system components and then we
have two additional subdirectories we've
got the all subdirectory so this is
anything that's going to be common
across our staging and production
environment would live in here within
that you we specify a custom resource
called a clue control deployment this is
how we tell clue control about our
project specifically we say here is the
repo on git and I want you to look in
module 14 my current module to find the
resources I care about and so by
specifying this clue control is going to
be able to manage itself via git Ops I
want to Target the cluster name
specifically and then I want to pass
that in as I deploy this such that it
will be usable as an argument these two
options allow the controller to then
clean things up if I were to delete the
resource from if I were to delete the
resource from my git repository and so
this is going to be shared across all of
our clusters with the only difference
being it will get a a different cluster
name specified from the argument that I
pass it back to our clusters deployment.
the final piece that we're going to
install is based on the cluster name one
of which will be staging and one of
which will be production we're going to
install either of these two deployments
this deployment is pointing to the
module 14 subdirectory these deployments
are going to be pointing to the module
12 directory and will control deployment
of our application itself just like we
did in module 12 but now in an automated
fashion now I know that might been a
little hard to follow with which
elements the clue control deployments
were managing so I drew this diagram to
help hopefully clarify things on the
left hand side we see the two clue
cuddle deployments the first of which
we're naming clue cuddle giops this is
going to be managing itself as well as
the clue cuttle controller and web UI
deployments and finally it will manage
the clue cuttle deployment referencing
our demo application deployment from the
other module by including itself in this
deployment now we can manage clue cuttle
via giops that second clue cuttle
deployment demo app references our
module 12 directory and so it will be
deploying our demo app clue cuddle
deployment that includes our thirdparty
dependencies the postgres cluster and
all of our first-party services will'll
manually deploy the clue cuddle giops
deployment one time it will then install
the second clue cuddle deployment which
will then in turn deploy all of our
applications let's go ahead and deploy
these two gitops controllers into the
staging and production class clusters
we'll start with staging I went ahead
and cleaned up the name spaces and
resources that we had deployed manually
for moduel 12 such that we would have a
fresh slate and we should be able to now
deploy into this navigating into our
module 14 into the clue cuddle get Ops
directory we can see we have four tasks
here the first one is to deploy into the
production cluster second one is to
deploy into the staging cluster let's
start with staging this just calls a
clue cuddle deploy passing it the
staging
Target we'll say
yes if we list our clue cuddle
deployments across all our Nam spaces
we've got our git Ops deployment uh this
one looks like it has finished deploying
it was successful this includes two pods
within the clue cuddle namespace the
controller this is where all of the clue
control logic is being applied and then
the web UI which we can actually use to
investigate and look at how these
deployments are progressing when we
deployed this a random password was
generated which I can get out of the
kubernetes secret using this command
I'll copy that and then I'll port
forward to the service in front of that
web UI so that's service clue cuddle web
UI and the clue cuddle system namespace
on Port 880 now I can go to Local Host
880 and log in with admin and that
username that I just copied and we can
see here's the gitops deployment it
looks like it's healthy you can see it
includes both the commands that I issued
via the command line so that's this path
it deployed two minutes ago and then and
then here are the deployments that will
be issued by the controller looks like
our demo app is still reconciling you
can see the node API is up the DB
migrator is crashing likely because the
database is not up yet okay it just came
up 38 seconds ago so hopefully the next
time that DB migrator restarts it should
connect
successfully that will enable the goang
API to come up and then our react Cent
to successfully start up as well once it
detects all of the necessary
backends I'll also create that secret
for our load generator python now if
this were a real project rather than
manually creating that image pull secret
I would store that in Google Cloud
secret manager and use external Secrets
manager like we showed in an earlier
module to pull those values in
automatically to our cluster and then
those non-sensitive external secret
configurations could live within the git
repo alongside the rest of our
configuration that way there would be no
manual steps after that initial
deployment and now a few minutes later
after all of those bootstrapping steps
have taken place all of our service pods
are now healthy we can find our external
IP edit Etsy
hosts this was our staging
cluster navigate to our staging URL and
there's our application completely
bootstrapped via gitops let's take
another look at that web
UI refresh the page I'm going to just
revalidate now that our application is
healthy we've got a healthy validation
State it's telling me that my reconcile
failed I think it's because it timed out
on that initial run let's try it
again it's still showing an error
here specifically for
the traffic dashboard Ingress route now
this error appears to be with something
with how the helm hook associated with
the traffic Ingress route for the
traffic dashboard is being applied let
me try manually deploying module 12 to
see if that resolves the
issue deoy
staging and that's one interesting thing
about the clue control giops model is
that it's meant to enable you to use
both the in-cluster controller in
conjunction with the CLI whereas flux
and Argo generally discourage that
practice by default if you manually
apply a change the gitops controller is
not going to revert that unless you have
specifically told it to or upon the next
upon the next time you push an update to
your git repo then it would revert those
manual changes and apply whatever
configuration you've pushed to the git
repo refreshing the web UI we can see
now that we have a command line push
here that was deployed 1 minute ago and
everything appears healthy let's rerun
our deployment ah I could have just
rerun that deployment on the server side
most likely and it would have succeeded
we'll try that in the production cluster
and so we've got our staging cluster
deployed now let's deploy our production
cluster clue cuddle deploy pass it the
target say
yes all right let's take look at that
web UI as the two clue cuddle
deployments come online this is a random
password that was generated so it'll be
different than the staging password you
can see the gitops clue control
deployment we deployed it first through
the command line and then the first
gitops reconciliation was successful we
can watch the logs of this demo app
production deployment going through it's
waiting on that migrator job which is
crashing until the postgres cluster
comes online looks like our database is
healthy our migrator job has completed
our two replicas of our goang API are
coming
online now I'm going to delete this pod
so it'll
restart and we've got our healthy
Services let's get our
service our external IP put it in Etsy
hosts navigate to our domain
and there we go our our production
application is now deployed via giops
let's check the web UI and see if that
same issue that happened on staging
happened in
production it looks like it did when I
click validate it checks that the target
is ready and it is true now let's click
deploy the controller should rerun that
deploy command behind the scenes and
everything should come up healthy there
we go we got a check mark at this point
at this point these clue cuddle
deployments will check for new
configurations on GitHub and rerun those
deployments every 5 minutes as
specified in their configuration and so
it will automatically pull in new
updates to demonstrate this we can go
here to demonstrate this we can go here
and merge this pull request that was
generated automatically by our GitHub
action and we should see an upgrade
across all our services on
staging from this version to that
version looks good let's go ahead and
it we'll switch over to our staging
cluster just to confirm the versions
that we're currently running with let's
do K get
podo we can see it was indeed using that
version now I could wait for this next
iteration of this or I can go ahead here
oh it looks like it has detected a new
version and run it on the GI op
side now once that 5 minutes has elapsed
this will rerun and we should get that
latest version updated I can also skip
that by going ahead and clicking the
deploy button let's go into our cluster
we'll do
K9s and it looks like that new version
must have been detected because we've
got new pods coming online
and see all of our pods have now
upgraded to the latest version let's
just confirm
that we're now on version
05045 and we can see that this was just
deployed 40 seconds ago
and so that just showcases making a
change in our git repo and having that
automatically be reflected in the n in
the Clusters so now instead of having to
deploy stuff manually we can just make
those changes in our git repo and those
will then flow automatically into the
cluster at the next iteration of that
deploy one aspect of our GitHub action
that we didn't
demonstrate was the trigger based on a
release event so now that we've made it
all the way through the course we've got
everything up and running
our gitops controllers are active we've
got our cicd set up I'm going to tag a
release we'll go here to the releases
page say draft new
release this is going to be the 1.0.0
release we'll create a new tag when we
publish
it and we will click publish this is
going to create the 1.0.0 tag we should
be able to go to GitHub actions and
see we now have a GitHub action running
our image CI workflow based on that
tag and now because of how we set up
that generate image tag command using
get describe we'll see here that the
image tag that's getting used for our
container images is
1.0.0 now that the images have been
built and pushed we're updating the
tags with that complete we see this
autogenerated pull request updating the
image tags to
1.0 you'll notice that it is updating
both our production tags as well as our
staging tags which is what we want we
want to be running this image across
both
environments we can merge
this we can go to
staging redeploy here
we can go to
production and redeploy
here we can see that our pods updated a
couple of minutes
ago let's check the version on
it and there we can see that our pod is
running that up updated 1.0.0 version in
production I expect it to be the same in
staging both of our apps are up and
healthy we can hit either one from the
browser and so with that we've got a
fully automated pipeline for making code
or configuration changes and pushing
those to get and having those changes
make their way into the appropriate
environment building that container
image pushing it to its registry
updating the git manifest and then
having our G op controller automatically
pull that in to the cluster and update
it State this gives us that powerful
familiar workflow where now we can push
code to Main and have it automatically
deploy to staging the one thing we would
need to change is rather than creating a
pull request from our GitHub action we
could commit those staging image changes
directly to main I just wanted to use
the pull request option to Showcase how
you could have a manual human in the
loop if you wanted
to but now you've got a really robust
git Ops based workflow that you can use
across any number of clusters within
your organization before signing off I
do want to call out a few additional
topics that could serve as logical next
steps as you continue to build your
kubernetes knowledge there's a few
networking topics that would be worth
looking into we learned about kubernetes
networking and how to get traffic into
your cluster and how to communicate
between services but there's a lot more
depth you could explore there I look at
the various cni plugins and the
trade-offs between them as as
potentially how to handle networking
across multiple clusters and optimizing
your network for maximum
scalability Additionally you could look
at Network policies and how they can
help you secure your your cluster by
defining the specific Network paths that
should be allowed for egress and Ingress
between and amongst your services and
then thirdly service meshes there's
tools like ISO and linkerd that can
provide a ton of networking capabilities
they'll give you Mutual TLS automated
retries and some additional
observability with no application code
changes on the workload optimization
side you should learn how to tune your
services with the appropriate level of
resources there's going to be a balance
between optimizing your resource
utilization and cost efficiency while
also achieving application stability in
order to do this you'll need to
understand the resources that your
applications consume under different
load patterns there's some tools that
can help with this like Goldilocks and
krr and you can use those to monitor
your applications and they'll provide
recommendations
about the resources that you should be
requesting I would also look at Auto
scaling throughout the course we had a
static cluster size and a fixed number
of replicas for all of our workloads
however within kubernetes you can scale
at both the Pod or the cluster
layer the horizontal pod autoscaler is a
component that allows you to scale the
number of replicas in a workload up or
down this can be based on CPU usage or
other custom metrics and then the
cluster autoscaler or there's an open
source project called Carpenter allow
you to scale your cluster by adding and
removing nodes based on the Pod
scheduling demand speaking of scheduling
we mostly let the default scheduler do
its thing with the exception of in
module 13 where we shifted some workload
from the old to the new node pool while
performing an upgrade you could look at
using node affinities taints and
tolerations or custom schedulers to
influence where pods get scheduled
within your cluster to ensure that
you're designing your systems for high
availability resource efficiency and to
meet whatever specific application
requirements you may have have as you
start running kubernetes in production
you're going to need to understand and
Implement some sort of Disaster Recovery
plan in case something goes wrong tools
like Valero and cast and K10 can help
with this if you're using gitops like we
did in the course then your cluster
State should be stored in Version
Control but any stateful applications
you're running will need to have an
appropriate backup and Recovery Solution
and you should be testing that solution
periodically to make sure it still works
finally we talked about operators in
module 8 and how you can extend the
kuber API but didn't dive deep into
actually doing so within the course
taking those ideas and building out a
custom operator of your own is another
great way to take your kubernetes skills
to the next level and with that you've
reached the end of the course if you
made it this far my hope is that you
feel ready to deploy and operate your
applications on kubernetes to briefly
recap we started by building our
foundational knowledge of kubernetes we
learned about the history and
motivations for the system explored the
built-in capabilities learned how to use
Helm to deploy applications we then took
that knowledge and deployed a
representative demo application along
with a variety of useful tooling into a
kuber Denis cluster finally we explored
what happens after your app is deployed
how do you debug how do you deploy to
multiple environments and how do you
automate the process of getting code
into your cluster with automated
pipelines and giops my goal is for this
course to become the go-to resource for
people who want to learn kubernetes
effectively if you found value in the
course consider sharing it with your
colleagues at work or with your Network
on social media if you do so please tag
me I'm @ Sid Palace on Twitter or you
can search Sid Palace on LinkedIn also
if you want to connect with others
who've completed the course come join my
Discord Community there's a link in the
description and we can continue to talk
about all things kubernetes remember
kubernetes is a vast and evolving
ecosystem hopefully this course has
given you a solid foundation but there's
always more to learn and remember just
keep building